<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Strong Opinions, Weekly Held</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/</link><description>Recent content on Strong Opinions, Weekly Held</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Asanka Herath</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 12:34:41 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://xn--izc.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Have-Loop</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/have-loop/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 21:45:28 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/have-loop/</guid><description>Have-loops are positive feedback loops which cause unsustainable
concentration of limited resources. Once you learn to recognize them,
you will see them everywhere.</description><content:encoded><figure><img src="./have.png" alt="The have loop is a positive feedback self-loop showing the effects of possessing something of limited supply."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">The have loop is a positive feedback
self-loop showing the effects of possessing something of limited
supply.</figcaption></figure><p>This is the Have-loop.</p><p>Positive feedback loops are neither new nor rare. The ones we are
concerned with, however, are those where possessing one thing leads to
possessing more of the same thing. Even more specifically, the have-loop
concerns itself with possessing something that is in<em>limited
supply</em>. Such a loop leads inevitably to<em>concentration</em> of
said resource.</p><p>If we consider<em>education</em> to be a profit-center<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> as
is the case in the United States, then education becomes part of a
have-loop across generations. In other words, the passage of time will
concetrate education on a shrinking educated class.</p><p>One example of this is wealth – because wealth begets wealth.
Inevitably this leads to concentration of wealth to an increasingly
smaller group of people<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>. There is no natural equilibrium
state absent external regulation.</p><p>Have-loops are inherently unsustainable. Have-loops inherently lead
to concentration of resources.</p><p>Wherever society allows a have-loop to exist, inequality will
inevitably grow.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>The terms “cost-center” and “profit-center” typically
refer to businesses. But they can also apply to societal policy where as
a society we decide that certain things should be done for profit while
certain other things should be available to everyone.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p>People tend to focus on income inequality, which is an
important factor. But another factor that drives extreme wealth
concentration is hyper-extraction. Much like extraction of natural
resources, hyper-extraction can also be directed towards individuals and
entire demographies. Measures of income equality will eventually fall
against another’s ability to enact hyper-extraction.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>When Your Feature Gets Someone Hurt</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/when-your-feature-gets-someone-hurt/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/when-your-feature-gets-someone-hurt/</guid><description>If Google Photos incorrectly tags a photo, what’s the worst that
could happen?</description><content:encoded><figure><img src="./album-of-ruins.jpeg" alt="An old photo album containing pictures of ruins. (Generated with Gemini)"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">An old photo album containing pictures of
ruins. (Generated with Gemini)</figcaption></figure><p>A story making the rounds recently opened some disturbing
implications. The New York Times ran the story as<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/27/technology/israel-facial-recognition-gaza.html">Israel
Deploys Expansive Facial Recognition Program in Gaza</a> which says in
part:</p><blockquote><p>To supplement Corsight’s technology, Israeli officers used Google
Photos, the free photo sharing and storage service from Google, three
intelligence officers said. By uploading a database of known persons to
Google Photos, Israeli officers could use the service’s photo search
function to identify people.</p></blockquote><p>Whether this particular use of Google Photos is compliant with the
usage policy is irrelevant. Those are concerns for PR firms and lawyers.
Google Photos is a consumer product. People use it for tagging their
family and friends in their vacation photos. The product works pretty
well for this purpose.</p><p>The humanity behind the product developers and those who are
unexpectedly and unwittingly blindfolded and led away to some unkonwn
prison somewhere is an entirely different matter.</p><p>The intended usage of a product – especially software products –
matters greatly. People responsible for these features decide its fit
for purpose based on this intended usage. From their point of view, a
mislabelled photo is an inconvenience; possibly a funny one. The error
thresholds were never decided based on whether someone could lose their
life for it.</p><p>Some developer wrote a conditional branch without giving it a second
thought. And now it decides the fate of a human life. That’s quite the
turn of events.</p><p>There’s no moral here. People are going to use your products in ways
that you never intended. I bet the people who designed coins have no
idea the extents to which those coins were flipped for. And so it
goes.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Secret Life of Systems</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/secret-life-of-systems/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 17:59:29 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/secret-life-of-systems/</guid><description>&lt;p>Lifecycles of software systems that solve real world problems can be
broken down into distinct phases based on where it is with respect to
the problem and the eventual solution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This article presents a taxonomy of these phases that should help you
understand how each part of the lifecycle fits together.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><p>Software systems aim to solve real world problems. They implement
some behavior that the authors of the system believe would address the
problem.</p><p>For non-trivial systems the coupling is imperfect between the real
world problem, the problem as understood by some group of people, the
perceived solution, the solution as it is actually implemented, and the
solution as received by the users.</p><p>The diagram below illustrates this phenomenon.</p><figure><img src="./lifecycle.png" alt="Software systems lifecycle. (Described in prose below)"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Software systems lifecycle. (Described in
prose below)</figcaption></figure><p>The software<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> system life-cycle begins – as most
things do – in the real world.</p><h4 id="the-problem-p">The Problem (P)</h4><p>There is a problem that affects some group of people<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>.
Let’s call it<strong>P</strong>.</p><p>We know these problems exist by their symptoms. For example people
might just feel something isn’t pretty great or that things could be
better if only we could figure out how.</p><p>Beyond that a precise and comprehensive definition of the problem
doesn’t exist. This might seem like a strong claim, but it comes down to
the fact that everything involving people is complicated.</p><h4 id="the-model-m">The Model (M)</h4><p>So people set out to understand the problem deeper. Experimentation,
user studies, interviews, observations, are all things that we do to
conjure these invisible problems into existence. We go probing for
symptoms to understand what might be causing them.</p><p>Based on these we develop and a model of the problem. The model may
be laid out for everone to see or it could be in someone’s head.</p><p>Let’s call this<strong>M</strong> for<em>model</em>. The model is
the entirety of our<em>understanding</em> of the problem. It is a
prerequisite before we can theorize about …</p><h4 id="the-solution-s">The Solution (S)</h4><p>At first the solutions are themselves models – things that work<em>in theory</em> when evaluated against the model<strong>M</strong>,
but yet to be verified against the real world problem<strong>P</strong></p><p>The models of solutions – let’s call them<strong>S</strong> – are
what we think will address what we assume is the problem. Depending on
the level of rigor, we will draw little diagrams, write design
documents, shop our ideas around, discuss alternatives, collaborate and
refine these solutions.</p><p>Eventually or during this process we will put something together that
works somewhat.</p><h4 id="the-implementation-i">The Implementation (I)</h4><p>So an implementation comes together – let’s call it<strong>I</strong>. The difference between<strong>S</strong> and<strong>I</strong> stems from practical matters. Time, resources,
technical limitations, all affect how much of our model solution<strong>S</strong> we can implement. The result is often different from
what we thought we would eventually have.</p><h3 id="deployment-d">Deployment (D)</h3><p>Whatever solution we put together is useless unless we take our
masterpiece to those who are experiencing the problem – the users.</p><p>The likelihood of a non-trivial solution reaching its entire intended
audience is low. The implementation may not be received in the same
spirit in which it was built.</p><p>And often, this is the point at which we will find out how much our
solution matches the needs of the real world.</p><p>They way in which our implementation<strong>I</strong> interacts
with the real world is – the deployment<strong>D</strong>.</p><hr/><p>Much like the subject at hand, systems lifecycles don’t follow neatly
delineated phases as described. Real systems typically exist in all
phases simultaneously. Understanding the question is a continuous
process. Plans change all the time. As any engineer will tell you, what
tools and resources are available are<em>also</em> part of the problem
statement.</p><p>But there are a few key observations that you can make from this
model:</p><ul><li><p><strong>We lose information at every phase</strong>. Our model of
the real world problem is guaranteed to be of much lower fidelity than
the real thing<a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a>. Our model solution is going to fall
short of addressing our model solution. Our implementation will not
match our aspirational solution. And whatever we manage to get in users
hands isn’t quite working the way we thought it would.</p></li><li><p><strong>Understanding the problem is a continuous
process</strong>. Every phase of this lifecycle brings with it new
insights into what it is we want to achieve and what we are working
with. Each new insight changes our problem statement, solution, and
eventually implementation and deployment.</p></li><li><p><strong>Understanding the problem must be deliberate</strong>.
Given that the deployed solution isn’t quite a match for the real world
problem, we need to ensure that we have the right measurements and
probes in place to understand this mismatch – be it telemetry, user
satisfaction surveys, interviews, or whatever else.</p></li></ul><p>Whenever we are holding some concept, being conscious about where in
the lifecycle that thing fits helps us get a sense for the level of
maturity of the concept and where you need to be to solve the
problem.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>The concept applies equally to non-software systems – as
long as they aim to solve real world problems.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p>Problems that we are interested in are those that affect
people. They tend to by squishy and ill-defined. Problems that are
defined entirely in the theoretical relam don’t fall into the model that
we are going to discuss. Theoretical subproblems like that are what we
use to construct solutions for the evolving squishy problems that we are
discussing here.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn3"><p>… which is why it is called a “model”.<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Why I Hate Carousels</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/why-i-hate-carousels/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 12:54:46 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/why-i-hate-carousels/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Don’t use carousels in your UI.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Instead, if you must stick content into little cards, let the
horionztal layout wrap to additional lines.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you end up with too many horizontal lines of content, then you
definitely have too many items that can be accessed via a horizontally
panning UI. You need a different UI altogether.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description><content:encoded><p>A carousel interaction pattern looks like this:</p><figure><img src="./dell.png" alt="A screenshot of dell.com from Nielsen Norman Group’s article on effective design of carousels."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">A screenshot of dell.com from<a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/designing-effective-carousels/">Nielsen
Norman Group’s article on effective design of
carousels</a>.</figcaption></figure><p>Basically it’s a layout pattern where one starts out positioning
content in vertical blocks. Some of those blocks are going to have
content arranged in horizontal blocks.</p><p>So far so good. You might think this will result in a layout that
roughly looks like this:</p><figure><img src="./vertical-and-horizontal-layout.png" alt="A layout consisting of vertically arranged blocks. One of the blocks contains a set of horizontally arranged blocks."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">A layout consisting of vertically
arranged blocks. One of the blocks contains a set of horizontally
arranged blocks.</figcaption></figure><p>This is a pretty common block structured layout. So common in fact
that most block structured layouts will flip orientation by nesting
level. If you nest a layout block inside a block that has vertical
layout then the inner block will automatically switch to doing
horizontal layout.</p><p>Notice that the entire layout fits snugly within the viewport.</p><h3 id="layout-runneth-over">Layout Runneth Over</h3><p>Interesting stuff happen when the layout doesn’t fit inside the
viewport. When it doesn’t fit vertically, obviously you’ll have to
scroll up and down to see the whole thing.</p><p>However, if<em>only the horizontal block doesn’t fit</em>, that’s
when the carousel pattern kicks in. So now things start looking like
this:</p><figure><img src="./layout-with-overflow.png" alt="The layout no longer fits within the cofines of the viewport."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">The layout no longer fits within the
cofines of the viewport.</figcaption></figure><p>How do you construct a UI affordance that lets people pan around
this? Of course you use … wait I already mentioned it ..<strong>pan</strong>. Maybe use scroll bars or just about any other
scrolling affordance.</p><p>So would it look like this if you scroll both horizontally and
vertically a little bit?</p><figure><img src="./shifted-viewport-position.png" alt="A viewport shifted a little bit both horizontally and vertically. The relative position of the blocks are still the same as before. Large portions of the viewport are now blank."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">A viewport shifted a little bit both
horizontally and vertically. The relative position of the blocks are
still the same as before. Large portions of the viewport are now
blank.</figcaption></figure><h3 id="sliiiiiide-to-the-right">Sliiiiiide To The Right</h3><p>To address all the blankness, the carousel pattern posits that the
the overflowing horizontal bits should be moved around independently of
the vertical bits. Like this:</p><figure><img src="./sliding-around-horizontally.png" alt="Vertically arranged bits move vertically. Horizontally arranged bits move horizontally."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Vertically arranged bits move vertically.
Horizontally arranged bits move horizontally.</figcaption></figure><p>We once again have the problem of affordances. There are many ways of
doing this. Most devices have some way of panning around both
horizontally and vertically. So the solution is obvious. Right?</p><p>If people stop here and implement that, then that would’ve been
over.</p><h3 id="uh-oh.-here-come-the-dots-of-stupidity">Uh oh. Here come the
dots of stupidity…</h3><p>Instead, they went with this:</p><figure><img src="./dots-of-stupidity.png" alt="Dots of stupidity. Little circles and left and right arrows. When you click/tap on the left arrow button, the carousal slides to the left. When you click/tap on the right arrow button, the carousel moves to the right."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Dots of stupidity. Little circles and
left and right arrows. When you click/tap on the left arrow button, the
carousal slides to the left. When you click/tap on the right arrow
button, the carousel moves to the right.</figcaption></figure><p>Let me summarize this interaction pattern.</p><ol type="1"><li>Use scroll bars, or whatever scrolling afforance to scroll up and
down to access bits that are above and below the viewport.</li><li>Click/tap on little circles with arrows to access bits that are on
either side of the viewport but only within the single sliding carousel
block containing the arrows.</li></ol><p>There’s a couple of problems with this:</p><ul><li>The obvious wonkiness of having two different methods of scrolling
horizontally and vertically.</li><li>Too easy to tap on the underlying “tile” instead of the
dot-of-stupidity.</li></ul><p>Carousel sympathizers explain the reasoning for this as follows:</p><ol type="1"><li><p><em>What if there was more than one horizontally sliding
thingies? How would one know which horizontally sliding thingy to apply
the horizontal scroll operation to?</em></p><p>This is a purely hypothetical problem that often doesn’t exist. But I
understand that UX designers have to account for the
possibility.</p></li><li><p><em>It’s okay because the user doesn’t always need to or want to
see everything in the carousal. Why bother them with details they don’t
need?</em></p><p>That’s nice, but how would the user know they don’t need to see the
thing without seeing the thing? It might be possible if all the visible
things in the carousel were irrelevant to the user then they’ll just
ignore the whole carousel.</p><p>But what about the very users who<em>are</em> interested? They need
to jump through hoops to look at the things that<em>are</em>
relevant.</p></li><li><p><em>What if there’s sooo many things in the horizontal slidey bit
that we can’t possibly accommodate all of it?</em></p><p><strong>Someone has to click on the little dot with the arrow enough
times to see each one incrementally. The number of items for which such
a UI works is far smaller than a UI where one scrolls past them using a
much more ergonomic interface.</strong></p></li></ol><h3 id="whats-better">What’s Better?</h3><p>Try wrapping the horizontal blocks so the page only overflows
vertically.</p><p>If there’s too many things to fit in a vertical overflow layout, then
there’s already too many things for anyone to click through individual
cards to see.</p><p>Just show the user a good subsample. If it whets their appetite, then
offer them a link to take them to a dedicated page.</p><figure><img src="./vertical-overflow-only.png" alt="Wrap the horizontal blocks so there’s only vertical overflow."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Wrap the horizontal blocks so there’s
only vertical overflow.</figcaption></figure><h3 id="in-summary">In Summary</h3><ul><li><strong>Don’t use carousels in your UI.</strong></li><li><strong>Instead, if you must stick content into little cards, let
the horionztal layout wrap to additional lines.</strong></li><li><strong>If you end up with too many horizontal lines of content,
then you definitely have too many items that can be accessed via a
horizontally panning UI. You need a different UI
altogether.</strong></li></ul></content:encoded></item><item><title>Inclusion/Equity and Evaluating Negatives</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/evluating-negatives/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 21:58:34 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/evluating-negatives/</guid><description>Evaluating properties like inclusion and equity of products can’t be
done through exhaustive enumeration of product outcomes. Instead we will
need to increasingly rely on the controls that we place how we construct
the products.</description><content:encoded><p>Privacy, security, inclusion, equity, accessibility, … all of these
have an interesting property in common. When evaluation products against
such questions you are usually trying to establish a negative.</p><h3 id="to-prove-a-negative">To Prove A Negative</h3><p>Proving a negative requires providing<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evidence_of_absence">evidence of
absence</a>.</p><p>If one wanted to<em>disprove</em> the claim<em>“all primes are
odd”</em> one only needs to prove<em>“some primes are even”</em>. The
latter can be accomplished by finding a single counterexample – the
number 2. On the other hand if one wanted to<em>prove</em> the claim,
they would need establish that all primes are odd. Another example is
the claim<em>“there are no vermin in this house,”</em> proving which
requires an exahustive search of the premises. Once again, disproving
the claim only requires a single piece of evidence – a mouse.</p><p>Going back to the beginning, asking someone whether a product is<em>secure</em>,<em>private</em>,<em>inclusive</em>,<em>accessible</em> etc… fall into the same category. Answering these
questions require proving that there is nothing<em>insecure</em>,<em>privacy violating</em>,<em>non-inclusive</em>, or<em>inaccessible</em> about this product. These questions are even worse
than the one about vermin from before because it’s not even clear where
to start looking. People who have spent their entire careers studying
the subject would find the criteria difficult or downright impossible to
evaluate.</p><p>Despite this apparent futility, there is hope.<strong>Knowing that
the criteria holds under a limited set of circumstances is sometimes
enough</strong>. Often it is the best that we can do.</p><h3 id="proof-by-enumeration">Proof By Enumeration</h3><p>In security and privacy parlance this limited scope is called the<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Threat_model"><em>threat
model</em></a>.</p><p>Absolute security is impossible, so one would start by establishing
the specific threats that they would like to deal with. For example when
considering the security of a networked application one could start by
drawing out a<a href="https://www.lucidchart.com/pages/data-flow-diagram">data flow
diagram</a> and then going over the different points at which data would
be at risk of being compromised. Enumeration of vulnerabilities and
threats in this way opens up the possibility of thoroughly examining the<a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/attack-surface">attack surface</a>.
Thus the previously intractable problem becomes finite.</p><p>As our understanding of threats improve, so does the effectiveness of
the threat model. Historically, understanding this kind of problem space
takes time and many – often costly – mistakes. The boundaries sometimes
only become known when someone exploits it.</p><p>Similarly, when evaluating a squishy concept like inclusion and
equity one would also start with a well defined scope that lends itself
to examination. Just like before, often we only learn where to look for
problems the hard way. So we come up with methodologies like carefully
curated<strong>dimensions of identity</strong>. Enumerations like that
give us a finite set of things to consider with our finite resources.
Additionally these methodologies also grant us a taxonomy with which we
can organize our hard earned knowledge on the topic.</p><h3 id="proof-by-enumerating-product-outcomes">Proof by Enumerating
Product Outcomes</h3><p>Enumeration based approaches establish clusters of<em>possible
product outcomes</em> which we can then evaluate individually.</p><p>As an example, a product that processes pictures of people can be
evaluated based on the outcome of handling pictures of people with
different skin tokes, gender expressions, body types, ages, hair and
accesories, visible disabilities, and lighting conditions. Coming up
with these outcomes can be laborious and expensive, but it is tractable.
Costs of curating suitably detailed test cases and data sets should
amortize across their potentially broad applicability.</p><h3 id="proof-by-construction">Proof By Construction</h3><p>But sometimes the set of outcomes do not cluster effectively or are
too numerous to exhaustively evaluate. In security this would be similar
to asking whether some software system is free from<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffer_overflow">buffer overruns</a>
– a question that is theoretically impossible to answer in general if
the method of construction is not amenable to analysis. The best we
could do is for suitably skilled persons to go through the code with a
fine toothed comb looking for potential problems; a task that is both
impractical as it is prone to error.</p><h3 id="proof-by-process-of-construction">Proof by Process of
Construction</h3><p>Instead we could try using programming languages that provide certain
safety guarantees:<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/memory-safe-programming-languages">memory-safe
languages</a>. These safety guarantees establish the memory safety of
the resulting behavior as a consequence of the method by which the
underlying software is constructed. Another method we can use is to
continue using an unsafe language<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>, but invest in
development practices like<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuzzing">fuzz testing</a> which give
us sufficient<a href="https://www.georgefairbanks.com/ieee-software-v37-n3-may-2020-testing-numbs-us-to-our-loss-of-intellectual-control">statistical
control</a> over the behavior of our software.</p><p><em>Inclusion and equity</em> can follow a similar paradigm where we
establish certain process requirements that also yield a favorable
outcome with a high likelihood. Google’s<a href="https://design.google/library/building-for-everyone">Building for
Everyone</a> outlines some of these processes criteria such as involving
a diverse group of people during the ideation and design phases of a
product, and involving a diverse group of people during testing. Once
again, these approaches don’t guarantee success, but have a much higher
likelihood of delivering a favorable outcome.</p><h3 id="amalgam-engineering">Amalgam Engineering</h3><p>Increasingly software systems are built as amalgamations of systems
that are themselves complex. The behavior of each constituent is
difficult to reason about let alone the behavior of the
amalgamation.</p><p>To establish some desirable property of the amalgamation, it becomes
necessary to progressively establish the same or minor properties of the
constituents.<strong>The point of establishing these properties is to
yield a simpler more tractable model of a system</strong> that we can
readily reason about. We can then infer or at least approximate the
behavior of the amalgamation based on the simplified models that we
derive of the contituents.</p><p>We don’t expect this situation to get better given that many of these
contituent parts will be ML models that are too complex for us to
understand. As enumerating product outcomes becomes less effective, we
will need to rely ever more on process criteria and governance of
construction to curb the product outcomes.</p><p>The accuracy of the resulting simplified models is all that we will
have to grasp in order to have some say how technology will govern us in
turn.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Continuing to use an unsafe language isn’t as dumb as it
sounds. Large tech companies with massive software estates are often in
the unenviable position of being unable to move enmasse to better
platforms due to the cost. Thus less than perfect interim measures are
not that silly.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Happy New Year 2024 and Year in Review 2023</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/happy-new-year-2024-and-year-in-review-2023/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 14:12:21 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/happy-new-year-2024-and-year-in-review-2023/</guid><description>Happy New Year Everyone! I hope everyone has a great year in 2024!
What We Are Leaving Behind I’m acknowledging but not going into details of the cruelty we are inflicting on ourselves in Ukrain, the Gaza strip, Myanmar, Niger, Burkina Faso, Azawad, Tunisia, Sudan, Columbia, Afganistan, Pakistan, Somalia, Democratic Republic of Congo, Nigeria, Iraq, Rwanda, Burundi, Mexico, Camaroon, Chad, Syria, Yemen, Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates, Ethiopia, Haiti, and pretty much everwhere.</description><content:encoded><h2 id="happy-new-year-everyone">Happy New Year Everyone!</h2><p>I hope everyone has a great year in 2024!</p><h2 id="what-we-are-leaving-behind">What We Are Leaving Behind</h2><p>I’m acknowledging but not going into details of the cruelty we are
inflicting on ourselves in Ukrain, the Gaza strip, Myanmar, Niger,
Burkina Faso, Azawad, Tunisia, Sudan, Columbia, Afganistan, Pakistan,
Somalia, Democratic Republic of Congo, Nigeria, Iraq, Rwanda, Burundi,
Mexico, Camaroon, Chad, Syria, Yemen, Saudi Arabia, United Arab
Emirates, Ethiopia, Haiti, and pretty much everwhere.</p><p>Instead let’s skip over to the the weirdness that happened in the
tech sector.</p><h2 id="generative-ai-has-entered-the-chat">Generative AI Has Entered
The Chat</h2><p>Educated people often make the mistake of underestimating the
disruption that can happen in an industry. In this case, we are talking
about generative AI and its disruption of the tech sector.</p><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transformer_%28machine_learning_model%29">Transformer
models</a> have been around for a while (since before 2017) but they
have mostly been a curiousity rather than a serious practical tool. It
held much promise and excitement but was considered to be a technology
that was in its infancy. The only real production workloads they handled
were around machine translation.</p><p>However, a sudden disruption happened in 2023 where:</p><ul><li>AI models become capable enough to give a somewhat convincing
approximation of intelligence. This led people to conclude that
generative AI is now ready for use in industry – a claim that is
debateable.</li><li>Generative AI models became accessible to the general public largely
in the form of ChatGPT though others followed quickly.<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a></li><li>People started incorporating generative AI into their lives and
businesses.<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a><a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a><a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"><sup>4</sup></a></li><li>This triggered an influx of financial investment in generative AI.<a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5" role="doc-noteref"><sup>5</sup></a><a href="#fn6" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref6" role="doc-noteref"><sup>6</sup></a></li><li>Which was followed closely by legislation that aimed to mitigate the
perceived harm of AI.<a href="#fn7" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref7" role="doc-noteref"><sup>7</sup></a></li></ul><p>All this in the span of a year.</p><p>I’m not directly involved in any ML work, so the way I experienced it
was:</p><ul><li>At the start of the year I had a couple of<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_language_processing">NLP</a>
projects that I had lined up to complete by the end of the year. The
tasks were somewhat complex and involved fiddling with a lot of
NLP.</li><li>By the end of the year the tasks were reduced to producing a prompt
for an LLM and then parsing its result.</li></ul><p>In addition to all the assistive coding tasks that are pretty much
production ready at this point, the transformation of a complex coding
task into simple English question and answer is kind of mind
blowing.</p><p>I’m waiting to see what the new year is going to bring in terms of
automation. We are truly living in the future.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p><a href="https://www.salesforce.com/news/stories/generative-ai-statistics/#:~:text=45%25%20of%20the%20US%20population%20surveyed%20is%20using%20generative%20AI.">“45%
of US population surveyed is using generative AI”</a> according to
Salesforce.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p>See McKinsey’s<a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/capabilities/quantumblack/our-insights/the-state-of-ai-in-2023-generative-ais-breakout-year">the
state of AI in 2023: Generative AI’s breakout year</a>.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn3"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/gdb/status/1599683104142430208">“ChatGPT just
crossed 1 million users; it’s been 5 days since launch.”</a><a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn4"><p><a href="https://advisory-marketing.us.kpmg.com/speed/genai2023.html#:~:text=Three%20in%20four%20business%20leaders%20%2874%25%29%20rank%20generative%20AI%20as%20the%20top%20emerging%20technology%20that%20will%20impact%20their%20business%20over%20the%20next%20year%20and%20a%20half.">“Three
in four business leaders (74%) rank generative AI as the top emerging
technology that will impact their business over the next year and a
half.”</a><a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn5"><p>Funding for AI-related startups were more than $65
billion in 2023. See TechCrunch’s<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/12/05/mega-deals-ai-funding-q3/#:~:text=Funding%20for%20AI%2Drelated%20startups,substantial%20portion%20of%20that%20figure.">‘Mega-deals’
could be inflating overall AI funding figures</a><a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn6"><p><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/company/press/generative-ai-to-become-a-1-3-trillion-market-by-2032-research-finds/">“Generative
AI to Become $1.3 Trillion Market by 2023, Research Finds”</a><a href="#fnref6" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn7"><p><a href="https://www.ncsl.org/technology-and-communication/artificial-intelligence-2023-legislation#:~:text=In%20the%202023%20legislative%20session%2C%20at%20least%2025%20states%2C%20Puerto%20Rico%20and%20the%20District%20of%20Columbia%20introduced%20artificial%20intelligence%20bills%2C%20and%2015%20states%20and%20Puerto%20Rico%20adopted%20resolutions%20or%20enacted%20legislation.">“In
the 2023 legislative session, at least 25 states, Puerto Rico and the
District of Columbia introduced artificial intelligence bills, and 15
states and Puerto Rico adopted resolutions or enacted
legislation.”</a><a href="#fnref7" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Thirteen Years</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/thirteen-years/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 16:30:52 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/thirteen-years/</guid><description>Some reflections from thirteen years at Google.</description><content:encoded><p>And just like that, another year sped by. It’s now been thirteen
years since I joined Google.</p><p>Of the people who started at Google that day just a hair over 50% are
still at Google. Glancing through the list<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> I
see a couple of folks who have left for greener pastures or pursuing
something on their own. Others who are still here have made their way up
the organizational ladders.</p><p>But for everyone on that list the Google of today is not the Google
we joined all those years ago. Someone who had been at Google much
longer than I have<a href="https://ln.hixie.ch/?start=1700627373&amp;count=1" title="Ian Hixie's blog: Reflecting on 18 years at Google">recently
published their thoughts</a> after they left Google. They had good
things to say about Google, but they also had some pretty harsh things
to say. I can’t comment about some of the specifics they mentioned but
the general sentiment checks out.</p><p>Avery Pennarun<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a> wrote a post that I think touches on
something relevant and important. The post is called<a href="https://apenwarr.ca/log/20190926" title="What do executives do anyway?">What do executives do anyway?</a>.
To save you a read (though you really should add it to your<a href="https://support.google.com/chrome/answer/7343019?hl=en" title="Read pages later &amp; offline">reading list</a>), the salient
points are:</p><ul><li>An executive’s<strong><em>only</em></strong> job is to<em>“enforce<strong>culture and values</strong> for their whole
organization.”</em><a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a></li><li>The executives set and enforce the values. The rest of the company
comes up with strategies accordingly.</li><li><em>“In a large organization, executives don’t set strategy.”</em> …<em>“It’s an illusion to believe you can enforce a strategy.”</em></li><li>Useful organizational values involve real tradeoffs.</li></ul><p>People have a common misconception that all employees of big
companies are constantly thinking of the bottom line. This is not the
case. Precious few teams can draw a clear line from their day-to-day
work to any measurable change in the company’s performance<a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"><sup>4</sup></a>. So
at an individual level, decisions are influenced by concerns much closer
to themselves: things like base pay, career, admiration of their peers,
and their own sense of accomplishment.</p><p>There are many things that an individual can work on to satisfy their
immediate concerns. The<em>culture and values</em> of a company help
narrow these options down to those that benefit everyone.</p><p>The reason I brought up the topic of culture and values is because
Google has a vacuum where an inspiring vision once was. Layoffs wreaked
havoc with the trust that people had for each other and themselves. We
are still<em>trying</em> to<a href="https://about.google/philosophy/" title="Ten things we know to be true">focus on the user</a>;<a href="https://blog.google/inside-google/message-ceo/january-update/#:~:text=important%20moments%20to-,sharpen%20our%20focus,-%2C%20reengineer%20our%20cost" title="A difficult decision to set us up for the future">sharply, in
fact</a>. But it is evident that company and its people are increasingly
acting out of self preservation,</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>There’s a mailing list for the folks who started on the
same day.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p>Avery is also a Xoogler.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn3"><p>The article goes into detail about ratifying good
decisions and arbitrating difficult decisions. But those are not
relevant to this discussion.<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn4"><p>You can, however, affect the stock price by getting
something really really wrong. Noone wants to be in this position
though.<a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Pillars And Governance Structures</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/pillars-are-governance-structures/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 20:18:23 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/pillars-are-governance-structures/</guid><description>Originally published on 2023 September 8. Revised 2023 November 12 with hopefully less rambling.
Re-orgs.
It’s a fact of life for large organizations. A popular metaphor making the rounds now is this concept of pillars. The metaphor makes sense to some extent.
A house without a foundation Let’s start with a picture of how a sanitized version of a pillar structure would look like.
A goal at the top and a bunch of pillars at the bottom.</description><content:encoded><aside class="note"><p>Originally published on 2023 September 8. Revised 2023 November 12
with hopefully less rambling.</p></aside><p>Re-orgs.</p><p>It’s a fact of life for large organizations. A popular metaphor
making the rounds now is this concept of pillars. The metaphor makes
sense to some extent.</p><h2 id="a-house-without-a-foundation">A house without a foundation</h2><p>Let’s start with a picture of how a sanitized version of a pillar
structure would look like.</p><figure><img src="./just-pillars-and-a-goal.png" alt="A goal at the top and a bunch of pillars at the bottom. No foundation."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">A goal at the top and a bunch of pillars
at the bottom. No foundation.</figcaption></figure><p>On the top is some kind of goal or an organization. In the case of an
organization we can think of organization’s mission as the goal. Pillars
support the goal.</p><h2 id="stage-2-subpillars">Stage 2: Subpillars</h2><figure><img src="./pillars-and-subpillars.png" alt="A goal at the top, a bunch of pillars holding it up, and then a bunch of subpillars. Still no foundation."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">A goal at the top, a bunch of pillars
holding it up, and then a bunch of subpillars. Still no
foundation.</figcaption></figure><p>Massive corporations can’t be organized around a handful of pillars.
We need more structure: subpillars.</p><p>The subpillars are holding up the pillars. Together all of them hold
up the goal.</p><p>Collectively what we are looking at is a system for organizing
people. One that is hierarchical and tree structured.</p><p>We all know this. Because that’s what org charts have always looked
like.</p><h2 id="team-topologies">Team Topologies</h2><p>In<a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/TeamTopologies.html">TeamTopologies</a><a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> Martin Fowler et. al. discusses
different kinds of software teams.</p><p>One can think of pillars and sub-pillars as being higher level
structures for organizing these teams. Individual teams at the
granularity at which team topologies apply are too granular for
pillars.</p><p>What I found compelling in “Team Topologies” were the concepts of<strong>Outcome Oriented teams</strong> and<strong>Activity Oriented
teams</strong>. These have always had names –<strong>project
teams</strong> and<strong>service teams</strong>.</p><p>Fowler’s article mentions</p><p>To put it in a nutshell,</p><ul><li><p><strong>Outcome oriented teams</strong> are teams that are
working towards something. They hope to achieve some sort of goal, and
once it is achieved the purpose of the team has been fulfilled and
typically people move on to other things.</p><p>Outcome oriented teams have specific measurable goals like…</p><ul><li>build a thing,</li><li>make specific qualitative change happen,</li><li>research something, or</li><li>achieve a sales goal.</li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Activity oriented teams</strong> are teams that perform
some sort of activity for the organization. They do things like keeping
the lights on, bug fixing, and occasional feature development. Activity
oriented teams are typically in the service of enabling an outcome.</p><p>Activity oriented teams have qualitative goals like</p><ul><li>uptime,</li><li>efficiency,</li><li>user-satisfaction, and</li><li>level of support.</li></ul></li></ul><p>There are more details and nuances and much hair-splitting. But the
gist of it can be understood without diving too far into the weeds. What
is important is that …</p><blockquote><p>Outcome oriented teams and activity oriented teams can mutually
depend on each other.</p></blockquote><p>Also …</p><ul><li><p>A single outcome oriented team can depend on multime activity
oriented teams.</p><p>For example, a team tasked with building a new service will depend on
multiple existing services that are under the purview of multiple
activity oriented teams.</p></li><li><p>A single activity oriented team can depend on multiple outcome
oriented teams.</p><p>For example, a team tasked with maintaining a critical service will
at times need to implement large changes or features, which require
multiple outcome oriented teams.</p></li></ul><p>Uh oh. Our organization is not tree-shaped anymore.</p><h2 id="its-a-graph">It’s a Graph</h2><figure><img src="./graph-shaped-dependencies.png" alt="Interdependencies form a graph, not a tree."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Interdependencies form a graph, not a
tree.</figcaption></figure><p>The problem is that the the thing we are trying to organize is not
tree structured. Each group has relationships that stretch vertically
along the reporting chain, and also horizontally across “enabling”
teams, support teams, infrastructure teams, or other teams that are
solving similar problems.</p><p>An organization especially at this level of abstraction cannot
represent all this complexity. A large number of free-floating small
teams interacting with each other won’t be very efficient<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>.
Nor is it conducive to goals at a large scale because that would require
a degree of cooperation that won’t appear spontaneously.</p><p>So we need to steer this pool of teams. It needs some structure so
that some higher level of management can coordinate a number of smaller
groups; so that they can collectively work towards a common but larger
goal.</p><p>With this newfound knowledge we can once again approach the pillars
but this time with goals and activities for the higher level teams.</p><h2 id="its-a-tree-again">It’s a Tree (Again)</h2><p>However, the leadership needs to figure out which of these
relationships to organize around.</p><p>This isn’t quite satisfactory yet because we can’t made things fit
into the pillar system. Once people get stuck on pillars everything
needs to be a pillar.</p><p>We can, however, stick teams into pillars. These teams would be
outcome oriented if they are stuck into outcome oriented pillars. It
follows that activity oriented pillars will need to be stuck into
activity oriented pillars.</p><p>So it’ll kind of look like this:</p><figure><img src="./all-together-now.png" alt="Big organization, goals, outcome oriented pillars, outcome oriented teams, activity oriented pillars, and activity oriented teams"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Big organization, goals, outcome oriented
pillars, outcome oriented teams, activity oriented pillars, and activity
oriented teams</figcaption></figure><p>And there you have it.</p><p>In reality, the structure can be made much cleaner once you start
asking each team what their goals are.</p><p>But the gist of it is you can’t plan teams or pillars until you know
what their goals are.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>I don’t believe the concepts introduced in<a href="https://teamtopologies.com/">Team Topologies</a> don’t apply
universally even across software companies. I work in one where it
doesn’t.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p>Even though in the aggregate, you can think of the open
economy as being a very large number of small “teams” with a very dense
network of interdependencies. Sure, it’s leaving people in poverty and
is killing the planet; but it still kind of works.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>A Good API: g9</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/a-good-api/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 19:29:31 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/a-good-api/</guid><description>Adding more knobs doesn’t make your API more powerful.</description><content:encoded><p>Once in a while an API comes around that makes me stop and and look
at what I’m doing.</p><p>Like many aspects of design, when it comes to APIs, what is not there
matters as much as what is. Engineers like to fiddle around with things.
So they like to add knobs and dials for fiddling around with things.</p><p>People say platitudes like good API design has to do with balancing
flexibility and simplicity. People throw around the word “simplicity” as
if people just need to be reminded of it and all will be well. “Simplify
your API” isn’t the same as “put on sunscreen.” It takes work. Lots of
work. Intentional work with the goal of simplifying because there is
little chance you are going to arrive at the right solution by
accident.</p><p>An example of a good API is<a href="https://github.com/bijection/g9">g9</a>.</p><p>Before you look at it, think about how you would construct an API
that:</p><ul><li>… allows you to draw a diagram on an HTML canvas – perhaps with a
limited set of drawing primitives.</li><li>… once the diagram is rendered, allows users to manipulate the
diagram by dragging points around.</li></ul><p>There are millions of ways of designing this. But g9’s approach takes
the cake. You can take a shortcut and have a look at their<a href="https://github.com/bijection/g9#docs">API documentation</a> or
their<a href="https://omrelli.ug/g9/gallery/">examples</a>. But
basically it is this:</p><ol type="1"><li>Tell us what your mutable parameters are.</li><li>Draw your diagram with based on the set of parameters.</li><li>…</li></ol><p>That’s it. That’s all there is.</p><p>Now, you can sit there and come up with a million knobs that you
claim makes the API more powerful. And you might be right – you’ll be
able to do more things with the API with the knobs you add.</p><p>But when you start treating simplicity as a feature, you’ll notice
that adding knobs isn’t the same as making a more powerful API. All
those additional knobs must be essentially invisible for people who
don’t need them. Otherwise every addtional knob will waste more of your
users’ time and energy for nothing.</p><p>The power of an API comes from letting users to express more with
less.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Point of a Strategy</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/the-point-of-a-strategy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2023 11:00:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/the-point-of-a-strategy/</guid><description>The only useful strategy is one that reduces risks.</description><content:encoded><p><strong>Q</strong>: How do you win a soccer match?</p><p><strong>A</strong>: Score more goals than the other team.</p><p>This is a dumb strategy, right? But why?</p><p>Compared to a more<em>reasonable</em> strategy like start preparing
with plenty of time to spare, invest in a good team, hire a good coach
and what not,<em>why</em> is scoring more goals a dumb strategy? That’s
because the bad strategy didn’t<strong>reduce risk</strong>.</p><p>The whole point of a strategy is to mitigate risk. One could imagine
gathering up a bunch of random people and somehow lucking out at the
game and winning it. You need a strategy if you don’t want to leave
everything to chance.</p><p>That’s why the next strategy you write down needs to account for
these:</p><ol type="1"><li><p>State your goal clearly.</p><p>A good goal should clearly articulate<strong>the outcome</strong>,
and<strong>constraints</strong>. E.g. MVP available for limited testing
(<em>the outcome</em>) by end of Q4 (<em>the constraint</em>).</p><p>It should be obvious to anyone when the goal has been reached. This
is by design, since there should not be any question of what you are
collectively trying to accomplish.</p></li><li><p>Identify the risks.</p><p>Mitigating risks begin by identifying them. Some risks are obvouls,
but still write them down because you need to address them.</p><p>Failing to meet the goal is an obvious risk, but why would you fail
to meet the goal?</p><p>A common reasons is simply that you need more time. E.g. you are at
risk of not meeting the constraints due to underestimating the amount of
work required.</p><p>Another reason could be technology you are using not performing as
expected due to bugs. Every part of your tech stack is a gamble. A part
that you don’t own is a specially big risk because you may not be able
to fix it or work around a problem.</p></li><li><p>Figure out how to mitigate the risks.</p><p>At risk of schedules slipping? Have intermediate deliverables and
milestones along the way. Instead of everything falling apart at the
end, you’ll know when things are not going to schedule much earlier in
the product life cycle. Knowing early means that you can address them
before failures snowball into a giant ball of trouble.</p><p>Unreliable tech-stack? Choose stacks that have a solid user base and
support structure. A project with bugs that are getting addressed is a
lower risk than one that hasn’t seen any updates in a year.</p></li><li><p>Stack up your goal, risks, and mitigations.</p><p>There’s your strategy.</p></li></ol><p>It’s not a strategy is risks are not identified and mitigated.</p><p>A common mistake is to write down a list of steps that, if followed,
achieve a stated goal. A good first step. But the unless the strategy
can<strong>reduce</strong> risk, it is not a useful.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Just Enough Technical Debt</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/just-the-right-amount/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/just-the-right-amount/</guid><description>Zero technical debt isn’t always the answer.</description><content:encoded><p>Zero technical debt sounds like a great target to aim for. In my
earlier developer days I strongly believed that all projects should go
for this target. At a company all-hands I heard from a senior engineer
that having zero technical debt is often not what we want. I felt
betrayed.</p><p>Why is it that zero technical debt isn’t what we want?</p><h2 id="memory-allocation-strategy-leak-all-allocations">Memory
Allocation Strategy: Leak All Allocations</h2><p>Let’s take a moment and think of a hypothetical program. If you knew
that your program ran once and terminated, would you go through the
effort of deallocating each individual memory allocation at the end? You
are about to end the process and drop the entire heap anyway. Cleaning
the heap at this point is a waste. For short-lived programs who’s memory
consumption is bounded and less than the available memory the more
efficient strategy is to just leak all memory.</p><p>One might wonder if such a strategy would break reusability. “Leak
all allocations” doesn’t mean that you shouldn’t call<code>free()</code> (or equivalent) in your code. It means that the
memory manager would treat<code>free()</code> as a no-op. This
principal also applies to garbage collected languages. After all, the<a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20100809-00/?p=13203#:~:text=Garbage%20collection%20is%20simulating%20a%20computer%20with%20an%20infinite%20amount%20of%20memory."><em>job
of memory management is to simulate infinite memory</em></a>. If you are
only going to use a finite amount of memory then you don’t need memory
management.</p><h2 id="what-does-just-enough-technical-debt-look-like">What Does Just
Enough Technical Debt Look Like?</h2><p>Some of the motivation for stopping short of perfect comes from the<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mythical_Man-Month">Mythical
Man Month</a>.</p><figure><p>For the human makers of things, the incompletenesses and
inconsistencies of our ideas become clear only during implementation.
Thus it is that writing, experimentation, “working out” are essential
disciplines for the theoretician.</p><figcaption><p>― Frederick P. Brooks Jr., The Mythical Man-Month: Essays on Software
Engineering</p></figcaption></figure><figure><p>The hardest part of the software task is arriving at a complete and
consistent specification, and much of the essence of building a program
is in fact the debugging of the specification.</p><figcaption><p>― Frederick P. Brooks Jr., The Mythical Man-Month: Essays on Software
Engineering</p></figcaption></figure><p>Software projects tend to be characteristically similar. Putting too
much effort into a project features you don’t need and polishing up code
that nobody will reuse is wasteful. It’s just a little bit harder to
know when you’ve crossed the point of diminishing returns where cleaning
up the code no longer makes sense.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Code As UI: The UX of config-as-code and everything-as-code</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/code-as-ui/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/code-as-ui/</guid><description>Configuration-as-code has the same usability issues as everything
else as code along with the same benefits.</description><content:encoded><h2 id="welcome-to-the-ui-review">Welcome to the UI review</h2><p>Your UX person comes up to you with the new mocks for the
configuration UI. It looks like this:</p><figure><img src="./blank-ui.png" alt="A UI mock where all the labels are text boxes, and the values are also text boxes. The button just “button”."/><br/><figcaption>
Your new UX.</figcaption></figure><p><strong>You</strong>: What is this? Is this modern?</p><p><strong>UX</strong>: That’s be beauty of it. The user can type in the
label<em>and</em> type in the value.</p><p><strong>You</strong>: And how would they know what the labels are and
what valid values are?</p><p><strong>UX</strong>: We will write some documentation on what the
labels and values should be.</p><p><strong>You</strong>: What about validation?</p><p><strong>UX</strong>: Hmm. That would be nice. But the UI doesn’t
really know what the valid values are.</p><p><strong>You</strong>: Come again?</p><p><strong>UX</strong>: The UI is neutral. Again, the valid labels and
values are documented.</p><p><strong>You</strong>: Is it a good document?</p><p><strong>UX</strong>: Let’s not get ahead of ourselves.</p><p><strong>You</strong>: Is it a single document?</p><p><strong>UX</strong>: We are thinking more along the line of leaning
into crowd sourcing. Like there will be some documentation, but really
the labels and values are consumed by the backend. We don’t really have
much control of that.</p><p><strong>You</strong>: So, the backend is responsible for keeping the
documentation up to date? How has that worked out before?</p><p><strong>UX</strong>: Not great.</p><p><strong>You</strong>: So, any good news here? Why are we doing
this?</p><p><strong>UX</strong>: Because it’s config-as-code. It’s the new
hotness.</p><p><strong>You</strong>: Say no more fam.</p><p>So here’s the thing. Config-as-code isn’t new. That’s how it was
before any GUIs existed. Anyone hows configured an old OS, and some new
ones, will tell you that the only way some parts can be configured is by
editing text files; sometimes using an esoteric editor called<code>vi</code><a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>.</p><p>Then there was a glorious age of GUIs. At some point they started
treating developers and sysadmins like real people. You might not
believe this, but they even did user experience testing to make sure
those sysadmins’ lives were as easy as possible. It was glorious.</p><p>And now, what’s old is new again.</p><h2 id="the-pros">The Pros</h2><p>There are in fact good reasons for config-as-code. Here’s a few:</p><ol type="1"><li><p><strong>No more opaque configuration</strong>.</p><p>Fancy UIs often mean that the configuration data goes straight into
an opaque configuration store somewhere. Sure it will come around and
affect the behavior of whatever it was that is being configured. But
that stuff usually doesn’t involve the user.</p><p>Usually the the platform doesn’t have much reason to keep
configuration a secret. So there will be some schema and some method to
storing and querying the configuration.</p><p>However when it comes to third-party or hosted services, this is not
always the case. The how the configuration is stored and how it is
reified into behavior is opaque.</p><p>With configuration-as-code (Can I call this CaC? That’ll be more
convenient.) the user is in control of storage. How else would they
write it down? The schema must necessarily also be made available to the
user.</p></li><li><p><strong>All the controls of source code</strong>.</p><p>Anyone who’s written some source code and used some source control
tool will tell you how useful source control can be.</p><p>Almost trivially you get:</p><ol type="1"><li><p><strong>History</strong> and all that comes with it like the
ability to revert back to known good states.</p></li><li><p><strong>Blame/Praise</strong> and attribution of changes to
specific authors – assuming there’s sufficient authentication and
authorization in place.</p></li><li><p><strong>Reviews/Approvals</strong> that verify that the changes
were correct and appropriate.</p></li></ol><p>Unless someone can be mandated to stand behind you and look over your
shoulder taking notes, none of that comes for free with a sysadmin at a
GUI.</p></li><li><p><strong>Audits, validation, automation</strong>.</p><p>Follows from the above. Now that the configuration is inspectable and
understandable, it is easily amenable to automation and validation.</p><p>One could argue that this was always the case. However, now the user
is empowered to do so with the same fidelity as the authors of the
system.</p></li></ol><h2 id="and-the-cons">And the cons</h2><p>The things that need<em>fixing</em> is usability.</p><p>We spent decades saying Fitt’s law this and “recognition over recall”
that, and then threw everything away. It’s time we put all that
experience into action.</p><p>Just because the configuration is in text files doesn’t mean that it
has to be authored that way. Even if it did, it is still possible to
substantially improve the UX there.</p><p>Why do people enjoy Mad Libs but wouldn’t enjoy writing the same
content from scratch? The answer is “recognition over recall”.</p><figure><img src="./madlibs.png" alt="The original Mad Libs book gave this example: “___________! he said ________ as he jumped into his convertible ______ and drove off with his _________ wife.” exclamation adverb noun adjective."/><br/><figcaption>
An example from the original Mad Libs book.<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mad_Libs">Source: Wikipedia</a></figcaption></figure><p>We can have the format and options documented somewhere and have the
user consult the document at every step of the way. This sound
reasonable at first. So people write things like “read all the
documentation carefully before attempting to configure the thing.”</p><p>But the amount of information that a human being can keep track of at
a given time is limited. What it ends up being is a tiresom sequence of
flipping back and forth between reference and implementation.</p><figure><img src="./reference-and-configuration-eyes.png" alt="Attention shifts from the reference to the configuration being edited and back; repeatedly."/><br/><figcaption>
Left to right to left to right …</figcaption></figure><h2 id="making-things-better">Making things better</h2><p>It turns out we already have some ideas on how to fix this, because
the same problems plague software engineering. Or I should say the other
areas of software engineering.</p><p>Here are several approaches I’ve seen in practice that make
config-as-code more bearable.</p><h3 id="language-serversautocomplete">Language Servers/Autocomplete</h3><p>Pretty much the only useful development in coding in the past several
decades is autocomplete. A good schema along with documentation can make
a huge difference. Try editing the VS Code settings file to see it in
action.</p><h3 id="templates">Templates</h3><p>As the Mad Libs example shows, templates are much easier and more
expedient than a blank empty document.</p><p>Other examples of templates include:</p><p>But templates in general only work the first time. So subsequent
edits to the configuration will have to contend without the help of a
template. This is a biggie since configurations can’t be updated when
updating their corresponding templates.</p><h3 id="alternate-uis">Alternate UIs</h3><p>We once used to have WYSIWYG UI editors. Now we have to write our UIs
as code in one of any number of frameworks that in turn try to reduce
the toil of writing UIs. It doesn’t have to be this way.</p><p>At least for configuration, just because the configuration is written
down as code doesn’t mean it has to be edited as code. The same UIs that
we once used can still generate those text files.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Vim is actually quite awesome.<a href="https://neovim.io">Neovim</a> is slightly more or less awesome
depending on who you are ask.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Promise Fatigue</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/promise-fatigue/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:03:16 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/promise-fatigue/</guid><description>Setting low but realistic expectations is better than setting high
but unrealistic ones.</description><content:encoded><ul><li>I’ll get it to you by the end of the day.</li><li>I’m working on it right now.</li><li>I’ll get it done today.</li></ul><p>Even though the word “promise” doesn’t appear in any of these, they
still represent a commitment you make to someone else. If you fail to
keep your promise, you will disappoint someone or more than one.</p><p>But if you fail to keep your promises, eventually, you’ll stop
disappointing people. That’s because they no longer expect you to keep
your word. Of course, by then, you would have irreparably damaged your
reputation – and people will no longer consider you as being
reliable.</p><p>Before making a commitment, always think about<strong>promise
fatigue</strong>. Setting low but realistic expectations is better than
setting high but unrealistic ones.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Loss of a Virtuous Culture</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/the-loss-of-a-virtuous-culture/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 17:13:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/the-loss-of-a-virtuous-culture/</guid><description>Luck isn’t enough. You need a culture of virtue.</description><content:encoded><p>Long ago, around 2011, we had an espresso machine in the Google micro
kitchen – or MK as we called it – near my desk. There were no baristas
at the time, so people made their own. Some folks thought we could use
more sophisticated coffee beans than they had in the MK. A designated
person would purchase these higher-quality beans using money that
everyone collected in a jar in the MK.</p><p>This cash jar was not locked. Instead, it was in a conspicuous
location, along with a note suggesting that people using the “good”
beans should consider dropping some cash there so that people could
continue purchasing premium beans.</p><p>One day, the cash in the jar went missing.</p><p>The response was swift. Donations poured from everywhere in the
office, offering to replace the lost cash. Noone speculated on who took
the money. Things were back to normal as soon as the incident was
reported. The cash jar was re-instated.</p><p>The cynic in me wondered why the money didn’t get stolen sooner. But
everything worked on the honor system at Google. And we were insistent
on keeping it that way.</p><p>As far as I know, the money never went missing again, though the cash
jar system went away as folks moved around inside the ever-expanding
office.</p><p>Cash isn’t used as much anymore. However, would a similar system work
now? We no longer place as much trust in each other as we did. We don’t
even know most of the people we see walking around. But something is
going on beyond that. Even if we did know the people, we are now more
attuned to insider risk – and justifiably so. As a result, there is more
of an air of distrust.</p><p>What would be the consequences of a breakdown in mutual trust among
employees? In<a href="https://brianlui.dog/2020/10/06/upside-decay/">“Upside Decay,”</a>
Brian Lui argues that such a breakdown in virtue limits an
organization’s ability to benefit from luck.</p><figure><img src="virtuous-cycle.png" alt="How a culture of virtue increases the likelihood of collaboration outside of their core work."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">How a culture of virtue increases the
likelihood of collaboration outside of their core work.</figcaption></figure><p>As the diagram indicates, a virtuous culture cultivates
collaboration, leading to successful extra-curricular activity beyond
their core work, which reinforces the culture. Notably, many of Google’s
successful billion-dollar products came about or benefited from
unexpected collaborations that were more or less luck. In a culture of
mistrust, such associations outside of their core work would never have
happened.</p><p>Leadership can identify, plan, and account for some contingencies in
core work. Non-core work, on the other hand, relies on self organization
within the company. That self organization needs trust. Every large
project owes its existence to this non-core work.</p><p>And that’s not all. Some of this work may well become large products
in their own right. Any large tech company will have tons of stories of
this happening repeatedly.</p><p>The importance of “serendipitous collaboration” isn’t lost on
executives. It is the reason behind many pushes for bringing tech
workers back to the office.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Lettergrade Rule</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/the-lettergrade-rule/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 20:27:57 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/the-lettergrade-rule/</guid><description>Don’t block a code review because of minor issues that are best left
to the discretion of the author.</description><content:encoded><p>How do you know when a code review is “done”?</p><p>Let’s say you are the reviewer and see many small changes you’d like
the author to make. At some point, you’ll agree that the introduced
behavior changes are correct or at least harmless. The remaining
comments are largely stylistic or involve misalignments in minor
architectural choices.</p><p>The letter grade rule is a lens for determining if any remaining
comments justify blocking the change. It goes something like this:</p><blockquote><p>Does addressing your comment or doing what you suggest improve the
reviewed code by at least half a letter grade?</p></blockquote><p>Your comments are not worth blocking the review if the answer is no.
Instead, leave them as suggestions that the author can take and do with
it what they will. Then, move on with your life.</p><p>This route is respectful of the author’s time and yours. It also
implicitly places some amount of trust and responsibility on the author,
which is empowering.</p><p>You might now wonder what constitutes a half-a-letter-grade
improvement.</p><p>Here’s a non-exhaustive list of things it is not:</p><ul><li>Stylistic choices that don’t violate the project’s style guide.
Please choose a coding style and enforce it via a code formatting tool
if this is a common cause of disagreement. Use a code formatting tool
even if it isn’t a common cause of dispute. There should be no reason to
format text with a spacebar in 2022.</li><li>Choice of identifier name; unless the name diverges from the
project’s domain model and naming convention or objectively hurts
readability.</li><li>“This isn’t how I would have done it.”</li><li>There are minor grammar issues or word choices in comments that
don’t decrease the readability of the code. You should be able to trust
the author to make those fixes and submit the change without you having
to do another pass.</li></ul></content:encoded></item><item><title>All natural numbers are interesting</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/interesting-numbers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 11:50:46 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/interesting-numbers/</guid><description>A proof.</description><content:encoded><p><strong>Theorem</strong>: All natural numbers are interesting.<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a></p><p>Proof by contradiction.</p><p>Assume the theorem is false. Then there must be at least one number<span class="math inline">\in \N</span> that is boring.</p><p><strong>Let</strong><span class="math inline">\mathbb{B} \subset
\N</span> be the set of boring numbers.</p><p>By the assumption, we have:</p><p><span id="eq:e"><span class="math display">\mathbb{B} \ne
\phi\qquad{(1)}</span></span></p><p>Thus, because<span class="math inline">\mathbb{B}</span> is
non-empty<span class="math inline">\mathbb{B} \subset \N</span>, the<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Well-ordering_principle">Well
Ordering Principle</a> tells us that:</p><p><span id="eq:b"><span class="math display">\exists b \in \mathbb{B}
\| b = \mathrm{inf}(\mathbb{B})\qquad{(2)}</span></span></p><p>Thus this<span class="math inline">b</span> is the smallest boring
natural number in existence; which makes<span class="math inline">b</span> interesting. A contradiction! ∎</p><p>Note that the same doesn’t trivially hold for the set of real numbers
since you’d first have to prove that the set of boring real numbers is
either finite or bounded, and that the infimum is a member of the set.
Neither does this hold for<span class="math inline">\Z</span> since a
non-finite subset in<span class="math inline">\Z</span> doesn’t
necessarily have a minimum.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Not actually a theorem.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Use Git hooks to automatically push after every commit</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/git-autopush/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 16:15:23 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/git-autopush/</guid><description>During before and after various Git operations, Git invokes special
hooks that can be used execute custom scripts. This article explains how
to use them to automatically push to an upstream repository every time
you make a commit to a local repo.</description><content:encoded><p>A Git hook is a shell script that is invoked at specific points
during some Git operations. They are documented in<a href="https://www.git-scm.com/docs/githooks#_post_commit">the Git
book</a>.</p><p>The hook we are interested in is<code>post-commit</code> (<a href="https://www.git-scm.com/docs/githooks#_post_commit">documented
here</a>). It gets run after a new commit is made. This is exactly when
we want to try and update our remote.</p><p>Our hook will:</p><ul><li>Execute each time you commit something into your repository.</li><li>Avoid doing anything if the commit is made during a rebase or
merge.</li><li>Push to a remote named<code>origin</code> (or whichever one you
change the<code>UPSTREAM</code> shell variable to point).</li><li>Create or update a remote reference that matches the branch name
that’s currently checked out.</li></ul><p>Copy and paste the following script into a file named<code>.git/hooks/post-commit</code> in your repository directory.</p><aside class="important"><p>Afterwards make the script runnable via<code>chmod +x .git/hooks/post-commit</code>.</p></aside><script src="https://gist.github.com/asankah/a6263bbd6081bffd031ca066e5177df2.js"/></content:encoded></item><item><title>DARPA's Heilmeier Catechism</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/darpa-heilmeier-catechism/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 10:11:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/darpa-heilmeier-catechism/</guid><description>A set of questions help you think through and evaluate proposed
projects and research programs.</description><content:encoded><p>It seems the hardest part of engineering is the part where you are
staring at a blank page with a vague notion of a problem statement in
your head.</p><p>First you seek structure. After all your attention span can only hold
so much at the same time. In order to tackle larger problems, you need
to reduce large parts of the problem area into intuition. And in turn,
to reduce parts of the problem into intuition, you need to break those
pieces into smaller simpler pieces that you can chew on
individually.</p><p>Losing sight of the forest for the trees is easy during this
process.</p><p>Why were you trying to solve this problem in the first place? Would
you have started if you knew then what you know now about the real scope
of the problem?</p><p>Such concerns are also part of the problem statement; parts that help
your prioritize and select the best solution amongst many. Throughout
all, it’s always good to keep and eye on the prize. That being the end
goal of the exercise. The goal must justify the effort involved. Once
again, for that you need to reduce your motives into intuition.</p><p>The<a href="https://www.darpa.mil/work-with-us/heilmeier-catechism">“The
Heilmeier Catechism”</a> is “a set of questions […] to help Agency
officials think through and evaluate proposed research programs”. The
list of questions is duplicated here for your convenience. It’s a short
and terse list. Much like what your design sketch should be.</p><ul><li>What are you trying to do? Articulate your objectives using
absolutely no jargon.</li><li>How is it done today, and what are the limits of current
practice?</li><li>What is new in your approach and why do you think it will be
successful?</li><li>Who cares? If you are successful, what difference will it make?</li><li>What are the risks?</li><li>How much will it cost?</li><li>How long will it take?</li><li>What are the mid-term and final “exams” to check for success?</li></ul><p>(Source<a href="https://www.darpa.mil/work-with-us/heilmeier-catechism">The
Heilmeier Catechism - DARPA</a>).</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Markdown should be readble without knowing Markdown</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/mark-goes-up-and-down/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 13:02:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/mark-goes-up-and-down/</guid><description>Markdown started out as a way to write text files that could also be machine parsed and rendered into a higher fidelity format.
To quote from the Philosophy:
Readability, however, is emphasized above all else. A Markdown-formatted document should be publishable as-is, as plain text, without looking like it’s been marked up with tags or formatting instructions.
This particular aspect of the format wasn’t maintained very well. Immediately following the “Philosophy” section is “Inline HTML” which contradicts the “without looking like it’s been marked up” requirement.</description><content:encoded><p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax">Markdown</a>
started out as a way to write text files that could also be machine
parsed and rendered into a higher fidelity format.</p><p>To quote from the Philosophy:</p><blockquote><p>Readability, however, is emphasized above all else. A
Markdown-formatted document should be publishable as-is, as plain text,
without looking like it’s been marked up with tags or formatting
instructions.</p></blockquote><p>This particular aspect of the format wasn’t maintained very well.
Immediately following the<em>“Philosophy”</em> section is<em>“Inline
HTML”</em> which contradicts the<em>“without looking like it’s been
marked up”</em> requirement.</p><p>The ease of writing goal was met head on. So much so that it is now
the de-facto format for writing documentation that documents in general
that has any kind of formatting at all. This blog post is also based on
a markdown document.</p><p>People – of course – need more features. And features there were
many. The<em>“Variants”</em> section of the<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown#variants">Wikipedia page on
Markdown</a> touches upon<em>some</em> of the popular syntaxes that
exist now.</p><p>On pet-peeve I have is that these new features don’t even try to
adhere to the minimum markup philosophy. And hence just introduce HTML
tags – or worse HTML-like but not HTML tags – into the format. Someone
who’s not familiar with Markdown syntax – or for that matter whatever
dialect you are using for some document – shouldn’t be thrown off by the
additional markup.</p><h2 id="better-definition-lists">Better Definition Lists?</h2><p>I really don’t like the<em>“Definition List”</em> syntax. This
feature isn’t in the original Markdown syntax, but is a part of<a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/extended-syntax/#definition-lists">many
extended syntaxes</a>. It looks like this:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb1"><pre class="sourceCode markdown bad"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb1-1"><a href="#cb1-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>Some term</span><span id="cb1-2"><a href="#cb1-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>: The definition of the term. Long lines can be</span><span id="cb1-3"><a href="#cb1-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/> broken down while preserving the indent. But</span><span id="cb1-4"><a href="#cb1-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/> the first character can't be ':' or it will become</span><span id="cb1-5"><a href="#cb1-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/> *another* definition.</span></code></pre></div><p>See, it’s easy to see the<code>:</code> as some misplaced
punctuation rather than markup when just reading the text. Instead how
about maybe this?</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb2"><pre class="sourceCode markdown maybe"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb2-1"><a href="#cb2-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="an">Some term:</span></span><span id="cb2-2"><a href="#cb2-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/> The definition starts here. Long lines can be</span><span id="cb2-3"><a href="#cb2-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/> broken down like this.</span><span id="cb2-4"><a href="#cb2-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb2-5"><a href="#cb2-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/> Maybe continue the definition here.</span></code></pre></div><p>It looks more like a definition in a regular text file.</p><h2 id="better-code-blocks">Better Code Blocks?</h2><p>The original syntax for code blocks is to just add extra space in the
middle, like so:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb3"><pre class="sourceCode markdown good"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb3-1"><a href="#cb3-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb3-2"><a href="#cb3-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>This is normal text.</span><span id="cb3-3"><a href="#cb3-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb3-4"><a href="#cb3-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> function ThisIsACodeBlock() {</span></span><span id="cb3-5"><a href="#cb3-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> }</span></span><span id="cb3-6"><a href="#cb3-6" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb3-7"><a href="#cb3-7" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>More normal text.</span></code></pre></div><p>See, if you saw this in a text file, your eyes would easily follow
the context switch. Instead, the most popular markdown formats use the
following kind of markup:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb4"><pre class="sourceCode markdown bad"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb4-1"><a href="#cb4-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb4-2"><a href="#cb4-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>This is normal text.</span><span id="cb4-3"><a href="#cb4-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb4-4"><a href="#cb4-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in">```</span></span><span id="cb4-5"><a href="#cb4-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in">function ThisIsACodeBlock() {</span></span><span id="cb4-6"><a href="#cb4-6" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in">}</span></span><span id="cb4-7"><a href="#cb4-7" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in">```</span></span><span id="cb4-8"><a href="#cb4-8" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb4-9"><a href="#cb4-9" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>More normal text.</span></code></pre></div><p>See how the markup is in the way? There’s a reason for the special
markup; it allows specification of additional attributes like the
underlying language that the code block is in.</p><p>Instead, how about something like this?</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb5"><pre class="sourceCode markdown maybe"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb5-1"><a href="#cb5-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb5-2"><a href="#cb5-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>This is normal text.</span><span id="cb5-3"><a href="#cb5-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb5-4"><a href="#cb5-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>javascript code:</span><span id="cb5-5"><a href="#cb5-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb5-6"><a href="#cb5-6" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> function ThisIsACodeBlock() {</span></span><span id="cb5-7"><a href="#cb5-7" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> }</span></span><span id="cb5-8"><a href="#cb5-8" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb5-9"><a href="#cb5-9" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>More normal text.</span></code></pre></div><p>It re-uses the<code>some text:</code> syntax that’s used for
specifying links.</p><h2 id="better-admonitions">Better admonitions?</h2><p>Admonitions aren’t a feature of regular Markdown. It’s available<a href="https://python-markdown.github.io/extensions/admonition/">as an
extension in select Markdown processors</a>. The syntax is a little
horrendous:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb6"><pre class="sourceCode markdown bad"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb6-1"><a href="#cb6-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>!!! type "optional explicit title within double quotes"</span><span id="cb6-2"><a href="#cb6-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/> Any number of other indented markdown elements.</span><span id="cb6-3"><a href="#cb6-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb6-4"><a href="#cb6-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> This is the second paragraph.</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Okay the exclamation points kind of hints at what this is supposed to
mean. But how about this?</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb7"><pre class="sourceCode markdown maybe"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb7-1"><a href="#cb7-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="an">NOTE:</span><span class="co"> Optional explicit title</span></span><span id="cb7-2"><a href="#cb7-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="co"> Paragraph that contains extra details about the note.</span></span><span id="cb7-3"><a href="#cb7-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="co"/></span><span id="cb7-4"><a href="#cb7-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="co"> This is the second paragraph.</span></span></code></pre></div><p>It’s obvious from looking at the plain text what this is supposed to
be; no need to go look at the documentation for your Markdown dialect to
figure out what on earth<code>!!! title</code> is supposed to be.</p><h2 id="better-collapsed-sections">Better collapsed sections?</h2><p>Okay, so this one is specific to<a href="https://docs.github.com/en/get-started/writing-on-github/working-with-advanced-formatting/organizing-information-with-collapsed-sections">GitHub
Flavored Markdown</a>, and it’s terrible. It comes down to the genre of
just writing HTML:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb8"><pre class="sourceCode markdown bad"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb8-1"><a href="#cb8-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">details</span><span class="dt">>&lt;</span><span class="kw">summary</span><span class="dt">></span>CLICK ME<span class="dt">&lt;/</span><span class="kw">summary</span><span class="dt">></span></span><span id="cb8-2"><a href="#cb8-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">p</span><span class="dt">></span></span><span id="cb8-3"><a href="#cb8-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb8-4"><a href="#cb8-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="fu">#### We can hide anything, even code!</span></span><span id="cb8-5"><a href="#cb8-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb8-6"><a href="#cb8-6" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> ```ruby</span></span><span id="cb8-7"><a href="#cb8-7" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> puts "Hello World"</span></span><span id="cb8-8"><a href="#cb8-8" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> ```</span></span><span id="cb8-9"><a href="#cb8-9" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb8-10"><a href="#cb8-10" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="dt">&lt;/</span><span class="kw">p</span><span class="dt">></span></span><span id="cb8-11"><a href="#cb8-11" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="dt">&lt;/</span><span class="kw">details</span><span class="dt">></span></span></code></pre></div><p>WTF? You might as well write the thing in HTML and call it a day.
Maybe if they could’ve gone with something like:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb9"><pre class="sourceCode markdown maybe"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb9-1"><a href="#cb9-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb9-2"><a href="#cb9-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>Summary goes here.</span><span id="cb9-3"><a href="#cb9-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb9-4"><a href="#cb9-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/>Details:</span><span id="cb9-5"><a href="#cb9-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/> Details go here. and yes you can use fenced code blocks.</span><span id="cb9-6"><a href="#cb9-6" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb9-7"><a href="#cb9-7" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> Like this.</span></span><span id="cb9-8"><a href="#cb9-8" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"/></span><span id="cb9-9"><a href="#cb9-9" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/> Or the ugly way:</span><span id="cb9-10"><a href="#cb9-10" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/></span><span id="cb9-11"><a href="#cb9-11" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in">```</span></span><span id="cb9-12"><a href="#cb9-12" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> Like this.</span></span><span id="cb9-13"><a href="#cb9-13" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="in"> ```</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Once again it re-uses the<code>some text:</code> syntax, and it
could probably use either<code>details</code> or<code>Details</code>.
Either way, you don’t need to understand the markup to see where this is
going.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>On Gender Gap in Adolescent Mental Health</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/gender-gap-in-adolescent-mental-health/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 14:51:34 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/gender-gap-in-adolescent-mental-health/</guid><description>A recent study found that more gender-equal countries have larger
gender gaps in mental health. I look at the data that seems to have
yielded this counter-intuitive results and find it lacking.</description><content:encoded><p>Today is the first day of<a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/history/article/why-the-us-celebrates-womens-history-month-every-march">Women’s
History Month</a>.</p><p>Coincidentally there’s a paper making the rounds titled<em>“The
gender gap in adolescent mental health: A cross-national investigation
of 566,829 adolescents across 73 countries”</em><span class="citation" data-cites="campbell2021gender">(<a href="#ref-campbell2021gender" role="doc-biblioref">Campbell, Bann, and Patalay 2021</a>)</span>, which
makes some these interesting claims:</p><ul><li>Girls have worse average mental health than boys across 4 mental
health measures.</li><li>There is significant heterogeneity in the mental health gender gap
size across countries.</li><li>The gap is most pronounced for psychological distress and life
satisfaction.</li><li>More gender-equal countries have more gender gaps in mental
health.</li></ul><p>The last point, in particular, is a bit of an eyebrow-raiser. So
let’s have a closer look.</p><p>The study uses the<a href="https://www.oecd.org/pisa/data/2018database/">PISA 2018
dataset</a>, introducing a couple of caveats. Namely:</p><ol type="1"><li>All survey respondents were 15 years old; thus, the dataset doesn’t
consider higher education and employment effects.</li><li>The data is from 2018; thus excludes the effects of the pandemic. It
would be interesting to see how the responses change now that people are
coming out of a lengthy lock down.</li><li>Gender was binary. There was no non-binary option.</li></ol><p>The study<span class="citation" data-cites="campbell2021gender">(<a href="#ref-campbell2021gender" role="doc-biblioref">Campbell, Bann, and
Patalay 2021</a>)</span> derives five measures of mental health based on
the PISA 2018 dataset as follows:</p><ol type="1"><li><p><em>“Life satisfaction”</em> measures responses to the question<em>“on a scale of 0-10, overall, how satisfied are you with your life
as a whole these days?”</em></p></li><li><p><em>“Psychological distress”</em> measures responses to the
question on how often they felt<em>“sad”</em>,<em>“miserable”</em>,<em>“scared”</em>, and<em>“afraid”</em> on a scale of<em>“never”</em>,<em>“rarely”</em>,<em>“sometimes”</em>, and<em>“always”</em>. Each
response yields points ranging from 1 through 4, respectively. Summing
the points for each question results in a score of 4-16.</p><p>The survey doesn’t appear to have clarified the difference between<em>“sad”</em>/<em>“miserable”</em> and<em>“scared”</em>/<em>“afraid”</em>. PISA 2018 mentions that:</p><blockquote><p>All questions were translated into the languages of participating
countries by two independent linguists and then reconciled by a third to
ensure consistent meaning in all countries.</p></blockquote></li><li><p><em>“Hedonia”</em> measures the responses to the question on how
often they felt<em>“happy”</em>,<em>“lively”</em>,<em>“proud”</em>,<em>“joyful”</em>, and<em>“cheerful”</em> on the same scale. This
yields a combined scale of 5-20.</p></li><li><p><em>“Eudaemonic wellbeing”</em> measures the degree of agreement
with the below statements. The scale was<em>“strongly disagree”</em>,<em>“disagree”</em>,<em>“agree”</em>, and<em>“strongly agree”</em>
with a combined score in the range 3-12:</p><ol type="1"><li><em>“My life has clear meaning or purpose”</em>.</li><li><em>“I have discovered a satisfactory meaning in life.”</em></li><li><em>“I have a clear sense of what gives meaning to my
life”</em>.</li></ol></li></ol><p>Details of the analysis are in<a href="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S2352827321000173-mmc1.pdf">the
companion document (PDF link)</a>.</p><p>In figure S2 of<span class="citation" data-cites="campbell2021gender">(<a href="#ref-campbell2021gender" role="doc-biblioref">Campbell, Bann, and Patalay 2021</a>)</span> shows
the distribution of<em>life satisfaction</em>. Again, developed nations
are not doing well compared with countries like Saudi Arabia.</p><figure><img src="./life-satisfaction-eu.png" alt="Distribution of life satisfaction scores for France, Germany, Greece, and Iceland. The range of responses were from 0 through 10. Red is male, and blue is female."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Distribution of life satisfaction scores
for France, Germany, Greece, and Iceland. The range of responses were
from 0 through 10. Red is male, and blue is female.</figcaption></figure><p>Compare with:</p><figure><img src="./life-satisfaction-sa-uae.png" alt="Distribution of life satisfaction scores for Saudi Arabia and United Arab Emirates. Note that most respondents gave a score of 10."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Distribution of life satisfaction scores
for Saudi Arabia and United Arab Emirates. Note that most respondents
gave a score of 10.</figcaption></figure><p>I’m skeptical that these numbers represent reality. Unless there’s a
part of Saudi Arabia where adolescents are consistently happy all the
time, these numbers don’t make sense. My skepticism is also extended to
the data from the UAE.<a href="https://www.hrw.org/world-report/2021/country-chapters/united-arab-emirates">Human
Rights Watch’s report on the UAE</a> indicates that the UAE is far from
having any semblance of gender equality. Approximately 80% of the
population consists of migrant workers<a href="https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2022/2/21/thousands-of-children-in-uae-has-no-access-to-schooling-report">who’s
children don’t have access to formal education</a>. It’s unlikely that
these children of migrants participated in the study.</p><p>The curve fitting for the resulting graphs is what tells the stories
that are summarized at the start of this post. The axes are arranged so
that moving towards the right and moving upwards indicate better
conditions. Hence it’s apparent from the curves that male life
satisfaction is pretty consistent and not affected all that much by
GII<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>. Meanwhile, female life satisfaction
trends<em>downward</em> as GII improves; hence the conclusion that more
gender equality implies less happiness.</p><p>GSNI (Gender Social Norms Index) is also negatively correlated with
quality-of-life measures (where we put “good” on the high end and “bad”
on the low end).</p><figure><img src="./life-satisfaction-vs-other-indicators.png" alt="Life satisfaction plotted against per-capita GDP, Gini index, GII, GSNI, GGGI. The curves don’t quite fit very well."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Life satisfaction plotted against
per-capita GDP, Gini index, GII, GSNI, GGGI. The curves don’t quite fit
very well.</figcaption></figure><p>All the graphs show a high variance. Only a small number of countries
are present in the study. And whether the subjects of the study are
representative of the population is in doubt. Overall I find the study
unconvincing.</p><h2 class="unnumbered" id="references">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0" role="list"><div id="ref-campbell2021gender" class="csl-entry" role="listitem">
Campbell, Olympia LK, David Bann, and Praveetha Patalay. 2021.<span>“The Gender Gap in Adolescent Mental Health: A Cross-National
Investigation of 566,829 Adolescents Across 73 Countries.”</span><em>SSM-Population Health</em> 13: 100742.</div></div><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>GII is the Gender Inequality Index. It’s based on such
factors like<em>female and male shares of parliamentary seats</em>,<em>female and male population with at least secondary education</em>,<em>female and male labour force participation rates</em>,<em>maternal
mortality ratio</em>, and<em>adolescent birth rate</em>.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>On Highlighting Syntax vs. Semantics</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/syntax-highlighting/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/syntax-highlighting/</guid><description>Takes a look at an alternate form of code highlighting based on core
semantics instead of syntactic role.</description><content:encoded><p><span class="noun">Aesthetics</span><span class="adverb">aside</span>,<span class="noun">syntax</span><span class="gerund">highlighting</span><span class="preposition">in</span><span class="noun">code</span><span class="verb">performs</span><span class="determiner">an</span><span class="adjective">important</span><span class="noun">role</span><span class="preposition">in</span><span class="gerund">improving</span> the<span class="noun">readability</span><span class="preposition">of</span><span class="noun">code</span>.<span class="adjective">Most</span><span class="adjective">syntax</span><span class="gerund">highlighting</span><span class="noun">schemes</span><span class="gerund">including</span><span class="adjective">popular</span><span class="noun">libraries</span><span class="verb">are</span><span class="verb">limited</span><span class="preposition">to</span><span class="gerund">using</span><span class="noun">colors</span><span class="conjunction">and</span><span class="gerund">formatting</span><span class="noun">changes</span><span class="preposition">to</span><span class="verb">distinguish</span><span class="preposition">between</span><span class="adjective">different</span><span class="adjective">syntax</span><span class="noun">classes</span>.<span class="pronoun">This</span><span class="verb">is</span><span class="determiner">what</span><span class="pronoun">it</span><span class="verb">would look</span><span class="conjunction">like</span><span class="conjunction">if</span><span class="pronoun">we</span><span class="verb">apply</span><span class="determiner">the</span><span class="adjective">same</span><span class="noun">logic</span><span class="preposition">to</span><span class="proper">English</span><span class="noun">prose</span>.<span class="adjective">Each</span><span class="noun">word</span><span class="preposition">in</span><span class="pronoun">this</span><span class="noun">paragraph</span><span class="verb">is</span><span class="adverb">highlighted</span><span class="verb">using</span><span class="pronoun">its</span><span class="adjective">respective</span><span class="adjective">syntactic</span><span class="noun">purpose</span>.</p><p>Not very readable, is it? The colors aren’t random. They highlights
correspond to<span class="noun">noun</span>,<span class="adverb">adverb</span>,<span class="gerund">gerund</span>,<span class="preposition">preposition</span>,<span class="adjective">adjective</span>, and<span class="verb">verb</span>.
This is basically how people use syntax highlighting.</p><p>Typographers have long known that punctuation alone can’t
sufficiently convey emphasis and relative importance of prose. As<span class="citation" data-cites="truss2004eats">(<a href="#ref-truss2004eats" role="doc-biblioref">Truss 2004</a>)</span>
points out<em>italics</em> is<em>“the print equivalent of
underlining”</em> (via<span class="citation" data-cites="wiki:Italic_type">(<a href="#ref-wiki:Italic_type" role="doc-biblioref">Wikipedia 2021</a>)</span>). A number of uses exist
for this font variation including providing emphasis, stressing
important points, or indicating foreign words and phrases. When
conveying emphasis the syntactic role of a word does not change; the
word just is<em>more</em> important to make the central point than
others.</p><p>These key important words alone can’t convey a story. Grammar and
completeness demand accompanying words. It is the role of formatting,
whitespace, and punctuation to guide the reader towards what is
important. Without formatting and whitespace, prose would become an
intimidating “wall of words”; tedious and unwelcoming.</p><p>And so it goes for code; some code is more important than others. The
central logic of a snippet of code lies somewhere in the middle
surrounded by boilerplate, setup, and tear down logic. If syntax
highlighting were to make the central logic stand out, then it has to go
beyond mere syntactic purpose of the tokens comprising the code.</p><p>What would such a scheme look like?</p><div class="pre"><div class="line-block">bool ListValue::<span class="function hi">Set</span>(size_t<span class="var">index</span>,
std::unique_ptr&lt;Value><span class="var">in_value</span>) {<br/>
  if (!in_value)<br/>
    return false;<br/>
  if (index >= list().size())<br/>
    list().resize(index + 1);</div><div class="pre highlight"><div class="line-block">  <span class="function">list</span>()[<span class="var">index</span>] = std::<span class="function">move</span>(*<span class="var">in_value</span>);</div></div><div class="line-block">  return true;<br/>
}</div></div><p>Perhaps not the best example, but you should get the gist of where
I’m going with this. The highlighting quickly directs your eyes to the
parts that need attention. You’d still need to do the legwork for the
details. But for someone trying to figure out what some undocumented
function is doing, this kind of highlight makes quick work of going past
the boilerplate.</p><h2 class="unnumbered" id="references">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0" role="list"><div id="ref-truss2004eats" class="csl-entry" role="listitem">
Truss, Lynne. 2004.<span>“Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves: The Zero Tolerance
Approach to Punctuation.”</span> In, 146. Penguin.</div><div id="ref-wiki:Italic_type" class="csl-entry" role="listitem">
Wikipedia. 2021.<span>“<span class="nocase">Italic type</span> —<span>W</span>ikipedia<span>,</span> the Free Encyclopedia.”</span><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Italic%20type&amp;oldid=1049142359" class="uri">http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Italic%20type&amp;oldid=1049142359</a>.</div></div></content:encoded></item><item><title>Inktober - Stripes</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/inktober-stripes/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 17:20:38 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/inktober-stripes/</guid><description>“Stripes” - A bee wearing an incorrectly striped sweater For Inktober 52.</description><content:encoded><figure><img src="./inktober-stripes.png" alt="“Stripes” - A bee wearing an incorrectly striped sweater"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">“Stripes” - A bee wearing an incorrectly
striped sweater</figcaption></figure><p>For<a href="https://inktober.com/inktober52">Inktober 52</a>.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Inktober - Wild</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/inktober-wild/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 15:35:39 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/inktober-wild/</guid><description>“Wild” - Caught in the wild For Inktober 52.</description><content:encoded><figure><img src="./inktober-wild.png" alt="“Wild” - Caught in the wild"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">“Wild” - Caught in the wild</figcaption></figure><p>For<a href="https://inktober.com/inktober52">Inktober 52</a>.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Inktober - Decay</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/inktober-decay/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 15:21:37 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/inktober-decay/</guid><description>“Decay” - I was kind of going for tooth-decay caused by tiny little gremlins. For Inktober 52.</description><content:encoded><figure><img src="./inktober-decay.png" alt="“Decay” - I was kind of going for tooth-decay caused by tiny little gremlins."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">“Decay” - I was kind of going for
tooth-decay caused by tiny little gremlins.</figcaption></figure><p>For<a href="https://inktober.com/inktober52">Inktober 52</a>.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Quickly grab a snapshot of your reMarkable tablet</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/grab-diagram-workflow-re2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/grab-diagram-workflow-re2/</guid><description>How to bind a hotkey to grab a snapshot of your reMarkable display
and copy it to the clipboard on a Mac.</description><content:encoded><p>One everyday workflow that I wanted to optimize was quickly sketching
out a diagram on the reMarkable tablet and including it in a document I
was writing somewhere else.</p><p>My primary computer is a Mac. Here’s my solution:</p><ol type="1"><li>Set up<a href="https://github.com/asankah/reSnap"><code>reSnap</code></a>. This
step requires changes on both the reMarkable tablet and the local
machine. For the former, I followed the instructions in the<a href="https://github.com/asankah/reSnap#readme"><code>README</code></a>
file. For the latter, I only really needed to install<a href="https://www.ffmpeg.org/"><code>FFmpeg</code></a> and<a href="https://imagemagick.org/index.php"><code>ImageMagick</code></a>.</li><li>Create a Mac Quick Action to invoke reSnap.</li><li>Bind a hotkey that grabs the snapshot of the reMarkable display,
cleans it up, and sticks it in Mac’s clipboard.</li></ol><p>Details instructions follow. I can now just hit ⌘+⌃+⇧+P to grab the
snapshot and then hit ⌘+V to paste it into whatever application I am
using, usually Google Docs.</p><h2 id="setting-up-resnap">Setting up<code>reSnap</code></h2><p>I have<a href="https://github.com/asankah/reSnap">my fork of<code>reSnap</code></a>, which adds a few valuable tricks like cleaning
up the image and placing it in the system clipboard. By default, the
upstream<code>reSnap</code> script attempts to preview the image using<code>feh</code> (an image viewer I’ve never heard of). Immediately
viewing the picture wasn’t useful to me, so I made that optional. You
can grab my fork of reSnap<a href="https://github.com/asankah/reSnap">here</a>.</p><p>On the reMarkable tablet side, you must follow the instructions in
the<code>README</code> file to install<code>lz4</code> and<code>head</code> on the device.</p><p>It is important to set up SSH to use password-less logins since the
hotkey method relies on being able to connect without prompting for a
password. See instructions for<a href="https://remarkablewiki.com/tech/ssh#passwordless_login_with_ssh_keys">setting
up SSH for passwordless login</a>.</p><p>On the local machine – which in my case is a Mac – you can install
all the requirements using Homebrew as follows:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb1"><pre class="sourceCode sh"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb1-1"><a href="#cb1-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">brew</span> install ffmpeg imagemagick</span></code></pre></div><h2 id="creating-a-mac-quick-action">Creating a Mac Quick Action</h2><ol type="1"><li><p>Start “Automator.”<img src="./automator-icon.png" alt="Automator application icon."/></p></li><li><p>Create a new “Quick Action.”<img src="./quick-action-icon.png" alt="Select “Quick Action” from the “New” menu."/></p></li><li><p>Set up the workflow options to receive no input in any
application. All the other options are up to you, or you can leave them
as-is.<img src="./workflow-options.png" alt="Set the workflow options to recieve “no input” in “any application”."/></p></li><li><p>Drag over the “Run Shell Script” action from the actions library.<img src="./run-shell-script-action.png" alt="Drag over the “Run Shell Script” action."/></p></li><li><p>Paste something like the following (with the suggested
modifications to suit your local environment).</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb2"><pre class="sourceCode sh"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb2-1"><a href="#cb2-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">/usr/bin/env</span> PATH=/bin:/usr/bin:/usr/local/bin:/sbin /path/to/reSnap/reSnap.sh<span class="at">--sketch</span><span class="at">--copy</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Note that the reMarkable needs to be connected via a USB cable to
capture a snapshot using the above command. If you want to be able to
use WiFi you should use the<code>--host</code> option to specify either
the local hostname (usually “remarkable”) or the IP address. In all
cases the hotkey should only be expected to work when the reMarkable is
not sleeping.</p></li><li><p>If you’d like, you can also add a “Display Notification” action,
so you know when the script is done running. The<code>FFMpeg</code>
invocation may take a few seconds.</p></li></ol><p>Try it out with the “Run” button.</p><h2 id="binding-a-hotkey">Binding a hotkey</h2><p>Once you save your quick action, you can bind a hotkey like this:</p><ol type="1"><li><p>Open “System Preferences” and navigate to “Keyboard” ->
“Shortcuts”.</p></li><li><p>Click on “Services” and scroll to the bottom. You should see the
new quick action you just made listed under the “General” category. It
should have no keys assigned to it.</p><figure><img src="./keyboard-shortcuts.png" alt="Example of what you should see when you select “Services” in “Keyboard” -> “Shortcuts”"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Example of what you should see when you
select “Services” in “Keyboard” -> “Shortcuts”</figcaption></figure></li><li><p>Double click on the “none” and type your hotkey.</p></li></ol><p>That’s it.</p><p>Here’s what a snapshot looks like:</p><figure><img src="./snapshot-from-remarkable.png" alt="A snapshot from my reMarkable tablet"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">A snapshot from my reMarkable
tablet</figcaption></figure><h2 id="a-couple-of-notes-on-the---sketch-option">A couple of notes on
the<code>--sketch</code> option</h2><p>My fork of<code>reSnap</code> introduces a<code>--sketch</code>
option that cleans up the picture a little bit. It currently does the
following:</p><ol type="1"><li>Erase the little menu widget from the top-left corner of the image.
Since<code>reSnap</code> grabs the image right off the framebuffer this
little artifact makes its way to the resulting image.</li><li>Erase a tiny little black dot that appears in the bottom-left corner
of the image. I don’t know where this one comes from, but it’s
there.</li><li>Make the background transparent.</li><li>Resample the image at 50% resolution with anti-aliasing. The
original image is a stiff monochrome image with a white background and
black strokes. The resampling after making the background transparent
makes the edges smoother and a bit easier on the eyes. Otherwise all the
edges look jagged.</li><li>Trim the image to remove all the empty borders thus making the image
size just large enough to hold the actual image.</li></ol><p>All of this is done via an invocation of<a href="https://imagemagick.org/index.php">ImageMagick</a>.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Note-taking on a reMarkable 2</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/remarkable-first-impressions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 16:10:30 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/remarkable-first-impressions/</guid><description>Sentiments after using the reMarkable 2 tablet for a month.</description><content:encoded><p>After much dillydallying about which note-taker/ebook reader I wanted
to get, I went ahead and got a<a href="https://remarkable.com/">reMarkable 2</a>. I’ve been using it for
about a month now. I must say that it’s the closest thing to writing on
paper that I have encountered.</p><p>My requirements of a note-taking tablet were:</p><ol type="1"><li>Replace my paper notebooks.</li><li>Quickly transfer diagrams and drawings to the computer/laptop.</li></ol><p>Replacing a paper notebook is a tall order. A paper notebook is …</p><ul><li>Ready as soon as I open it.</li><li>Lightweight.</li><li>Durable.</li><li>Can be used with a comfortable pen.</li><li>Doesn’t make my eyes tired.</li></ul><h2 id="an-unsuccessful-attempt-with-a-pixelbook">An Unsuccessful
Attempt With A Pixelbook</h2><figure><img src="./picture-of-pixelbook.png" alt="A Pixelbook like this was my first attempt at using a tablet for note-taking. (Image source)"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">A Pixelbook like this was my first
attempt at using a tablet for note-taking.<a href="https://www.google.com/chromebookdevice/google-pixelbook/">(Image
source)</a></figcaption></figure><aside class="note"><p>The comments below<em>only</em> apply to the Chromebook Pixel’s
utility as a note-taking device. It is, of course, far more than a
note-taking device and will likely be a better choice for you if you
want to use the web, consume lots of eBooks, or otherwise need the
functionality of a modern laptop.</p></aside><p>The<a href="https://www.google.com/chromebook/device/google-pixelbook/">Pixelbook</a><a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> was my first attempt at using a
tablet for note-taking. Unfortunately, while it had other advantages,
the Pixelbook falls far short on convenience.</p><p>Ad-hoc note-taking is a hassle. Getting started requires logging in.
There are good reasons for needing signing-in, and it does have an
option to use the built-in sketch app from the lock screen using the
Pixelbook pen. But the sketch app doesn’t suffice as a note-taking
app.</p><p>I do like the privacy model of the Pixelbook’s lock screen sketch app
– namely, that the note drops into a black box that only the owner can
open. However, I wish the reMarkable could have a feature where adding a
new note doesn’t simultaneously require viewing every note on the
device.</p><p>Once folded over, I get paranoid about the keys underneath. Can I
place it on a table without worrying too much? It’s anxiety-inducing.
It’s also a laptop, which means that someone who’s easily distracted
would be … easily distracted.</p><p>So over to the reMarkable…</p><h2 id="moderate-success-with-the-remarkable-2">Moderate Success With
The Remarkable 2</h2><figure><img src="./picture-of-re2.png" alt="The reMarkable 2 was my next choice. (Image Source)"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">The reMarkable 2 was my next choice.<a href="https://remarkable.com/">(Image Source)</a></figcaption></figure><p>First of all, this is a note-taking device. You should not expect
much more from it. I thought it would make for a good ebook reader and
journal article reader – it is neither. Its support for ebooks is
limited to PDFs and EPUBs.</p><p>I’m still looking for a satisfactory method of keeping a set of
journal articles synchronized between my laptop and the reMarkable
tablet. The current method is to go through their proprietary cloud
service, which I can only do for my personal usage but not for work.</p><p>Once again,<strong>this is neither a laptop nor an ebook
reader</strong>.</p><p>There are, however, two important points to note about the reMarkable
tablet:</p><ol type="1"><li>It’s the closest I’ve seen to writing on paper. The hardware is
pretty much spot on.</li><li>There’s an active community of hackers who constantly push the
tablet’s capabilities.</li></ol><p>The second point bears repeating. The biggest thing going for the
reMarkable tablet right now is the developer community surrounding it.
Have a gander at the<a href="https://remarkablewiki.com/">reMarkableWiki</a>’s<a href="https://remarkablewiki.com/tips/start">Tips and Tricks</a> page or
the<a href="https://github.com/reHackable/awesome-reMarkable">Awesome
reMarkable</a> list. Some highlights include:</p><ul><li>Ability to use third-party clouds or local storage for synchronizing
your reMakable documents (via<a href="https://remarkablewiki.com/tips/rclone">rclone</a> or<a href="https://github.com/simonschllng/rm-sync">rm-sync</a> or many other
options).</li><li>Setting up an email address to which you can email documents which
will appear on your reMarkable (via<a href="https://remarkablenewsletter.com/">reMarkable
Newsletter</a>).</li><li>Stream your reMarkable screen (via<a href="https://blog.afandian.com/2020/10/pipes-and-paper-remarkable/">pipes
and paper</a>,<a href="https://github.com/rien/reStream">reStream</a>,<a href="https://github.com/bordaigorl/rmview">rMview</a>, or
others).</li></ul><p>If you are into tinkering with electronics, the reMarkable will
provide ample entertainment in addition to note-taking.</p><h2 id="workflows">Workflows</h2><p>The process of making myself at home with the reMarkable 2 involved
coming up with good workflows for the things that I want to do with it.
My goal here is to reduce the overhead as much as possible. Although a
paper notebook is close to ideal for writing things down, it’s not easy
to get that content out to an electronic format. I hope that the
reMarkable 2 will keep the former as-is while significantly improving
the latter.</p><p>Not all notes are equal. Some are ad-hoc sketches and doodles. Some
need to be a bit more longevity, like daily diary entries. Some are
drafts of design documents, diagrams, or blog posts that I’d need to
move over to an electronic format. Then there are work-related things
like interview notes and meeting notes. So we have three overall
workflows:</p><ol type="1"><li>Missives that I may want to keep around only to satisfy some sort of
hoarding instinct.</li><li>Notes that I want to transcribe into some electronic form. If the
originals are to be kept, they must be labeled or categorized somehow.<ol type="1"><li>Pictures or diagrams.</li><li>Text.</li></ol></li><li>Notes that, regardless of whether any transcription is needed, carry
confidential or proprietary information.</li></ol><p>Of these, the first one is trivial. Pull out the device, write stuff,
move on with life. If necessary, I can always look at the recent notes,
but I will likely never look at anything older than a month.</p><p>The second one is easy if you are using the<a href="https://remarkable.com/store/connect">Connect cloud</a>. There are
multiple integrations that they already have for moving content to other
cloud providers, including conversion to different image formats. The
Connect cloud also handles the work of extracting text from what you’ve
written. In my experience, the handwriting recognition results have been
quite good though they require the occasional cleanup.</p><p>The third one is tricky. Again, sidestepping the Connect cloud
offering, the aforementioned hacking resources really help get material
from the device onto your machine.</p><p>I’ll leave the details for another blog post, but the gist of it is
that we can quickly transfer the contents of the display as a picture to
a laptop or desktop computer via Wifi or via USB. From there, you can
use any number of tools to extract the text or clean up the drawings.
With a little bit of automation, the process was more accessible than
the Connect cloud.</p><h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2><p><strong>Pros</strong>:</p><ul><li><p>Writing is as close to writing on a paper as one could
get.</p></li><li><p>Tight integration with their cloud offering.</p></li><li><p>Great ecosystem of hackers who push the capabilities of the
device far beyond the stock software.</p></li><li><p>The device lasts for days on a single charge. Their marketing
materials mention two weeks. I haven’t pushed it that far due to
occasionally connecting it to the laptop via USB for content transfer. I
can, however, say that based on the battery remaining this claim seems
to be correct in my case.</p></li><li><p>Can’t do much else other than note taking.</p></li><li><p>Relatively cheap compared to other note-taking devices.</p></li></ul><p><strong>Cons:</strong></p><ul><li><p>The nib on the pen wears out quickly.</p><p>They do include 9 additional nibs in the package, but I suspect that
I’ll be buying more within a few months. Compare that with something
like<a href="https://supernote.com/pages/feelwrite-self-recovery-soft-film-technology">Supernote</a>
which boasts that their nibs provide the same level of paper-like
friction without as much wear.</p></li><li><p>Requires a lot of hand tinkering unless you subscribe to their
cloud offering.</p></li><li><p>Limited support for ebook formats mean that you likely can’t read
your purchased ebooks on this device.</p></li><li><p>No support for labeling or organizing your notes – as of this
writing.</p></li></ul><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>In case the Pixelbook site goes offline, here’s the
Wayback Machine’s<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210725184512/https://www.google.com/chromebook/device/google-pixelbook/">snapshot
from when I wrote this article</a>.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Why 'Strong Opinions Weekly Held'</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/why-strong-opinions-weekly-held/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/why-strong-opinions-weekly-held/</guid><description>Previously on this blog I wrote a short note on Why Strong Opinions Weakly Held.
I’m trying to get something out every week. Hence the new blog title.</description><content:encoded><p>Previously on this blog I wrote a short note on<a href="/posts/why-strong-opinions-weakly-held/">Why Strong Opinions Weakly
Held</a>.</p><p>I’m trying to get something out every week. Hence the new blog
title.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Visualizing A Million People</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/visualizing-people-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/visualizing-people-2/</guid><description>If your feature pisses off a million people what does this angry mob
look like? Spoiler: We only get to 750,000.</description><content:encoded><aside class="note"><p>This article was formerly published as<a href="/posts/visualizing-people/">Visualizing Internet Users</a>. This
version is more generalized and up-to-date.</p></aside><p>What if you introduce a bug and/or a feature that pisses off a
million people?</p><p>The scenario isn’t all that hard to imagine these days if you work at
a big tech company or even a small one with a considerable user base. It
seems a million users aren’t all that hard to reach these days.</p><p>What is harder though is to imagine what a million people looks like.
What if you were being stared down by the entirety of the affected user
base? Or worse you had to stand on a stage in front of them and explain
yourself?</p><p>If you have 1 billion users and you ship a bug that only manifests 1
in a million times, then you have yourself 1000 angry users. It’s good
to know what that group looks like.</p><p>We can easily imagine a single person, 10, or even 25 people. But
exceed a couple of hundred and our imagination falters. It becomes just
a number and stops feeling like “users” or “people.” The perceived
significance of the population thus starts to diminish.</p><h1 id="so-whats-the-significance-of-a-million-people-anyway">So what’s
the significance of a million people anyway?</h1><p>World population is teetering on roughly 7.7 billion people (in
2019). So<strong>a million people is about 0.01% of the global
population</strong>.</p><figure id="fig:worldpop"><img src="world-population-2021.png" alt="World population in 2021 is 7.7 billion approximately."/><figcaption>Figure 1: World population in 2021 is 7.7 billion
approximately.</figcaption></figure><p>Internet users, on the other hand, come up to something like half of
the world population based World Bank figures which<em>imply</em> that
roughly 50% of the population should have internet access in 2021<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>.</p><figure id="fig:internetpop"><img src="worldbank-individuals-using-internet.webp" alt="Percentage of population who has access to the internet (World Bank 2017)"/><figcaption>Figure 2: Percentage of population who has access to the
internet (World Bank 2017)</figcaption></figure><p>So<strong>a million users would be 0.02% of the population with some
access to the internet</strong>. Still not that big.</p><p>But once you focus on a smaller scale like a geographic region or a
user base of some application, then suddenly the million users looks
much bigger.</p><h2 id="to-49">1 to 49</h2><p>Let’s skip this range since this is in the range of what you’d see in
a mirror, can fit on a bicycle, can fit on a sofa, your team, gathering
of friends, significant annual family event, or other familiar
situation.</p><h2 id="from-50-to-100000">From 50 to 100,000</h2><p>An example of visualizing populations for small numbers can be found
at<a href="https://blog.lime.link/visualizing-crowd-sizes/">Visualizing
Crowd Sizes</a>. It goes from around 50 people up to 100,000 people.</p><p>While 100,000 is interesting we need to go all the way to 1
million.</p><h2 id="section">200,000</h2><p>200,000 was the estimated number of people who attended the<a href="https://marchforourlives.com/">March for Our Lives</a> in D.C..
There aren’t any photos capturing<em>all</em> attendees in one shot,
but there are numerous pictures in<a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/march-for-our-lives-crowd-size-estimated-200000-people-attended-d-c-march/">this
CBS News article</a> to give you a good idea.</p><p>In more terrible examples,<a href="https://www.dw.com/en/more-than-200000-indonesians-protest-governor-purnamas-alleged-blasphemy/a-36611145">this
article on dw.com</a> suggests that the crowd size pictured is roughly
around 200,000 people.</p><blockquote><p>More than 200,000 conservative Muslims gathered in Indonesia’s
capital Jakarta on Friday to protest against the city’s Christian
governor, who is facing trial for blasphemy, police estimated.</p></blockquote><figure><img src="dw-com-indonesia-protest-2020-11-20.jpg" alt="Image from dw.com of a protest in Indonesia allegedly showing 200,000 people. Image Source"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Image from dw.com of a protest in
Indonesia allegedly showing 200,000 people.<a href="https://www.dw.com/en/more-than-200000-indonesians-protest-governor-purnamas-alleged-blasphemy/a-36611145">Image
Source</a></figcaption></figure><h2 id="section-1">250,000</h2><p>The March on Washington in 1963– an<em>“event focused on employment
discrimination, civil rights abuses against African Americans, Latinos,
and other disenfranchised groups, and support for the Civil Rights Act
that the Kennedy Administration was attempting to pass through
Congress”</em> – drew an estimated 250,000 people according to the
National Park Service.</p><blockquote><p>Rustin coordinated a staff of over 200 civil rights activists and
organizers to assist in publicizing the march and recruiting marchers,
organizing churches to raise money, coordinating buses and trains, and
administering all of the other logistical details. In many ways, the
March defied expectations. The number of people that attended exceeded
the initial estimates made by the organizers. Rustin had indicated that
they expected over 100,000 people to attend - the final estimate was
250,000, 190,000 blacks and 60,000 whites.</p></blockquote><p>(From<a href="https://www.nps.gov/articles/march-on-washington.htm">March on
Washington for Jobs and Freedom – National Parks Service</a>)</p><figure><img src="march-on-washington-1963.jpg" alt="Image from nps.gov showing the crowd estimated to be around 250,000 people at the March on Washington on August 28, 1963. See Image Source for full resolution image."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Image from nps.gov showing the crowd
estimated to be around 250,000 people at the March on Washington on
August 28, 1963. See<a href="https://www.loc.gov/resource/ppmsca.37248/">Image Source for full
resolution image.</a></figcaption></figure><h2 id="section-2">500,000</h2><p>We are heading into shaky ground here. A 800*600 picture only
contains 480,000 pixels. So we are now reduced to indicating population
by inference. It is no longer possible to capture 500,000 people in a
webpage sized picture while showing each person individually.</p><p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/philadelphia/comments/3by9g8/if_this_is_what_500k_people_look_like_xpost_from/">This
Reddit post</a> claims that there are 500k people in the picture, but I
couldn’t readily find any good references backing up that claim.</p><p>Another event that drew 500,000 people is<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/show-me/video/nearly-500-000-people-march-in-anti-violence-rally-in-barcelona-1033617987741">an
anti-violence rally in Barcelona as reported by NBC</a>. While there’s
video, the content doesn’t quite capture the massive number of people.
Also it’s<em>“nearly 500,000”</em> people.</p><p>However, the closest we’ll probably get to a somewhat believable
500,000 person crowd would be the March for Science. They posted the
following picture on<a href="https://www.facebook.com/marchforscience/posts/836983043362678">Facebook</a>
noting that “There are 500,000 people on strike in Montreal”.</p><figure><img src="march-for-science-crowd-2020-11-20.jpg" alt="March for Science on Facebook: Picture of protest. Image source"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">March for Science on Facebook: Picture of
protest.<a href="https://www.facebook.com/marchforscience/posts/836983043362678">Image
source</a></figcaption></figure><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodstock">Woodstock</a> or
“an Aquarian Exposition: 3 Days of Peace &amp; Music” festival held in
1969 reportedly attracted “over 400,000”, “450,000”, or “500,000” people
depending on the source. Let’s assume that the real number is somewhere
in-between which gets us to somewhere in the neighborhood of 500,000
people.</p><p>There are numerous aerial photos of the Woodstock crowds, some of
which you can find in<a href="https://www.gettyimages.com/photos/woodstock-and-aerial">this
image gallery from Getty images</a>.</p><h2 id="section-3">750,000</h2><p>Off to look at protests again. This time we are looking at Barcelona
where 750,000 Catalan independence supporters are demanding the release
of their leaders according to<a href="http://www.timealem.com/750000-people-flood-barcelona-demanding-release-of-catalan-leaders_d575.html">this
article</a>.</p><figure><img src="barcelona-protest-2020-11-20.jpg" alt="750,000 people flood Barcelona demanding release of Catalan leaders. Image source"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">750,000 people flood Barcelona demanding
release of Catalan leaders.<a href="http://www.timealem.com/750000-people-flood-barcelona-demanding-release-of-catalan-leaders_d575.html">Image
source</a></figcaption></figure><p>The crowd extends past the top of the frame and there’s no chance
this is the entire crowd. But you get the general idea. If you ship a
bug that affects 0.01% of the internet population, then this is a
conservative lower bound of what that angry mob would look like.</p><p>But wait, the<a href="https://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/news/non-corporate/2018/6/more-than-750-000-people-help-philippines-based-church-achieve-four-new-records-529029">Guinness
World Record for the largest charity walk/run</a> is 283,171 people at a
single venue. Have a look at that picture:</p><figure><img src="guinness-record-largest-walk-single-venu-2020-11-20.jpg" alt="Guinness Record for the largest charity walk or run at a single venue is for 283,171 people. Image Source"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Guinness Record for the largest charity
walk or run at a single venue is for 283,171 people.<a href="https://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/news/non-corporate/2018/6/more-than-750-000-people-help-philippines-based-church-achieve-four-new-records-529029">Image
Source</a></figcaption></figure><p>It seems that picture of 750,000 people doesn’t quite capture that
many people because clearly there are more people in the picture that’s
supposed to be 283k people. Which of course goes to show how hard it is
to really capture how massive a crowd 750k makes.</p><p>In an article on Wired that discusses how hard it is to estimate
crowd sizes, they note<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>:</p><blockquote><p>Every time a ton of people gather in one place, there are all sorts
of pronouncements made about how many folks really showed. The figures
rarely agree; Glenn Beck’s rally on the National Mall this summer
attracted a million people, according to Beck cohort Rep. Michelle
Bachman. CBS News pegged it at more like 87,000.</p></blockquote><h2 id="and-more">And More</h2><p>I’m going to give up at this point. Pictures purportedly of around
one million people are mostly parts of crowds that have been estimated
to be that big.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Note that fig. 2 indicates that the estimate is 49% of
the population would have internet access in 2017. It’s likely that by
2021 we’d at least have reached 50% based on the sharp growth curve.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p><a href="https://www.wired.com/2011/02/how-many-people-are-in-tahrir-square-heres-how-to-tell/">How
Many People Are in Tahrir Square? Here’s How to Tell</a><a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Fart Limit</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/fart-limit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 11:30:18 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/fart-limit/</guid><description>Can a fart be fatal? Let’s see what science and OSHA have to say.</description><content:encoded><p>Thanks to<a href="https://youtu.be/suwg7-y70FQ">Vsauce</a> for
bringing this particular issue to our attention. The TL;DR of that video
is:</p><ul><li>Most of the gases in your farts are odorless.</li><li>The one that usually makes things stinky is Hydrogen Sulfide.<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a></li><li>The content of H_2_S in a fart is around 50ppm.<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a></li><li>One fart can travel around 10 ft/s.</li></ul><p>Enter<a href="https://www.osha.gov/hydrogen-sulfide/hazards">OSHA</a>:</p><ul><li>H_2_S at a concentration of 50ppm (roughly what you’d get if you
inhaled a fart directly into your lungs) you’d suffer<em>Slight
conjunctivitis (“gas eye”) and respiratory tract irritation after 1
hour. May cause digestive upset and loss of appetite.</em><a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a>.</li><li>Any practical dosage would be around 3ppm. At that rate it would be<em>Odor becomes more offensive at 3-5 ppm. Above 30 ppm, odor described
as sweet or sickeningly sweet.</em>. The key point here is that around
10 times the usual dosage, a fart won’t stink. Instead it will smell
“sweet.”</li><li>At 100ppm – which is around 30 times the usual dose – you won’t
smell anything at all because you’ll lose your sense of smell
(<em>olfactory fatigue or paralysis</em>).</li><li>At 1000ppm – 300 times the usual dose – it’s<strong>nearly instant
death</strong>.</li></ul><p>So I guess it is in fact possible.</p><p>As an aside, I found it quite disappointing that the<strong>Listen</strong> button on the<a href="https://kidshealth.org/en/kids/fart.html">“What’s a Fart” page on
KidsHealth.org</a> doesn’t make a fart sound. I mean, what else was that
button supposed to do?</p><figure><img src="images/kids-health-fart.png" alt="KidsHealth: What’s a Fart?"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">KidsHealth: What’s a Fart?</figcaption></figure><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>https://web.archive.org/web/20210614200353/https://www.houstonmethodist.org/blog/articles/2020/oct/flatulence-everything-you-wanted-to-know-about-farting/<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p>https://www.chemistryworld.com/news/explainer-the-chemistry-of-farts/2500168.article<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn3"><p>https://www.osha.gov/hydrogen-sulfide/hazards<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Shannon Paper</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/shannon-paper/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 16:14:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/shannon-paper/</guid><description>Claude Shannon’s &lt;em>A mathematical theory of communication&lt;/em> is
an oft cited classic in information theory. Let’s dive in and try to
tease apart the “why”s that are often overlooked when people build on
top of the introduced theory. They are definitely things that I didn’t
consider to be obvious without the benefit of reading the paper.</description><content:encoded><p>Claude Shannon’s<em>A mathematical theory of communication</em> is
an oft cited classic in information theory. In fact, as of this writing
there are 84’411 citations and 139 versions of the article on Google
Scholar.</p><figure><img src="images/google-scholar-shannon-citations.png" alt="Screenshot of Google Scholar showing citation count for Shannon’s paper"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Screenshot of Google Scholar showing
citation count for Shannon’s paper</figcaption></figure><p>Let’s dive in and try to tease apart the “why”s that are often
overlooked when people build on top of the introduced theory. They are
definitely things that I didn’t consider to be obvious without the
benefit of reading the paper.</p><p>The section headings below correspond to the sections in Shannon’s
paper.</p><h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2><p>The paper’s introduction states the purpose as:</p><blockquote><p>… [To] extend [the general theory of communication] to include a
number of new factors, in particular the effect of noise in the channel,
and the savings possible due to the statistical structure of the
original message and due to the nature of the final destination of
information.</p></blockquote><p>The two most salient points from this section are</p><ol type="1"><li>the arguments for a logarithmic measure of information, and</li><li>what a measure of information actually measures.</li></ol><p>Logarithmic measures are well suited for measuring information,
Shannon states, because it’s<em>“nearer to our intuitive feeling as to
the proper measure.”</em> Additional rationalization exists in the
paper, but I found this to be the most convincing.</p><p>To intuit, adding a channel that’s equal in capacity to an existing
channel increases the space of transferrable messages quadratically.
However our intuition finds it easier to think of this as doubling the
capacity. The latter is more in line with a logarithmic measure.</p><p>Information is what’s ultimately useful for the recipient. Hence a
measure of information must be based on the ability gained by the
recipient upon receipt of the message. Receiving a signal means that the
recipient can now uniquely identify a message among a large number of
possible messages, or to reduce the space of possible messages.</p><p><strong>If the destination receives 10 bits of information, that
means that the recipient is now able to uniquely select a message from<span class="math inline">2^{10}</span> possible messages.</strong> Or
equivalently, the recipient can choose one out of<span class="math inline">2^{10}</span> outcomes.</p><p>Hence the measure of information is based on the ratio of the space
of possible messages before and after receipt of the information.</p><p>The following sections focus on defining and measuring the space of
messages.</p><h2 id="part-i-discrete-noiseless-systems">Part I: Discrete Noiseless
Systems</h2><p>A discrete noiseless channel is one in which a selection of symbols
from a finite alphabet can be transmitted from a source to a destination
without loss. It’s not necessarily the case that each symbol consumes an
equal amount of resources to send. Since the paper pertains to
electronic communication Shannon states the cost in terms of time.</p><h3 id="discrete-noiseless-channel">1. Discrete Noiseless Channel</h3><p>Capacity of a channel is defined to be the maximum amount of
information that can be transferred over that channel.</p><p>The capacity<span class="math inline">C</span> of a discrete
noiseless channel is defined to be:</p><p><span class="math display">C = \lim_{T \to \infty} \frac{\log
N(T)}{T}</span></p><p>Here<span class="math inline">N(T)</span> is the number of allowed
messages that take a duration of<span class="math inline">T</span> to
transmit. Let’s see how this comes about.</p><p>From the prior definition of information, if the recipient receives<span class="math inline">C</span> bits of information that means that
they were able to distinguish between<span class="math inline">2^C</span> possible messages.</p><p>So we start with counting the number of possible messages that
could’ve been transmitted over<span class="math inline">T</span> time.
If we denote this count as<span class="math inline">N(T)</span>, then
we know that there were<span class="math inline">\log{N(T)}</span> bits
of information transferred during<span class="math inline">T</span>
time. Hence the rate is:</p><p><span class="math display">R(T) = \frac{\log{N(T)}}{T}</span></p><p>To generalize, we find the limit of<span class="math inline">R(T)</span> as<span class="math inline">T</span>
tends to<span class="math inline">\infty</span>.</p><p>Suppose the channel can transmit<span class="math inline">n</span>
symbols<span class="math inline">{S_1, S_2, ..., S_n}</span> each of
which consume<span class="math inline">{t_1, t_2, ..., t_n}</span>
units of time. How many possible messages can there be in<span class="math inline">T</span> units of time? I.e. what’s<span class="math inline">N(T)</span>?</p><p>To break this down a bit further, we can ask<em>“how many possible
messages could there be that end in<span class="math inline">S_i</span>
during time period<span class="math inline">T</span>?”</em></p><p>Any message that ends in<span class="math inline">S_i</span> can be
written as a message consisting of arbitrary symbols<span class="math inline">s_1 s_2 ... s_k</span> (where each<span class="math inline">s_i \in S</span>) and ending with the symbol<span class="math inline">S_i</span>. I.e.:</p><p><span class="math display">\underbrace{\underbrace{s_1 s_2 s_3 ...
s_k}_{T - t_i \text{ seconds}} S_i}_{T \text{ seconds}}</span></p><p>As shown, the length of the<span class="math inline">s_1..s_k</span>
portion in time must be<span class="math inline">T - t_i</span> since
the remaining<span class="math inline">t_i</span> time is consumed by<span class="math inline">S_i</span>.</p><p>Hence there can be<span class="math inline">N(T - t_i)</span>
possibilities for the<span class="math inline">s_1 ... s_k</span>
prefix.</p><p>Thus we can state this problem recursively as follows:</p><p><span class="math display">N(T) = N(T - t_1) + N(T - t_2) + ... + N(T
- t_n)</span></p><p>… where<span class="math inline">N(T) = 0</span> for all<span class="math inline">T \lt \min(t_1, t_2, ... t_n)</span>.</p><p>Solving this equation involves recognizing that this is a<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_difference_equation">linear
difference equation</a> (not to be confused with a linear<em>differential</em> equation).</p><p><strong>If all<span class="math inline">t_i</span> are
distinct</strong>, then the characteristic polynomial corresponding to
this recurrence is:</p><p><span class="math display">X^{-t_1} + X^{-t_2} + ... + X^{-t_n} =
1</span></p><p>If<span class="math inline">X_0</span> is the largest real solution
to the characteristic equation, then<span class="math inline">N(T)</span> approaches<span class="math inline">X_0^T</span> for large<span class="math inline">T</span>.</p><p>(I need to check the math here since Shannon just says this is a well
known result and moves on.)</p><p>So now we have:</p><p><span class="math display">C = \lim_{T \to \infty} \frac{\log
N(T)}{T} = \log X_0</span></p><h3 id="the-discrete-source-of-information">2. The Discrete Source of
information</h3><p>This section of the paper focuses on defining what at discrete source
of information is. For our purposes it can be thought of as a stochastic
process which produces a stream of symbols.</p><h3 id="discrete-approximations-to-english">3. Discrete Approximations
to English</h3><p>Here we come to word and sentence generation using stochastic
processes. In particular Shannon takes us through the progression of
constructing messages via:</p><ol type="1"><li>Zero-order approximation. Symbols are individual letters with the
addition of a space. Each symbol is selected with equal
probability.</li><li>First-order approximation. As above, but the relative frequencies
correspond to actual letter frequencies in English.</li><li>Second-order approximation. As above, but selection of a symbol
depends on the previous symbol. I.e. follows a digram structure.
Probabilities correspond to English.</li><li>Third-order approximation. As above, but using trigrams instead of
digrams.</li><li>First-order word approximation. Start with a list of words and pick
them at random with probability corresponding to their usage in
English.</li><li>Second-order word approximation. As above, but selection frequencies
depend on the previous word. I.e. follows digrams.</li></ol><p>By the time we arrive at second-order word approximations, the
generated messages start to resemble natural English albeit
nonsensical.</p><h3 id="graphical-representation-of-a-markoff-process">4. Graphical
Representation of a Markoff process</h3><p>Identifies the previous stochastic processes as Markoff processes.
They are represented as a set of states. Each state can
probabilistically transition to number of states with some probability
distribution. Each transition emits a symbol.</p><p>If the emitted symbol doesn’t depend on any prior symbol, then we
only really need one state. It will have a self-edge for each possible
emitted symbol.</p><figure><img src="bd8dee1827299ffe57cd28ba5ce0c692e6d6b9ac.svg"/></figure><p>If the emitted symbol depends on the previous symbol, then there will
be as many states needed as there are symbols. This is the case for
digrams.</p><figure><img src="f9fa7c718ef9a3a8831a3d06ef1ddfe65a1b342e.svg"/></figure><p>For trigrams, since they depend on the previous two symbols, require<span class="math inline">n^2</span> states.</p><h3 id="ergodic-and-mixed-sources">5. Ergodic and Mixed Sources</h3><blockquote><p>In an ergodic process every sequence produced by the process is the
same in statistical properties. […] Roughly the ergodic property means
statistical homogeneity.</p></blockquote><h3 id="choice-uncertainty-and-entropy">6. Choice Uncertainty and
Entropy</h3><p>Here we come to the part that is most often cited. The definition of
entropy.</p><p>Shannon lays out three requirements for a measure of information<span class="math inline">H(p_1, p_2, .. p_n)</span> which measures the
information content of a set of outcomes each of whose probability is<span class="math inline">p_i</span>:</p><ol type="1"><li><span class="math inline">H</span> should be continuous in the<span class="math inline">p_i</span>.</li><li>If all<span class="math inline">p_i</span> are equal, i.e. <span class="math inline">p_i = \frac{1}{n}</span> then<span class="math inline">H</span> should be a monotonic increasing function
of<span class="math inline">n</span>.</li><li>If a choice be broken down into two choices, then the original<span class="math inline">H</span> should be the weighted sum of the
individual values of<span class="math inline">H</span>.</li></ol><blockquote><p>The only<span class="math inline">H</span> satisfying the above
three requirements is of the form:<span class="math display">H = -K
\sum_{i=1}^n p_i \log p_i</span></p></blockquote><p>The constant<span class="math inline">K</span> is merely a unit of
measure and can be set to 1.</p><p>Some interesting properties of<span class="math inline">H</span>:</p><ol type="1"><li><span class="math inline">H = 0</span> only when all but one<span class="math inline">p_i = 0</span>, and the remaining<span class="math inline">p_j = 1</span>.</li><li>For a given<span class="math inline">n</span>, the maximum<span class="math inline">H</span> is reached when all<span class="math inline">p_i = \frac{1}{n}</span>.</li><li>The joint entropy of two random variables follow the relation:<span class="math display">H(x,y) \le H(x) + H(y)</span> The condition of
equality implies that<span class="math inline">x</span> and<span class="math inline">y</span> are independent.</li><li>Any change towards equalization of probabilities<span class="math inline">p_i</span> increases<span class="math inline">H</span>. I.e. if<span class="math inline">p_1 \lt
p_2</span> and<span class="math inline">\delta \lt |p_1 - p_2|</span>,
then the entropy of<span class="math inline">p_1, p_2, ... p_n</span>
is lower than the entropy of<span class="math inline">(p_1 + \delta),
(p_2 - \delta), p_3, ... p_n</span>.</li><li>For two variables<span class="math inline">x,y</span>,there’s
conditional probability<span class="math inline">p_i(j)</span> of<span class="math inline">y</span> having value<span class="math inline">j</span> assuming<span class="math inline">x</span>
has value<span class="math inline">i</span>. This is given by:<span class="math display">p_i(j) = \frac{p(i,j)}{\sum_j p(i,j)}</span> The
corresponding conditional entropy<span class="math inline">H_x(y)</span> is given by:<span class="math display">H_x(y) = - \sum_{i,j} p(i,j) \log p_i(j)</span>
This conditional entropy then holds the relation:<span class="math display">H(x,y) = H(x) + H_x(y)</span></li><li>From 3 and 5, we have:<span class="math display">H(y) \le
H_x(y)</span></li></ol><h3 id="the-entropy-of-an-information-source">7. The Entropy of an
Information Source</h3><p>Let<span class="math inline">S_i</span> be a set of states each of
which produce some set of outputs<span class="math inline">s_j</span>
with probability<span class="math inline">p_{i,j}</span>.</p><p>Each state<span class="math inline">S_i</span> has an associated
entropy<span class="math inline">H_i</span> representing the entropy of
all possible outputs from that state. I.e.:</p><p><span class="math display">H_i = - \sum_j p_{i,j} \log
p_{i,j}</span></p><p>Each such state also has a probability of occurrence<span class="math inline">P_i</span>.</p><p>The entropy of the entire information source is the weighted sum of
the state-wise entropies. The weight being the probability of
occurrence. Thus:</p><p><span class="math display">\begin{align*}
H &amp; = \sum_i P_i H_i \\
&amp; = - \sum_{i,j} P_i p_{i,j} \log p_{i,j}
\end{align*}</span></p><p>If the source is operating at some definite time rate, then the<strong>entropy per second</strong>, or<strong>entropy rate</strong> is<em>defined</em> to be:</p><p><span class="math display">H' = \sum_i f_i H_i</span></p><p>where<span class="math inline">f_i</span> is the average frequency
of state<span class="math inline">i</span>.</p><p>Shannon says “Clearly<span class="math inline">H' = mH</span>
where<span class="math inline">m</span> is the average number of
symbols produced per second.” But in order to make the connection you
need to observe that<span class="math inline">f_i = m \cdot
P_i</span>.</p><p>This is followed by a derivation that takes some work to follow.
Let’s go through it step by step:</p><ol type="1"><li><p>Suppose that the information source consists of a single state
and<span class="math inline">n</span> symbols each of which is emitted
with a probability of<span class="math inline">p_i</span>.</p></li><li><p>Now take a string of length<span class="math inline">N</span>
emitted by this source. The expected number of occurrences for symbol<span class="math inline">s_i</span> is<span class="math inline">N
p_i</span>.</p></li><li><p>A message of sufficient length where all symbols appear at their
expected occurrence count would have a probability of occurring of:</p><p><span class="math display">p = \prod_i p_i^{N p_i}</span></p></li></ol><p>From there we see that:</p><p><span class="math display">\begin{align*}
\log p &amp; = \sum_i N p_i \log p_i \\
&amp; = N H
\end{align*}</span></p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Sometimes It's the Interviewers Who Suck</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/sometimes-its-the-interviewers-who-suck/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 19:09:49 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/sometimes-its-the-interviewers-who-suck/</guid><description>I’ve done hundreds of interviews. I’ve also served in numerous hiring committees over the years.
Tech companies tend to have cultures built around tech people interviewing other tech people, typically in what is not-so-affectionately known as the “Tech interview.” This is good because candidates would be evaluated based on their actual skills instead of keywords in their resume. Interviewers are in effect choosing their future coworkers which makes in interview serve the interest of both the interviewer and the interviewee.</description><content:encoded><p>I’ve done hundreds of interviews. I’ve also served in numerous hiring
committees over the years.</p><p>Tech companies tend to have cultures built around tech people
interviewing other tech people, typically in what is
not-so-affectionately known as the “Tech interview.” This is good
because candidates would be evaluated based on their actual skills
instead of keywords in their resume. Interviewers are in effect choosing
their future coworkers which makes in interview serve the interest of
both the interviewer and the interviewee. However candidates – at least
the one who didn’t get accepted according to exit polls – tend to hate
these.</p><p>The goal of the tech interview is to assess how well the candidate
will be able to perform in the role as a tech worker. Unfortunately the
typical problems that one would encounter during the course of a career
in tech aren’t easy to replicate within a 40-60 minute interview. So
partly the criticism is around the fact that such interviews bear little
resemblance to what the actual job would entail. Deciphering what
happens during an interview and distilling it into a prediction of
future success is quite difficult in the best of times.</p><p>Making this much worse is the undeniable fact that many if not most<em>tech workers are just not good interviewers</em>.</p><p>This is as true as a claim that most tech workers aren’t good
managers – whether it’s managing projects or people. Interview follow-up
don’t take this factor into consideration quite as much as they
should.</p><p>My anecdotal evidence is that when presented with the artifacts from
a bad interview, hiring committees will disproportionately blame the
candidate for it. After all if the candidate was really good, they
would’ve potentially salvaged the interview. The problem
disproportionately affects candidates who are near the middle of the
skill curve where things can probably go one way or the other depending
on the combination of question asked, and caliber of the interview.</p><p>Interviews at Google famously involve a bunch of paperwork where each
interviewer is expected to produce some verbose artifacts detailing what
happened. Since these artifacts come from the interviewer, hiring
committees need to exercise some due diligence to discern what actually
happened based on the writeup. So how do we go about spotting bad
interviews?</p><h2 id="the-writeup-is-terse.">The writeup is terse.</h2><p>Not in and of itself a conclusive sign, but if the writeup doesn’t
have any details that a committee could use to form a decision, it’s
likely a sign that the interview didn’t really gather much information
about the candidate in the first place. Typically these kinds of
writeups are from novice interviewers who don’t know what to write
about.</p><h2 id="the-writeup-uses-adversarial-framing.">The writeup uses
adversarial framing.</h2><p>A very frequent problem specially with novice interviewers is that
they go into the interview thinking that it is some sort of competition
between the interviewer and the interviewee. The interviewer might
consider it a<em>bad</em> thing if a candidate were to hit their
question out of the park. Some of this comes from a certain level of
imposter syndrome where they don’t want to come across as less smart
than the candidate. Either way this mentality comes across during the
interview as hostile or condescending.</p><h2 id="the-interviewer-takes-too-much-pleasure-in-the-interviewees-misery.">The
interviewer takes too much pleasure in the interviewee’s misery.</h2><p>Each mistake is gloated on while points at which the interviewee
obviously shone are muted.</p><h2 id="the-question-is-unnecessarily-hard.">The question is
unnecessarily hard.</h2><p>Solving a hard question that requires a great deal of time and
thought is very satisfying. But it isn’t what you do on a day-to-day
basis.</p><h2 id="the-interviewer-allows-the-interviewee-to-march-into-the-weeds-without-helping-them-back.">The
interviewer allows the interviewee to march into the weeds without
helping them back.</h2><p>The interviewer has the luxury of having seen the question beforehand
and also having studied possible solutions to it. They should be
familiar enough with the question that they could spot
misunderstandings, misconceptions, and common mistakes. How a candidate
notices a misstep and how they dig themselves out is important to note.
However, letting the candidate languish in a dead-end while the clock
ticks away the remaining minutes of an interview does not help
anyone.</p><h2 id="obvious-misunderstandings-are-not-corrected.">Obvious
misunderstandings are not corrected.</h2><p>It is the interviewer’s responsibility to explain the problem
clearly. The problem itself doesn’t need to be fully explained since
there’s much value in seeing how a candidate explores and understands
the problem area. However if it is obvious that the candidate has
fundamentally misunderstood some critical aspect of the question, the
interviewer should step in and intervene<strong>early</strong>. We all
misunderstand things, specially when they aren’t clearly explained. It’s
not useful to knowingly send a candidate down the wrong path.</p><h2 id="the-interviewer-seemed-annoyed-or-angry.">The interviewer seemed
annoyed or angry.</h2><p>This one should be self explanatory. The candidate is anxious enough
as it is. The interviewer should not frustrate the interviewee’s
attempts at asking questions and seeking clarity around the question.
It’s likely that while the problem is obvious to one, the problem area
may be unfamiliar to others who may need extra help figuring their way
around. In fact the ability to resolve such ambiguities and seek clarity
are<em>good</em>. If the interviewer actively discourages such inquiry
that’s on the interviewer – not the candidate.</p><h2 id="one-interview-diverges-significantly-from-others.">One interview
diverges significantly from others.</h2><p>There’s more than one interview for a reason. If one interview
highlights an area as being weak while another interview highlights the
same area as being strong, then there’s something going on that needs
scrutiny. There can be many reasons why a candidate bombs an interview.
Not all of them say anything bad about their ability to function well in
their job. The causes should be teased out.</p><hr/><p>What happens when an interview is pretty much unsalvageable? It might
be that the writeup is inconclusive due to issues such as those
highlighted above. A committee could ignore that specific interview and
base their decision on the other interviews, or failing that schedule
another interview to account for the lack of decisive information.</p><p>From a candidate’s point of view, it is<strong>really</strong>
important that they report any unpleasant interactions to one’s
recruiter immediately after the interview. This allows a recruiter to go
to bat for you and perhaps get you another interview if appropriate.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>On WontFixing Bugs</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/on-wontfixing-bugs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2021 17:15:06 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/on-wontfixing-bugs/</guid><description>&lt;p>Large projects accumulate a large number of issue reports over time.
This is normal. Typically for a “successful” project the rate of new
issues being reported will exceed the rate of issues being fixed. Hence
the growth.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But what are they to do about this ever-growing pile of bugs?&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><p>This was partly inspired by a Tweet by a co-worker. The tweet is:</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">wontfix-ing valid bugs (that have been triaged as such) with bots because you haven't been able to fix or prioritize them yet is kinda hostile to contributors, imho<a href="https://t.co/faxtbpoiII">pic.twitter.com/faxtbpoiII</a></p>&mdash; Mike Taylor (@miketaylr)<a href="https://twitter.com/miketaylr/status/1366762904851279877?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 2, 2021</a></blockquote><script async= src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"/><p>For projects that are under-resourced but has heavy usage it is in
fact quite normal to accumulate a large number of issue reports over
time. Take Chromium for example. There are (at the time of writing)
~95,000 open bugs. Many of these are task tracking bugs rather than
tracking actual product bugs. But still that’s a lot of real bugs.</p><p>What’s even more interesting is the accumulation of bugs. Typically
for a “successful” project the rate of new issues being reported will
exceed the rate of issues being fixed. Hence the growth.</p><h2 id="what-matters">What Matters …</h2><p>Issues are often annotated to indicate some measure of<em>severity</em> and<em>priority</em>. These are two different axes of
measurement:</p><p><strong>Severity</strong> refers to the degree of impact that an
issue has. How many users are affected? Is the effect isolated or spread
across a large user base? Severity is supposed to summarize the answer
to these questions.</p><p><strong>Priority</strong> refers to what the issue triagers deemed to
be the relative importance of the issue. A bug that affects a large
number of users – hence a high severity – might not be a high priority
due to mitigating factors. Typically a project owner would tackle higher
priority issues first. Under-resourced projects – which is the case for
pretty much every successful project I’ve seen – will accumulate lower
priority issues across time.</p><p>Neither<em>severity</em> nor<em>priority</em> are static either. An
issue with a low severity might be elevated to a higher severity if the
affected population of users is discovered to be larger than originally
assumed. Or the priority may be raised if the issue is blocking the fix
for another more severe issue. It’s not uncommon for some low priority
issue to be suddenly elevated to critical status once someone figures
out how to exploit it.</p><p>In practice<em>perceptual priority</em> is the only one that
matters. It doesn’t matter what the issue tracker label or score is.
What matters is that there’s a contributor who’s motivated to fix it.
The decisions of a contributor are complex and subjective. So while the
most important issues will<em>likely</em> get fixed, just because an
issue is real or important doesn’t mean that it will be addressed.</p><p>What this means is that it is important for issue reports to stick
around. At worst they will accumulate more evidence of severity or clues
to what the issue is. Often the desired outcome isn’t universal either.
So an issue report also functions as an opinion catchment area where
interested parties can hash out their differences.</p><h2 id="and-what-doesnt">And What Doesn’t …</h2><p>However, the health of the project then depends on not only handling
new issues, but also in how they shepherd existing or known issues.</p><p>Much like any other todo list, the effectiveness of the issue tracker
decreases when there’s an overwhelming number of items to look at. The
cognitive overhead of correct prioritizing increases dramatically, as
does the time it takes for triaging.</p><h2 id="strategies-that-dont-work">Strategies That Don’t Work …</h2><p>So projects tend to use various techniques to deal with the growing
pile of issues. The more overwhelming it is, the more drastic the
mitigation strategy.</p><p>One such strategy in action is what we see in the Tweet above where
there’s a bot that automatically closes old issues that haven’t seen any
activity. At first glance this seems to make sense.</p><p>The assumption seems to be that if the issue was important enough
then an endless stream of users would pipe up on the bug with “me too”s
to keep the issue open. The issue tracker is now a battlefield where
issue reporters have to continually work to keep the issue alive until a
contributor takes pity and addresses it.</p><p>Issue reporters themselves who are often volunteers who are electing
to participate in a project can also burn out. If the issues they file
are automatically closed, it’s frustrating to the reporters. Chances are
that with every few issues that are closed due to inactivity, the
project loses a contributor.</p><p>Another strategy is to have new issues start at some sort of<em>unconfirmed</em> state. Once the issue has been acknowledged and
accepted it can proceed to some other state which makes the issue become
a candidate for contributor consideration. This one is a bit better in
that it doesn’t discard<em>confirmed</em> issues.</p><p>However, eventually the real issues will accumulate to the point
where some sort of bookkeeping is needed. Along comes<code>WontFix</code> and friends. This is a state where the issue is
marked as<em>“this is a real issue but we will probably never get
around to fixing it.”</em></p><p>Reporters nevertheless find this state to be no-less frustrating than
an outright closure.<code>WontFix</code>ed bugs don’t show up by
default in issue searches, so they are effectively undiscoverable to
future issue reporters. All time invested in that issue is now lost.</p><h2 id="and-one-that-does">And One That Does? …</h2><p>The alternative is to just leave the issue open, but lower the
priority down to something that reflects the current opinion of the
project maintainers.</p><p>This strategy acknowledges that the issue is real. It serves as
documentation that the product has a known defect, and in addition it
can serve the purposes of accumulating evidence of severity along the
way. If the issue becomes prominent enough then it can be retriaged.</p><p>That’s it. So far I haven’t seen alternatives that are much better
than this. I’m generally against mass issue closing events like
declaring “bug bankruptcy.” The bugs don’t care about the state of the
issue report. All you’ve accomplished is to throw away the accumulated
history and evidence of a defect.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Deriving the Poisson Distribution</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/poisson-distribution/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 11:13:39 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/poisson-distribution/</guid><description>Where does the Poisson Distribution come from?
A little bit of research1 tells us that the distribution was originally introduced by Abraham de Moivre in 1710 in an article called “On the Measurement of Chance, or, on the Probability of Events in Games Depending Upon Fortuitous Chance” 2 (not the original title).
A few steps that will get us there is laid out below.
Let’s start with a simple “rate” problem.</description><content:encoded><p>Where does the Poisson Distribution come from?</p><p>A little bit of research<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> tells us that the
distribution was originally introduced by<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham_de_Moivre">Abraham de
Moivre</a> in 1710 in an article called<em>“On the Measurement of
Chance, or, on the Probability of Events in Games Depending Upon
Fortuitous Chance”</em><a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a> (not the original title).</p><p>A few steps that will get us there is laid out below.</p><p>Let’s start with a simple “rate” problem.</p><blockquote><p>How likely is it that you’ll receive 12 visits next week given that
you had 10 visitors this week?</p></blockquote><p>This is clearly not a question to be answered based on a lot of
information. However when the assumption is that<em>on average</em> you
get 10 visitors a week, then the question sounds a bit more
reasonable.</p><p>While we say the<em>rate</em> is 10 visitors per week, that’s
obviously not going to be uniformly distributed. Maybe given the nature
of your site, people are more likely to visit over the week-end rather
than during the week. However for the purpose of this analysis we are
going to assume that the rate is uniform.</p><p>Simplifying things a bit more, we can ask the question in a different
way:</p><blockquote><p>How likely is that that the rate of visitors for your site will be<span class="math inline">\frac{12}{7}</span> per day next week given
that the usual rate is<span class="math inline">\frac{10}{7}</span> per
day?</p></blockquote><p>Or in another way:</p><blockquote><p>How likely is that that the rate of visitors for your site will be<span class="math inline">\frac{12}{7 * 24}</span> per hour next week
given that the usual rate is<span class="math inline">\frac{10}{7 *
24}</span> per hour?</p></blockquote><p>Why do this? Without much explanation this reformulation gets us to a
rate that’s less than one per unit of time being considered. This way we
can now look at each time unit and assume that we’ll either get 1
visitor or none any given hour.</p><p>So each hour, there’s a probability of<span class="math inline">\lambda</span> that there will be a user, and<span class="math inline">1 - \lambda</span> that there won’t. Here we are
using<span class="math inline">\lambda = \frac{10}{7 * 24}</span> for
convenience. The latter is also the “rate” of events or arrivals. The
term<em>arrivals</em> or<em>occurrences</em> is common in
literature.</p><p>The probability that there will be 12 visitors is the probability
that there will be 12 hour slots where there’s an arrival and the rest
will be slots without an arrival.</p><p>Treating this as a list of one-hour “slots”, the outcome would look
like:</p><table style="width:82%;"><colgroup><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 4%"/><col style="width: 7%"/><col style="width: 4%"/></colgroup><tbody><tr class="odd"><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>…</td><td>0</td></tr></tbody></table><p>The number in each box is the number of arrivals during that slot
which is either 1 or 0. So there are<span class="math inline">2^n</span> possible outcomes where<span class="math inline">n = 7 * 24</span>. Each 1 has a probability of<span class="math inline">\lambda</span> and 0 has a probability of<span class="math inline">1 - \lambda</span>.</p><p>So for there to be exactly<span class="math inline">k</span>
arrivals – where<span class="math inline">k = 12</span> which is the
target – there needs to be<span class="math inline">k</span> ones and<span class="math inline">n - k</span> zeros.</p><p>So the probability of one of those events happening is<span class="math inline">\lambda^k (1 - \lambda)^{n-k}</span>.</p><p>But there are lots of ways of choosing<span class="math inline">k</span> boxes out of<span class="math inline">n</span>. In fact there is exactly<span class="math inline">\binom{n}{k}</span> ways.</p><p>So the probability of getting exactly<span class="math inline">k</span> arrivals is:</p><p><span class="math display">\Pr(k) = \binom{n}{k} \lambda^k
(1-\lambda)^{n - k}</span></p><p>With me so far?</p><p>Astute readers will note that we did some hand-waving up there.
Specifically we assumed that the possibilities for any 1-hour block is
either there being an arrival or there not being one. This isn’t always
the case since there could be more than 1 arrival in any given hour.</p><p>One way to address this is to consider increasingly smaller units of
time. For example, if we divide the one-hour block into<span class="math inline">m</span> equal sized pieces then it’ll be a bit more
likely – assuming<span class="math inline">m \gt 1</span> – that there
will be at most 1 arrival during that time period. In fact if<span class="math inline">m</span> is very large, then it is increasingly
likely that the choices are either 1 or 0.</p><p>So the number of boxes is now<span class="math inline">n*m</span>,
and the probability of an arrival during any single timeslot is now<span class="math inline">\frac{λ}{m}</span>. Substituting these, our
new probability is:</p><p><span class="math display">\Pr(k) = \binom{nm}{k} \left(
\frac{\lambda}{m} \right)^k \left(1 - \frac{\lambda}{m}\right)^{nm -
k}</span></p><p>Alright. We are getting somewhere now. The next step is to increase<span class="math inline">m</span> all the way to<span class="math inline">\infty</span>.</p><p><span class="math display">\begin{align*}
\lim_{m \to \infty} \Pr(k) &amp; = \lim_{m \to \infty} \binom{n*m}{k} (
\frac{λ}{m} )^k (1 - \frac{λ}{m})^{nm - k} \\
&amp; = \lim_{m → \infty} \frac{(nm)!}{k! (nm - k)!} ( \frac{λ}{m} )^k
(1 - \frac{λ}{m})^{nm - k}
\end{align*}</span></p><p>The right side looks a bit daunting, the we can simplify things quite
a bit by looking at each part separately.</p><p>For example:</p><p><span class="math display">\begin{align*}
\binom{nm}{k}\left( \frac{\lambda}{m} \right)^k &amp; = \frac{(nm)!}{k!
(nm - k)!}\left( \frac{\lambda}{m} \right)^k \\
&amp; = \frac{nm \cdot (nm - 1) \cdot (nm - 2) \cdot ... (nm - k +
1)}{k!}\left( \frac{\lambda}{m} \right)^k \\
&amp; = \left( \frac{nm}{m} \right) \left( \frac{nm - 1}{m}\right) ...
\left( \frac{nm - k + 1}{m}\right) \frac{\lambda^k}{k!}
\end{align*}</span></p><p>Furthermore:</p><p><span class="math display">\left( \frac{nm}{m} \right) \left(
\frac{nm - 1}{m}\right) ... \left( \frac{nm - k + 1}{m}\right)
\frac{\lambda^k}{k!} = \frac{\lambda^k}{k!}\prod_{i=0}^{k-1} \left(n -
\frac{k - i}{m}\right)</span></p><p>As<span class="math inline">\lim_{m → \infty}</span> we see that<span class="math inline">\frac{k-i}{m}</span> tends to<span class="math inline">0</span>. This makes our lives a bit easier.</p><p>Now we have:</p><p><span class="math display">\begin{align*}
\Pr(k) &amp;= \lim_{m \to \infty}\frac{(n \lambda)^k}{k!} \left(1 -
\frac{\lambda}{m} \right)^{nm - k} \\
&amp;= \lim_{m \to \infty}\frac{(n \lambda)^k}{k!} \left(1 -
\frac{\lambda}{m} \right)^{nm(1 - \frac{k}{nm})}\end{align*}</span></p><p>Remember that:</p><p><span class="math display">\lim_{n \to \infty} \left( 1 + \frac{x}{n}
\right)^n = e^x</span></p><p>So substituting<span class="math inline">n \to nm</span> and<span class="math inline">x \to - \lambda n</span> gets us:</p><p><span class="math display">\lim_{nm \to \infty} \left( 1 -
\frac{\lambda}{m} \right)^{nm} = e^{- \lambda n}</span></p><p>Now going back to<span class="math inline">\Pr(k)</span>:</p><p><span class="math display">\Pr(k) = \frac{(n \lambda)^k e^{- \lambda
n}}{k!}</span></p><p>Let’s do another substitution. Remember that<span class="math inline">\lambda</span> is the number of arrivals during<span class="math inline">n</span> time periods. If we consider<span class="math inline">n</span> time periods (originally hours) to be a
single unit of time, then our rate of arrivals is<span class="math inline">\lambda n</span>. So without loss of generality
let’s substitute<span class="math inline">\lambda n \to
\lambda</span>.</p><p>This gives us:</p><p><span class="math display">\Pr(k) = \frac{\lambda^k e^{-
\lambda}}{k!}</span></p><p>… which is the PDF of the Poisson distribution.</p><p>n.b.: In retrospect it would’ve been easier to consider the unit of
time to be<span class="math inline">n</span> hours in the first place,
but I’m too lazy to go back and rewrite everything.</p><p>…</p><p>…</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Also known as reading the relevant Wikipedia article. In
this case that’s the<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poisson_distribution#History"><em>History</em>
section of the article on the Poisson distribution</a>.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p><a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstl.1710.0018">The
original article in Latin</a> is available via<a href="https://royalsociety.org/journals/">The Royal Society
Publishing</a>.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Ten Years</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/ten-years/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 21:41:50 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/ten-years/</guid><description>It’s been ten years since I started at Google. The work anniversary fell on 6th of December.
Ten years ago my wife and I made our way to Mountain View for my orientation; all excited for a brand new chapter in our lives. After spending a week in Mountain View / Palo Alto we both decided that California was not for us. But that’s beside the point.
I was elated. This was pretty much everything I dreamt of as a kid growing up in Sri Lanka.</description><content:encoded><p>It’s been ten years since I started at Google. The work anniversary
fell on 6th of December.</p><p>Ten years ago my wife and I made our way to Mountain View for my
orientation; all excited for a brand new chapter in our lives. After
spending a week in Mountain View / Palo Alto we both decided that
California was not for us. But that’s beside the point.</p><p>I was elated. This was pretty much everything I dreamt of as a kid
growing up in Sri Lanka. Except those days we dreamt of someday working
for Microsoft or starting our own software company.</p><p>One afternoon during orientation – maybe it was the evening, I don’t
remember – I was walking by a bunch of outdoor tables next to one of the
larger café’s at the Google HQ. As I walked by I overheard a Googler on
the phone telling someone how they just had a really shitty day. I
remember being confused. How could someone have a bad day at Google?
Inconceivable.</p><p>Obviously this feeling didn’t last. People normalize things quickly.
The problem with achieving your dreams is that now you have to make
more; an eternal treadmill. It’s nice to periodically look back though.
The novelty isn’t there anymore, but it’s humbling to recall how much we
dreamt for the things that we now take for granted.</p><p>Looking back at the last years, the things that I’m really proud of
aren’t my code contributions. If any aren’t already obsolete then by now
it’s become some legacy crap that some engineer has to maintain.</p><p>But the things that I really remember are the three times I talked
hiring committees into hiring someone they had decided not to hire.
Those were good candidates whom I thought didn’t get a fair shake.</p><p>Also I clearly remember the smart people who acknowledged and
appreciated my work. I also remember the ones that took credit for my
work or didn’t treat me with dignity, but I don’t think about them that
often.</p><p>I remember the big projects that I initiated, the big ideas I sold,
and the ones I managed to pull off.</p><p>Then there are the low points. Moments when I let people down or
burned a bridge or two for the wrong reasons.</p><p>But overall, looking back there isn’t much there. It’s surprising how
little really matters in the long run.</p><p>I should remember that the next time I feel like staying up late
trying to get something done because I feel some sort of obligation or
bigger purpose in doing it. Often there is none.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Visualizing Internet Users</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/visualizing-people/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 11:37:53 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/visualizing-people/</guid><description>What does 0.3%1 of internet users look like?
As of this writing the global population hovers around 7.7 billion according to the World Population Clock 2.
Screenshot from census.gov showing the world population clock. The International Telecommunications Union “estimates that at the end of 2019, 53.6 per cent of the global population, or 4.1 billion people, are using the internet.”3
Screenshot from itu.int showing historical internet usage numbers as a percentage of the world population So a 0.</description><content:encoded><p>What does 0.3%<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> of internet users look like?</p><p>As of this writing the global population hovers around 7.7 billion
according to the World Population Clock<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>.</p><figure><img src="images/census-gov-population-clock-2020-11-20.png" alt="Screenshot from census.gov showing the world population clock."/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Screenshot from census.gov showing the
world population clock.</figcaption></figure><p>The<a href="https://www.itu.int/">International Telecommunications
Union</a> “estimates that at the end of 2019, 53.6 per cent of the
global population, or 4.1 billion people, are using the internet.”<a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a></p><figure><img src="images/itu-internet-usage-stats-2019.jpg" alt="Screenshot from itu.int showing historical internet usage numbers as a percentage of the world population"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Screenshot from itu.int showing
historical internet usage numbers as a percentage of the world
population</figcaption></figure><p>So a 0.3% of the internet would be a roughly 12,300,000 or around
12.3 million. A nice little number.</p><h2 id="from-50-to-100000">From 50 to 100,000</h2><p>It’s interesting to try and visualize this. An example of visualizing
populations for small numbers can be found at<a href="https://blog.lime.link/visualizing-crowd-sizes/">Visualizing Crowd
Sizes</a>. It goes from around 50 people up to 100,000 people.</p><p>While 100,000 is interesting we need to go all the way to 12.3
million.</p><h2 id="section">200,000</h2><p>A particularly macabre topic these days since the United States
surpassed 200,000 deaths due to COVID-19 around September of 2020.<a href="https://www.ctpost.com/">ctpost</a> ran an article online title<a href="https://www.ctpost.com/news/coronavirus/slideshow/Analysis-What-200-000-COVID-deaths-actually-209169.php">“What
does 200,000 deaths actually look like”</a>. There are some interesting
comparisons there, but none make for a good visual. It’s just an
interesting number right now.</p><p>As for crowd sizes, 200,000 was the estimated number of people who
attended the<a href="https://marchforourlives.com/">March for Our
Lives</a> in D.C.. There aren’t any photos capturing<em>all</em>
attendees in one shot, but there are numerous pictures in<a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/march-for-our-lives-crowd-size-estimated-200000-people-attended-d-c-march/">this
CBS News article</a> to give you a good idea.</p><p>In more terrible examples,<a href="https://www.dw.com/en/more-than-200000-indonesians-protest-governor-purnamas-alleged-blasphemy/a-36611145">this
article on dw.com</a> suggests that the crowd size pictured is roughly
around 200,000 people.</p><blockquote><p>More than 200,000 conservative Muslims gathered in Indonesia’s
capital Jakarta on Friday to protest against the city’s Christian
governor, who is facing trial for blasphemy, police estimated.</p></blockquote><figure><img src="images/dw-com-indonesia-protest-2020-11-20.jpg" alt="Image from dw.com of a protest in Indonesia allegedly showing 200,000 people. Image Source"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Image from dw.com of a protest in
Indonesia allegedly showing 200,000 people.<a href="https://www.dw.com/en/more-than-200000-indonesians-protest-governor-purnamas-alleged-blasphemy/a-36611145">Image
Source</a></figcaption></figure><h2 id="section-1">500,000</h2><p>We are heading into shaky ground here. A 800*600 picture only
contains 480,000 pixels. So we are now reduced to indicating population
by inference. It is nolonger possible to capture 500,000 people in a
webpage sized picture while showing each person individually.</p><p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/philadelphia/comments/3by9g8/if_this_is_what_500k_people_look_like_xpost_from/">This
Reddit post</a> claims that there are 500k people in the picture, but I
couldn’t readily find any good references backing up that claim.</p><p>As is tradition by now, another protest that drew 500,000 people is<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/show-me/video/nearly-500-000-people-march-in-anti-violence-rally-in-barcelona-1033617987741">an
anti-violence rally in Barcelona as reported by NBC</a>. While there’s
video, the content doesn’t quite capture the massive number of people.
Also it’s “nearly 500,000” people.</p><p>However, the closest we’ll probably get to a somewhat believable
500,000 person crowd would be the March for Science. They posted the
following picture on<a href="https://www.facebook.com/marchforscience/posts/836983043362678">Facebook</a>
noting that “There are 500,000 people on strike in Montreal”.</p><figure><img src="images/march-for-science-crowd-2020-11-20.jpg" alt="March for Science on Facebook: Picture of protest"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">March for Science on Facebook: Picture of
protest</figcaption></figure><p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/marchforscience/posts/836983043362678">Image
source</a></p><h2 id="section-2">750,000</h2><p>Off to protests again. This time we are looking at Barcelona where
750,000 Catalan independence supporters are demanding the release of
their leaders according to<a href="http://www.timealem.com/750000-people-flood-barcelona-demanding-release-of-catalan-leaders_d575.html">this
article</a>.</p><figure><img src="images/barcelona-protest-2020-11-20.jpg" alt="750,000 people flood Barcelona demanding release of Catalan leaders. Image source"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">750,000 people flood Barcelona demanding
release of Catalan leaders.<a href="http://www.timealem.com/750000-people-flood-barcelona-demanding-release-of-catalan-leaders_d575.html">Image
source</a></figcaption></figure><p>The crowd extends past the top of the frame and there’s no chance
this is the entire crowd. But you get the general idea. If you ship a
bug that affects 0.01% of the internet population, then this is a
conservative lower bound of what that angry mob would look like.</p><p>But wait, the<a href="https://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/news/non-corporate/2018/6/more-than-750-000-people-help-philippines-based-church-achieve-four-new-records-529029">Guinness
World Record for teh largest charity walk/run</a> is 283,171 people at a
single venue. Have a look at that picture:</p><figure><img src="images/guinness-record-largest-walk-single-venu-2020-11-20.jpg" alt="Guinness Record for the largest charity walk or run at a single venue is for 283,171 people. Image Source"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Guinness Record for the largest charity
walk or run at a single venue is for 283,171 people.<a href="https://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/news/non-corporate/2018/6/more-than-750-000-people-help-philippines-based-church-achieve-four-new-records-529029">Image
Source</a></figcaption></figure><p>It seems that picture of 750,000 people doesn’t quite capture it
because clearly there are more people in the picture that’s supposed to
be 283k people. Which of course goes to show how hard it is to really
capture how massive a crowd 750k makes.</p><p>In an article on Wired that discusses how hard it is to estimate
crowd sizes, they note<a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"><sup>4</sup></a>:</p><blockquote><p>Every time a ton of people gather in one place, there are all sorts
of pronouncements made about how many folks really showed. The figures
rarely agree; Glenn Beck’s rally on the National Mall this summer
attracted a million people, according to Beck cohort Rep. Michelle
Bachman. CBS News pegged it at more like 87,000.</p></blockquote><h3 id="and-more">And More</h3><p>I’m going to give up at this point. Pictures purportedly of around
one million people are mostly parts of crowds that have been estimated
to be that big. Forget about 12.3 million.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Why 0.3% of the internet population? It’s a number that
came up when trying to come up with a reasonable sample size for
estimating the diversity of the internet population. There’s not much
special about it other than that.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p>The<a href="https://www.census.gov/popclock/">world
population clock</a>. This link is for the current number at whatever
time you clicked on the link assuming the site is still there. As of
November 20, 2021, the number was 7.7 billion. I’d link you to an
archived page but that doesn’t seem to work.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn3"><p><a href="https://www.itu.int/en/ITU-D/Statistics/Pages/stat/default.aspx">Statistics
pages on itu.int</a> project even higher numbers than 53.6% by the end
of 2020, but it’s possible numbers won’t behave according to historical
trends due to the effects of COVID.<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn4"><p><a href="https://www.wired.com/2011/02/how-many-people-are-in-tahrir-square-heres-how-to-tell/">How
Many People Are in Tahrir Square? Here’s How to Tell</a><a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Things You Can Do With Neovim and Vscode That You Can't Do With Neovim Alone</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/things-you-can-do-with-nvim-and-vscode/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/things-you-can-do-with-nvim-and-vscode/</guid><description>This is the third time I’ve tried in earnest to switch to VSCode from Vim (or Neovim in my case) for reasons not all of which are relevant to this post. But I love Vim style modal editing and I’ve grown accustomed to some features that aren’t present or not well emulated in VSCodeVim.
Enter VSCode Neovim. I was intrigued by their claim to integrate Neovim instead of trying to emulate Vim.</description><content:encoded><p>This is the third time I’ve tried in earnest to switch to VSCode from
Vim (or Neovim in my case) for reasons not all of which are relevant to
this post. But I love Vim style modal editing and I’ve grown accustomed
to some features that aren’t present or not well emulated in<a href="https://github.com/VSCodeVim/Vim">VSCodeVim</a>.</p><p>Enter<a href="https://github.com/asvetliakov/vscode-neovim">VSCode
Neovim</a>. I was intrigued by their claim to integrate Neovim instead
of trying to emulate Vim. After going through the code a bit I thought
this extension alone warranted a new attempt at switching to VSCode. So
far it’s going great.</p><h2 id="how-vscode-neovim-works">How VSCode Neovim Works</h2><p>Here’s the gist of how this extension works. Feel free to skip to the
good stuff below but this section is good background information for
understanding<em>why</em> it works the way it does.</p><ol type="1"><li><p><strong>Invokes an embedded Neovim instance.</strong></p><p>Code for this is in the<code>main_controller.ts</code> (<a href="https://github.com/asvetliakov/vscode-neovim/blob/master/src/main_controller.ts">linky</a>)
if you are curious about how exactly it’s implemented and the
commandline options that are passed in.</p><p>You’ll also notice that the code invokes<code>--cmd source ${neovimSupportScriptPath}</code> which runs<code>vim/vscode-neovim.vim</code> (<a href="https://github.com/asvetliakov/vscode-neovim/blob/master/vim/vscode-neovim.vim">linky</a>)
before running your<code>init.vim</code> file. This script is what sets
up the<code>g:vscode</code> flag and sources all the other<code>vscode-*.vim</code> scripts except<code>vscode-options.vim</code>. The latter runs<em>after</em> your<code>init.vim</code> in order to force some settings that would
otherwise break the extension or cause Neovim to be confused.</p></li></ol><p>So far this is pretty standard fare for how Neovim would be embedded
for a custom UI. But things get a bit interesting from the next
step.</p><ol start="2" type="1"><li><p><strong>Creates a new Neovim buffer and window corresponding to a
VSCode editor.</strong></p><p>The buffer thus created is a plain text buffer without any bells or
whistles. Contents of the buffer comes from VSCode<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>.
VSCodeNeovim synchronizes the content between the Neovim buffer and the
VSCode editor. Thus the relationship between the contents and the
corresponding file on disk is mediated through VSCode. This is a key
difference between other custom UIs and this one and one that opens many
possibilities.</p><p>VSCodeNeovim defers to VSCode for handling insert mode. VSCode
handles autocompletion and other assistive features. You’ll have to get
used to your insert mode customizations not working, or replicating that
with VSCode keyboard mapping customizations. When exiting insert mode
the extension asynchronously synchronizes the buffer contents – which at
this point would include the changes that were introduced – with Neovim.
The code for synchronizing the VSCode editor contents and the Neovim
buffer is in<code>buffer_manager.ts</code> (<a href="https://github.com/asvetliakov/vscode-neovim/blob/master/src/buffer_manager.ts">linky</a>)
which is also a good place to look if you want to know the details about
buffer options that are being set.</p></li></ol><p>Of course I’m eliding lots of detail here including integrations for
other areas of UI. But I think this captures the pertinent details. The
extension is a pretty impressive piece of work which is well worth a
gander. Now on to the good stuff.</p><h2 id="responsive-neovim-experience-over-a-laggy-ssh-connection">Responsive
Neovim Experience Over A laggy SSH Connection</h2><p>This gets to the reason why I’m trying to move to VSCode in the first
place. I work on a project consisting of thousands of C++ source files.
My home-office doesn’t have enough hardware to do regular builds, or in
fact any build at all. The beefy machines are in a remote location
accessible via SSH.</p><p>I’ve been using Neovim over SSH for a while, but the latency really
bothers me. And no, neither SCP nor SSHFS scratches this itch because I
won’t have access to language smarts like<code>clangd</code> which
require access to all the source files and some build tooling.</p><p><a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/remote/remote-overview">VSCode
Remote Development</a> was a nearly perfect answer with the exception
that VSCodeVim didn’t quite have all the functionality I needed.
VSCodeNeovim addresses that last piece of the puzzle.</p><p>VSCode + Remote SSH + VSCodeNeovim + Neovim gives me:</p><figure><img src="8e18f57c165b71ad9bc1db511f5a219309015a0d.svg"/></figure><ul><li>On the remote machine:<ul><li>Source files.</li><li>Build tooling.</li><li><code>clangd</code> process invoked via<code>vscode-remote</code>.</li></ul></li><li>On the local machine:<ul><li>VSCode.</li><li>VSCodeNeovim.<ul><li>Neovim instance embedded by VSCodeNeovim.<ul><li>Neovim plug-ins and normal mode keybindings.</li></ul></li></ul></li></ul></li></ul><p>Since the embedded Neovim instance is local the editors are super
responsive. Completions via<code>clangd</code> is still laggy as one
might expect. But that’s something I’m willing to live with.</p><h2 id="proportional-fonts-with-neovim">Proportional Fonts With
Neovim</h2><p>Okay, so why would anyone actually want this? Turns out<a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=proportional+fonts+for+coding">I’m
not the only one</a>. In my case I prefer monospace for regular code,
but I’d much much rather read comments and prose in proportional font.
Also, I now spend a lot of my time writing Markdown with LatexMath.
Staring at monospaced prose all day is not my cup of tea.</p><p>This is what it looks like when I’m editing this post in VSCode (in
Markdown).</p><figure><img src="images/proportional-font-markdown.png" alt="Screenshot of VSCode editing Markdown in proportional font"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Screenshot of VSCode editing Markdown in
proportional font</figcaption></figure><p>The best part is that I can use my familiar Vim/Neovim keybindings
and modal editing. I had to make a couple of customizations and I only
have this set up for Markdown. But it works fairly well. One gotcha is
that the cursor jumps horizontally when moving the cursor up or down
since the columns are no longer neatly aligned.</p><h3 id="monospace-code-with-proportional-comments">Monospace Code With
Proportional Comments?</h3><p>What I really want isn’t proportional fonts everywhere. Rather I only
want proportional fonts for prose. In code, this would take the form of
comments.</p><p>Unfortunately, VSCode doesn’t support changing the font for specific
syntactic tokens or scopes. That would’ve been ideal because it would
let me configure things so that comments are in proportional font while
the rest is in monospace. Also in the case of Markdown, I’d be able to
make everything proportional except for inline code and fenced code
blocks. Alas we are not quite there yet. Several feature requests
already exist<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>, but hasn’t seen much activity.</p><h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2><ol type="1"><li>VSCodeNeovim is a functional replacement for the avid Neovim or
perhaps Vim user who wants it both ways. Lots of caveats exist including
the fact that Neovim mode only really works inside editor windows.</li><li>VSCodeNeovim + “Remote SSH” is an awesome combination for editing
remote files using Neovim with the latency of a local Neovim
instance.</li><li>You can use proportional fonts with VSCodeNeovim for super double
awesomeness.</li></ol><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Not quite the whole story because it’s possible a buffer
be created inside the Neovim instance and have it be mirrored in a
VSCode editor. But that’s probably not what you’ll be using on a regular
basis.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p>A quick search in the VSCode repository<a href="https://github.com/microsoft/vscode/search?q=tokenColorCustomizations+font+name">with
this query</a> yields several issues that request for pretty much the
same thing: Allow setting<code>fontName</code> in<code>tokenColorCustomizations</code>. There’s also<a href="https://github.com/deepanrajkumar/Italic-and-Ligature">this
curious experiment</a> which patches in a different font for italics so
that you can use the existing<code>fontStyle: "italic"</code> option in<code>tokenColorCustomizations</code> to switch fonts.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Why 'Strong Opinions Weakly Held'</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/why-strong-opinions-weakly-held/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 15:17:16 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/why-strong-opinions-weakly-held/</guid><description>Origins of the phrase The title of this blog is Strong Opinions, Weakly Held. The same concept shows up elsewhere are Strong Opinions Loosely Held. An eponymous essay by Paul Saffo in (2020) introduced the world to this concept.
In his essay – which isn’t very long if you would like to read the whole thing yourself – he lays out the concept as follows:
I have found that the fastest way to an effective forecast is often through a sequence of lousy forecasts.</description><content:encoded><h2 id="origins-of-the-phrase">Origins of the phrase</h2><p>The title of this blog is<strong>Strong Opinions, Weakly
Held</strong>. The same concept shows up elsewhere are<em>Strong
Opinions Loosely Held</em>. An eponymous essay by Paul Saffo in<span class="citation" data-cites="Saffo">(<a href="#ref-Saffo" role="doc-biblioref">2020</a>)</span> introduced the world to this
concept.</p><p>In his essay – which isn’t very long if you would like to<a href="https://www.saffo.com/02008/07/26/strong-opinions-weakly-held/">read
the whole thing yourself</a> – he lays out the concept as follows:</p><blockquote><p>I have found that the fastest way to an effective forecast is often
through a sequence of lousy forecasts. Instead of withholding judgment
until an exhaustive search for data is complete, I will force myself to
make a tentative forecast based on the information available, and then
systematically tear it apart, using the insights gained to guide my
search for further indicators and information.</p></blockquote><h2 id="criticism">Criticism</h2><p>Cedric Chin’s critique<span class="citation" data-cites="Cedric">(<a href="#ref-Cedric" role="doc-biblioref">2020</a>)</span> comes down to
two points that the author summarizes as follows:</p><figure><p>In my experience, ‘strong opinions, weakly held’ is difficult to put
into practice. Most people who try will either:</p><ol type="1"><li>Use it as downside-protection to justify their strongly-held bad
opinions, or</li><li>Struggle to shift from one strong opinion to another.</li></ol><p>The reason it is difficult is because it works against the grain of
the human mind.</p><figcaption><p>So don’t bother. The next time you find yourself making a judgment,
don’t invoke ‘strong opinions, weakly held’. Instead, ask: “how much are
you willing to bet on that?” Doing so will jolt people into the types of
thinking you want to encourage.</p></figcaption></figure><p>Michael Natkin on<span class="citation" data-cites="Michael">(<a href="#ref-Michael" role="doc-biblioref">2020</a>)</span> points out the
fallacy of assuming that strong opinions will be reliably
challenged:</p><figure><p>The idea of strong opinions, loosely held is that you can make
bombastic statements, and everyone should implicitly assume that you’ll
happily change your mind in a heartbeat if new data suggests you are
wrong. It is supposed to lead to a collegial, competitive environment in
which ideas get a vigorous defense, the best of them survive, and no-one
gets their feelings hurt in the process.</p><p>[…]</p><figcaption><p>What really happens? The loudest, most bombastic engineer states
their case with certainty, and that shuts down discussion. Other people
either assume the loudmouth knows best, or don’t want to stick out their
neck and risk criticism and shame. This is especially true if the
loudmouth is senior, or there is any other power differential.</p></figcaption></figure><h2 id="reconciliation">Reconciliation</h2><p>Both cases above illustrate the damage caused by the disconnect
between the holder of the opinion and others about the degree of
confidence with which the opinion is held. A strongly held – and thusly
communicated – opinion has a higher chance of being misinterpreted as
conviction.</p><p>Saffo’s original claim still holds that having a potentially
inaccurate position is<em>better than having none at all</em>. Such a
position elicits arguments and opens up avenues for investigation that
wouldn’t otherwise materialize in the absence of any other catalyst.</p><p>Cedric Chin’s essay points out a simple fix, where the holder of the
opinion also states the degree of confidence. This is meant to dress up
the opinion more as a target than a decree, thus inviting debate instead
of suppressing. I believe this to be good advice.</p><p>Back in my college days, I remember a particularly engaging professor
asking a question like “is claim<em>A</em> true or is claim<em>B</em>
true?” After observing a lackluster show of hands he remarked that of
the three groups of students – those that chose<em>A</em>, those that
chose<em>B</em>, and those that chose neither – the group that will
leave the lecture having learned the most is the group that gets the
answer wrong. He advised all of us to “get some skin in the game,” even
if you don’t know the answer.</p><p>There is some truth to this. Of course a corporate meeting where we
need to elicit debate from a group of people with varying levels of
confidence is a very different venue than a group of students answering
a question. But a similar principle still applies. The goals might be
different, but it’s still better to cajole everyone to get some skin in
the game instead of not passive silence.</p><h2 id="what-strong-opinions-weakly-held-means-to-me">What ‘Strong
Opinions Weakly Held’ Means To Me</h2><ol type="1"><li><p>Having an opinion is better than not having one. Accmulation of
raw data is great, but it’s even better when you intentionally accrete
them into something meaningful. Any interpretation of information beyond
establishment of fact is probably going to be in the realm of
opinion.</p></li><li><p>An opinion expressed is better than one that is not as long as
it’s open for criticism. You wouldn’t find out if you were wrong if you
didn’t tell anyone.</p></li><li><p>That it is weakly held is as important to communicate as the
opinion itself. Doing so invites criticism and discussion instead of
suppressing them.</p></li></ol><h2 class="unnumbered" id="references">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0" role="list"><div id="ref-Michael" class="csl-entry" role="listitem"><span>“Strong Opinions Loosely Held Might Be the Worst Idea in Tech -
the Glowforge Blog.”</span> 2020. September 4, 2020.<a href="https://blog.glowforge.com/strong-opinions-loosely-held-might-be-the-worst-idea-in-tech/">https://blog.glowforge.com/strong-opinions-loosely-held-might-be-the-worst-idea-in-tech/</a>.</div><div id="ref-Saffo" class="csl-entry" role="listitem"><span>“Strong Opinions Weakly Held : Paul Saffo.”</span> 2020. September
4, 2020.<a href="https://www.saffo.com/02008/07/26/strong-opinions-weakly-held/">https://www.saffo.com/02008/07/26/strong-opinions-weakly-held/</a>.</div><div id="ref-Cedric" class="csl-entry" role="listitem"><span>“<span>‘Strong Opinions, Weakly Held’</span> Doesn’t Work That
Well.”</span> 2020. September 4, 2020.<a href="https://commoncog.com/blog/strong-opinions-weakly-held-is-bad/">https://commoncog.com/blog/strong-opinions-weakly-held-is-bad/</a>.</div></div></content:encoded></item><item><title>Names for Name Conventions</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/symbol-name-types/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 12:32:45 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/symbol-name-types/</guid><description>Names I’ve seen used to refer to naming conventions:
snake_case, hacker_case, unix_hacker_style : Everything is lower case, though exceptions exist. E.g. HTTP_foo_bar. SCREAMING_SNAKE_CASE : Usually reserved for macros and constants. camelCase : The first letter is lowercase. PascalCase : The first letter is uppercase. kabob-case : Like snake_case, but uses dashes instead of underscores. Common for command-line options1, CSS styles, commands (e.g. git-receive-pack). While looking idly looking for details on this, I stumbled on this Medium post which is relevant.</description><content:encoded><p>Names I’ve seen used to refer to naming conventions:</p><ul><li><code>snake_case</code>,<code>hacker_case</code>,<code>unix_hacker_style</code> : Everything is lower case, though
exceptions exist. E.g.<code>HTTP_foo_bar</code>.</li><li><code>SCREAMING_SNAKE_CASE</code> : Usually reserved for macros and
constants.</li><li><code>camelCase</code> : The first letter is lowercase.</li><li><code>PascalCase</code> : The first letter is uppercase.</li><li><code>kabob-case</code> : Like<code>snake_case</code>, but uses
dashes instead of underscores. Common for command-line options<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>, CSS styles, commands (e.g.<code>git-receive-pack</code>).</li></ul><p>While looking idly looking for details on this, I stumbled on<a href="https://medium.com/better-programming/string-case-styles-camel-pascal-snake-and-kebab-case-981407998841">this
Medium post</a> which is relevant.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Opinions vary on whether the correct convention for
command line options is<code>snake_case</code> or<code>kabob-case</code>. Long form options are often written as<code>--long-option</code>, but can also be<code>--long_option</code>
(where the delimiter within the option is<code>_</code>).<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>How This Blog Works</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/how-this-blog-works/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:57:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/how-this-blog-works/</guid><description>How I put this site together and why.</description><content:encoded><h1 id="requirements">Requirements</h1><ul><li>Math. Preferably Latex.</li><li>Citations. I like to cite stuff.</li><li>Figures and pictures and references to thereof.</li><li>Be able to export to Github Flavored Markdown.</li></ul><h1 id="the-stack">The Stack</h1><ul><li><p>All documents are in Markdown. Specifically<a href="https://pandoc.org/MANUAL.html">Pandoc Markdown</a>. Obviously,
the source is processed via<code>pandoc</code>.</p></li><li><p>The site itself is compiled using<a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a>.</p><p>The current version (as of this writing) doesn’t support any
configuration when using Pandoc for markup processing. By default Hugo
only passes the<code>--mathjax</code> option to the<code>pandoc</code>
invocation. So I had to make some local modifications so that I can
specify filters and some other options to support citations and
references.</p><p>Pull request is<a href="https://github.com/gohugoio/hugo/pull/7529">here</a>.</p></li><li><p>Hugo output – which is a static HTML site – gets pushed out to a
separate private GitHub repository.</p></li><li><p><a href="https://www.netlify.com/">Netlify</a> monitors this
separate GitHub repository and updates this blog.</p><p>As a bonus, the generated static content is pushed out to my GitHub
Pages site. So there’s an easier to remember URL than<a href="https://අ.com">https://අ.com</a>.</p></li><li><p>Secondary sites are fed via Pandoc which converts from Pandoc
Markdown to Github Flavored Markdown.</p><p>Why secondary sites? For various reasons, the primary site for some
of the articles need to be their own GitHub repository. E.g.
https://github.com/asankah/identity-domains .</p><p>For all those sites, the primary source is the blog. That way I can
use Pandoc, use citations, use math etc. and things will “just work”
when publishing to another site that expects GitHub flavored
Markdown.</p></li></ul></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Comcast Technician Problem</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/comcast-technican-problem/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 13:21:51 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/comcast-technican-problem/</guid><description>Given a set of tasks, incentives are often aligned towards dropping a
task rather than allowing for perpetual accretion of delays.</description><content:encoded><h2 id="the-story">The Story</h2><p>As is a rite of passage in these parts, I waited for the Comcast<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> technician to arrive during their
scheduled appointment window. In preparation I had scheduled a day of
working from home.</p><p>As the appointment window unceremoniously came to a close vacillated
over when it would be a reasonable time to call Comcast again to see
what’s going on. That’s when I noticed the technician’s truck pull up
beside our house. They rolled down the window and surveyed the scene for
a brief moment, looked at something inside their truck, rolled up the
window and promptly drove off.</p><p>“That’s it,” I thought. That was the right time to call Comcast.
That’s what I did. After a long wait<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a> the friendly service
person on the other end of the line told me that the according to the
technician nobody answered the door. It took some convincing on my part
to establish that:</p><ol type="a"><li>I was there the whole time. Nobody rang the doorbell.</li><li>The doorbell works.</li><li>The technician — assuming that the person who drove by was the
scheduled technician — did drive by, but they didn’t get out of the
vehicle to ring any doorbell.</li><li>My phone didn’t ring, nor does it indicate any missed calls.</li><li>My phone works and has a signal.</li></ol><p>They were kind enough to ask the technician to return, but noted that
the appointment window would now be unpredictable due to prior
appointments. Sure.</p><p>Much later that evening, the same technician who drove by earlier
showed up. After they were done, I thanked them for showing up and
mentioned what happened to the original appointment slot. I didn’t
mention anything about seeing the same technician before. After all I
was just happy that I was done with this and didn’t want to cause any
trouble.</p><p>He said that technicians sometimes skip slots when they are running
behind schedule.</p><h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2><p>Looking at what happened from the perspective of the technician, the
logic behind all this becomes a little clearer.</p><p>You see, had the technician had tried to honor the original
appointment — one which they were already late for — they would’ve been
even more late for the next one. This would continue down the line until
by the end of the day pretty much all of his appointments that afternoon
would’ve registered as<em>late</em>.</p><p>Had they skipped one – my appointment as the case turned out – then
they’d potentially be on time for the rest of their appointments. The
one they skipped could later be justified as one where the customer was
not at home or any other reasonable excuses. Even if they were truthful
and were penalized for missing an appointment, it’s likely that they’d
still be better off than being late for so many more appointments.
Either way, the outcome is both better for the technician, and more
importantly, for their supervisor.</p><p>In the books, the two situations look like this:</p><table><colgroup><col style="width: 24%"/><col style="width: 29%"/><col style="width: 22%"/><col style="width: 23%"/></colgroup><thead><tr class="header"><th>Technician’s Choice</th><th>Successful appointments</th><th>Late appointments</th><th style="text-align: left;">“No-show”s<a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr class="odd"><td>Honor all slots</td><td><span class="math inline">g</span></td><td><span class="math inline">l</span></td><td style="text-align: left;"><span class="math inline">n</span></td></tr><tr class="even"><td>Skip when late</td><td><span class="math inline">g + l - s</span></td><td><span class="math inline">0</span></td><td style="text-align: left;"><span class="math inline">n +
s</span></td></tr></tbody></table><p>The outcomes depending on the technician’s decision on what to do
with late appointments. {#table:outcomes}</p><p><span class="math inline">g</span> are the<em>good</em> slots where
the technician is able to show up during the appointment window.<span class="math inline">l</span> are those where the technician was not
available during the appointment window. In either case some number of
households are not going to be home or not ready for service. Those are<span class="math inline">n</span>.</p><p>When the technician decides to skip late appointments some number –<span class="math inline">s</span> in the table above – will turn into
additional no-shows. However, skipping these will mean that the
technician can make it to<span class="math inline">l-s</span>
appointments on time.</p><p>Assuming<span class="math inline">l-s > 0</span>, then the
outcome of the<em>skip when late</em> strategy is strictly better for
the technician’s supervisor. I can’t imagine there being any incentive
for the supervisor to penalize this strategy. So the technician also
gets off scott free.</p><h2 id="why-this-is-relevant">Why This Is Relevant</h2><p>It’s easy to harp on Comcast<a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"><sup>4</sup></a> and some random lowly
technician. But this incentive pattern is everywhere. Even at Google and
s.</p><p>Every time you measure someone’s success on<em>how well</em> they
handled a number of issues or cases without taking into account<em>the
cost they incurred</em> to get there, you are creating a Comcast
Technician problem for your subordinates.</p><h2 id="but-is-it-bad">But Is It Bad?</h2><p>Dropping tasks instead of unbounded accretion of delay is sometimes a
better strategy.</p><p>One might even argue that this is the cost of doing business and it
would actually makes sense. One customer’s (or user’s or client’s or
patient’s) convenience doesn’t outweigh the convenience of many
others.</p><p>There could be additional complicating factors involved:</p><ul><li><p>What’s the cost of skipping or rescheduling a case? Is the cost
bourne by you? How much of the cost is bourne by the customer?</p></li><li><p>How do you choose which case to skip? It might be that the case
to skip isn’t the one that’s late, but one later down the schedule
that’s much cheaper to reschedule or less damaging to cancel.</p></li></ul><p>In either case, be forgiving when you inevitably find yourself as the
one who got the short end of the stick.</p><p>It just might be that all parties involved are rational actors, and
there’s really not a great alternative. Sometimes it’s just life.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2014/8/19/6004131/comcast-the-worst-company-in-america"><em>The
Verge</em>.<em>The worst company in America.</em></a> (Accessed July
13, 2020)<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p><a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Long%20Wait"><em>Urban
Dictionary</em>.<em>Long Wait</em></a> (Accessed July 13, 2020)<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn3"><p>“No-shows” are just going to be rescheduled. It’s not
the end of the world.<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn4"><p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2014/8/19/6004131/comcast-the-worst-company-in-america"><em>The
Verge</em>.<em>The worst company in America.</em></a> (Accessed July
13, 2020)<a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Vim: Use Drop Not Edit, SBuffer Not Buffer</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/use-drop-not-edit/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 12:02:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/use-drop-not-edit/</guid><description>I’m going to assume you are a Vim user.
Say you have a several windows open in Vim and you want to edit another file. Using :edit works if you want to open the file in the current window unconditionally.
But that’s often not what you want. If you have the same file open in another window, then the most efficient and least disruptive thing to do is to switch to that window.</description><content:encoded><p>I’m going to assume you are a Vim user.</p><p>Say you have a several windows open in Vim and you want to edit
another file. Using<code>:edit</code> works if you want to open the
file in the current window unconditionally.</p><p><em>But that’s often not what you want.</em> If you have the same
file open in another window, then the most efficient and least
disruptive thing to do is to switch to that window.</p><h2 id="drop">drop</h2><p>That’s where<code>:drop</code> comes in. In case you aren’t familiar
with the<code>drop</code> command, have a look at the help page in your
favorite editor (<code>:help drop</code>) or<a href="http://vimdoc.sourceforge.net/htmldoc/windows.html#:drop">here on
the web</a>. But the gist of it is that for most people<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a><code>:drop {file}</code> will:</p><ul><li>Switch to the window in which<code>{file}</code> is already
open.</li><li>Switch the buffer in the current window to<code>{file}</code>
otherwise.</li></ul><p>The<code>:drop</code> command is intended to be used as the “open
buffer” command for automated tooling like source browsers. For example,
you can configure<code>coc-nvim</code><a href="https://github.com/neoclide/coc.nvim">GitHub</a> to use<code>:drop</code> as the command used for opening a source file by
setting<code>coc.preferences.jumpCommand</code> to<code>drop</code>.
See<code>:help coc-configuration</code> for details on how to set this,
but basically it’s as simple as opening up the configuration using<code>:CocConfig</code> and then adding a<code>"coc.preferences.jumpCommand": "drop",</code> mapping to the
configuration JSON file.</p><h2 id="switchbuf-or-swb">switchbuf or swb</h2><p>Or perhaps configuring each plugin is too much work. Enter<code>switchbuf</code>. This is a global setting in Vim that controls
how Vim switches between buffers.</p><p>Setting<code>set switchbuf=useopen</code> has the same effect when
invoking<code>buffer</code>. Note that using<code>sbuffer</code>,<code>sbnext</code>, or<code>sbrewind</code> automatically behaves as
if this is the case. I.e. they will use an existing window if one
already has the buffer open.</p><p>Setting<code>set switchbuf=usetab</code> is similar to the effect of<code>useopen</code> except that it will look through windows in other
tabs.</p><p>See<code>:help switchbuf</code> or<a href="http://vimdoc.sourceforge.net/htmldoc/options.html#'switchbuf'">here
on the web</a> for full details.</p><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Assuming you have<code>set hidden</code> that is. See<code>:help drop</code> for more details on what happens when the
current buffer cannot be unloaded.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item><item><title>Notes from Crash Course's Videos on Fact Checking Information You See On The Internet</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/notes-on-fact-checking/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 18:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/notes-on-fact-checking/</guid><description>Hank Green’s Crash Course YouTube channel has an excellent series
about navigating digital information. It’s an excellent guide to how
internet users could intelligently consume information they see on the
internet. These are my (incomplete) notes from the series.</description><content:encoded><h1 id="fact-checking">Fact Checking</h1><p>Notes from<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCX6b17PVsYBQ0ip5gyeme-Q">Crash
Course</a>’s excellent series about fact checking information you see on
the internet. The series starts<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pLlv2o6UfTU">here</a>.</p><h2 id="three-questions">Three Questions</h2><ol type="1"><li>How is behind this information?</li><li>What is the evidence for their claims?</li><li>What do other sources say about the organization and its
claims?</li></ol><p>“A question wrongly put.”</p><h2 id="lateral-reading">Lateral Reading</h2><p>All information is produced by someone, and is produced for a
purpose. The lines between motives are unclear. There are always
multiple motives, and they don’t always conflict.</p><p>“Who made this and why?”</p><p>We read websites like we read books. We read vertically. You are only
seeing what the creator wanted you to see. It is often impossible to
tell reliable information from unreliable information.</p><p>A better alternative is to leave the site and search for
corroborating information. Look for conflicts of interest that are left
undisclosed which is a red flag.</p><p>Newspapers can be a good start. These are now digital media
companies. Sometimes they have their own point-of-view. Sometimes these
are stated explicitly and/or are obvious. But that’s not necessarily
always the case.</p><p>There is no magic arbiter of truth. All of these is created by humans
and humans make mistakes.</p><p>“The media” doesn’t exist. It is a large and diverse industry. It is,
however, possible to take these diverse points of view into account.</p><p>You should use Wikipedia. Not every article is perfect, but you
should see verifiable citations.</p><p>Because no source is perfectly objective, one might conclude that no
source is trustworthy. This is not true.</p><h2 id="deciding-whom-to-trust">Deciding Whom To Trust</h2><p>It is easy to be mislead. None of us have the time to be an expert in
everything.</p><p>We have to trust information from outside of ourselves we have to
find a way to accredit and trust experts, even though they will be wrong
some of the time.</p><p>“Listen to me”bloviate””</p><p>Before we place trust in a source, we should verify the authority,
and the validity of their evidence.</p><h3 id="investigating-a-sources-authority">Investigating A Source’s
Authority</h3><ul><li>The author or authors’ professional background.</li><li>The process they used to produce that information.</li><li>The systems that are in place to catch mistakes and correct
them.</li></ul><p>Everyone has a perspective influenced by their lived experience. This
doesn’t necessarily mean that they are unfairly biased. We should take
their perspective into consideration when examining their arguments.
They may be presenting their information in a way that’s persuasive.</p><p>“Opinion”, “Analysis” etc. mean that the work intends to be
persuasive rather than informative.</p><p>STOP, THINK, and LOOK AROUND.</p><p>Each bit of information we have about a source gives us a lens to
filter out their perspective.</p><h2 id="using-wikipedia">Using Wikipedia</h2><p>When used correctly Wikipedia can be a great place to start when
verifying the legitimacy of a source. It’s breadth can exceed any
newspaper. It gives you the general lay of the land when exploring or
researching a topic.</p><p>Wikipedia has become the internet’s largest general reference
work.</p><p>Their content policies:</p><ol type="1"><li>A neutral point of view.</li><li>No original research.</li><li>Verifiable.</li></ol><p>Modern Wikipedia has rigorous and robust mechanisms to keep things in
check.</p><p>Wikipedia is not a one-stop shop for in-depth research. Don’t cite
Wikipedia. That’s not a good look. And encyclopedia is not a source.</p><p>Citations help bring up more information from reputable sources.</p><p>Treat Wikipedia as a launch pad.</p><p>Wikipedia is another tool in your information evaluation tool
kit.</p><p>You go there for general overview a topic or a stepping stone to more
references, or to use as one lateral reading source among several.</p><p>And as long as your know how and when to use it appropriately,
Wikipedia can be a great friend.</p><h2 id="evaluating-evidence">Evaluating Evidence</h2><p>As you get older “because I said so” doesn’t cut it anymore. You need
to provide evidence and that evidence should be convincing.</p><p>“What is the evidence?”</p><p>Often when the evidence does not support the claim, it is misleading
or disinformation. Lack of evidence should be suspicious
immediately.</p><p>The mere existence of evidence doesn’t support the claim either.</p><p>Not all evidence is cerated equal.</p><p>The evidence a source provides should come from another reputable
source.</p><p>“Thousands of people never conspire to do anything secretly.”</p><p>Spurious correlation: The implied causal relationship between events
that are coincidentally linked.</p><p>The quality of our evidence like the quality of our information,
affects the quality of our decisions.</p><h2 id="evaluating-photos-videos">Evaluating Photos &amp; Videos</h2><p>Photographs feel real and authentic. Even when images aren’t altered,
they are selectively framed, or have their context falsified (e.g. with
a false explanation, or date).</p><p>We are used to thinking that “seeing is believing”.</p><p>Thanks to their power, images are a very common form of online
evidence. But just like data or text image-based evidence can be<strong>relevant</strong> and<strong>reliable</strong>, or<strong>irrelevant</strong> and<strong>unreliable</strong>.</p><p>When you encounter a suspicious image online it is crucial to
investigate who is behind it and whiter they are a reliable source. We
also must verify the surrounding context and whether it supports any
claims being made.</p><p>Use reverse image search on Google to track down sources. Turn to
fact checking sites like Snopes and Politifact.</p><p>Videos can also be dramatically altered. It is important to know
where a video came from, who created it, and whether it’s been altered
before you believe what you see.</p><h2 id="data-and-infographics">Data and infographics</h2></content:encoded></item><item><title>Easier CLI for ad-hoc Ansible tasks and playbooks</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/ansible-cli-sugar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/ansible-cli-sugar/</guid><description>Encode the host and group names into the name of a wrapper script for
quick ad-hoc invocation of Ansible tasks and playbooks.</description><content:encoded><p>This article is about using<a href="https://ansible.com">Ansible</a>
on the command-line.</p><h2 id="problem">Problem:</h2><p>You …</p><ul><li><p>… want a convenient way to do ad-hoc tasks on a bunch of
machines.</p></li><li><p>… already have a few playbooks and machine groups defined in your
inventory.</p></li><li><p>… don’t want to invest too much into Ansible because you have
other things to do and Ansible is just a tool to deal with one aspect of
what you want to do.</p></li><li><p>… live on the command-line.</p></li><li><p>… think<code>ansible-playbook</code> and<code>ansible</code>
commands have too many knobs and too few knobs at the same
time.</p></li></ul><h2 id="a-possible-solution">A Possible Solution</h2><p>Taking a page from old school Posix tools, let’s make a script that
encodes Ansible group names into the filename.</p><p>Then you can go from this:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb1"><pre class="sourceCode sh"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb1-1"><a href="#cb1-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> ansible atlanta<span class="at">-m</span> copy<span class="at">-a</span><span class="st">"src=https://xn--izc.com/etc/hosts dest=/tmp/hosts"</span></span><span id="cb1-2"><a href="#cb1-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> ansible webservers<span class="at">-m</span> service<span class="at">-a</span><span class="st">"name=httpd state=started"</span></span></code></pre></div><p>To this:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb2"><pre class="sourceCode sh"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb2-1"><a href="#cb2-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> atlanta copy<span class="st">"src=https://xn--izc.com/etc/hosts dest=/tmp/hosts"</span></span><span id="cb2-2"><a href="#cb2-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> webservers service<span class="st">"name=https state=started"</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Or from this:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb3"><pre class="sourceCode sh"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb3-1"><a href="#cb3-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> ansible-playbook<span class="at">-l</span> atlanta go-to-the-moon</span><span id="cb3-2"><a href="#cb3-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> ansible-playbook<span class="at">-l</span> webservers do-the-other-things</span></code></pre></div><p>To this:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb4"><pre class="sourceCode sh"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb4-1"><a href="#cb4-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> atlanta go-to-the-moon</span><span id="cb4-2"><a href="#cb4-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> webservers do-the-other-things</span></code></pre></div><h2 id="setting-up">Setting Up</h2><p>These are just examples. Please don’t spend time bikeshedding names
because you can use whichever names you like.</p><ol type="1"><li><p>Download the contents of<code>ansible-by-proxy</code> from<a href="https://github.com/asankah/ansible-cli-sugar/blob/master/ansible-by-proxy">here</a>.
It’s a starter script that includes a bunch of sensible settings
expressed via environment variables. Remove or change these to match
your needs.</p><p>Note that the script expects to find a sub-directory called<code>ansible</code> in the same directory as the script which contains
the playbooks and the inventory file.</p></li><li><p>Store this file somewhere on the system<code>PATH</code>.</p><p>Don’t forget to mark the file as executable if it isn’t already.</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb5"><pre class="sourceCode sh"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb5-1"><a href="#cb5-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> chmod +x ansible-by-proxy</span></code></pre></div></li><li><p>Create symlinks to the file that have the same name as hostnames
or groups as described in the includes:</p><div class="sourceCode" id="cb6"><pre class="sourceCode sh"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb6-1"><a href="#cb6-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> ln<span class="at">-s</span> ansible-by-proxy atlanta</span><span id="cb6-2"><a href="#cb6-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"/><span class="ex">$</span> ln<span class="at">-s</span> ansible-by-proxy webservers</span></code></pre></div><p>and so on.</p></li></ol><p>That’s it. Now you can invoke playbooks and tasks just by using the
name of host or group.</p></content:encoded></item><item><title>Identity Domains</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/identity-domains/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/identity-domains/</guid><description>An Identity Domain is a scope within which we assume that the user’s
identity can roam freely.</description><content:encoded><blockquote><p>An<strong>Identity domain</strong> is a scope within which we
consider it a given that the user has a shared or trivially joinable
identity.</p></blockquote><p>This is a privacy boundary, not a security boundary. Hence it assumes
that where possible all sites share information.</p><figure><img src="images/identity-domains.png" alt="Diagram of example identity domains described below"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">Diagram of example identity domains
described below</figcaption></figure><p>Above is a diagram showing relationships between clusters of
documents and identity domains.</p><ul><li><code>foo.example</code> and<code>baz.example</code> belong to the
same first party set.</li><li><code>a.example</code> has no first-party relationship with any
other domain.</li></ul><p>The<em>Identity domain</em> has the following properties:</p><ul><li><p>All<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/browsers.html#active-document">active
documents</a> in<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/browsers.html#list-of-the-descendant-browsing-contexts">descendent
browsing contexts</a> belong to the same<strong>identity
domain</strong> as the active document in the<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/browsers.html#top-level-browsing-context">top-level
browsing context</a>.</p><p>See each cluster of browsing contexts in the diagram above.</p></li><li><p>All active documents in top-level browsing contexts that share
the same<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/webappapis.html#site">site</a>
also share the same<strong>identity domain</strong>.</p><p>In the diagram above,<code>foo.example</code> in cluster 1 and<code>baz.example</code> in cluster 2 belong to the same first-party
set, hence they are considered to belong to the same identity domain.
However<code>a.example</code> in cluster 3 does not belong to the same
identity domain because there’s no first party relation between<code>a.example</code> and any other top level domain in the
diagram.</p></li><li><p>All<strong>private client state</strong> including but not
limited to open sockets, socket pools, cookies, storage, permissions /
content settings, transient caches of credentials, cached resources,
service workers, and shared workers accessible to any document in an
identity domain also belong to the<strong><em>identity
domain</em></strong>.</p></li><li><p><strong>Identity domains</strong> don’t span browser
profiles.</p><p>See clusters 1 and 4 in the diagram above. Both share top-level
origins, but don’t share identity domains because they are in two
different browser profiles.</p></li><li><p><strong>Identity domains</strong> don’t span browsers.</p><p>Derived from above.</p></li><li><p><strong>Identity domains</strong> don’t survive browsing data
erasures.</p><p>Erasing an identity domain – and thus an identity – requires
destroying all private client state mentioned previously. Hence erasing
an identity domain involves discarding all<code>Document</code> objects
and workers in that identity domain.</p></li></ul><p>Note that in the existing web privacy model third-parties can
trivially associate identities across top-level contexts. Thus the
entire internet essentially amalgamates into a single identity
domain.</p><p>The boundaries discussed herein require moving to a different model
of identity on the web. The privacy threat model guiding this model is
discussed in PING’s<a href="https://w3cping.github.io/privacy-threat-model/">Target Privacy
Threat Model</a> document which is a work in progress as of this
writing.</p><h2 id="additional-notes-and-observations">Additional Notes and
Observations</h2><ul><li><p>The identity domain is a privacy boundary. The boundary is
something that’s asserted by the user-agent and doesn’t depend on the
cooperation of sites. I.e. assumes that sites involved are worst case
actors.</p><ul><li>Not to be confused with security boundaries like those imposed via<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/CSP">Content
Security Policy</a>.</li></ul></li><li><p>The definition assumes that sites can share information
out-of-band. The identity domain boundary does not require sites to
cooperate.</p></li><li><p>The same site can appear in multiple identity domains. For
example, re-identification is equivalent to a single site joining an
identity across disjoint domains.</p><p>One can also imagine a user-agent that maintains multiple identity
boundaries for the same top-level site for the purpose of allowing
multiple sets of cookies to be used from the same device.</p></li><li><p>Two identity domains can be joined by sharing a unique identifier
between the two domains.</p><ul><li><p>WRT federated identity (as detailed in<a href="https://github.com/samuelgoto/WebID">WebID</a>) multiple relying
parties join identity domains by virtue of shared unique identifiers
like email address. Similarly identity providers can also generate and
use unique identifiers linking domains.</p><p>We likely need another term for describing externally joined identity
domains. In such cases the UA doesn’t necessarily know or can prevent
joining of identity domains.</p></li></ul></li><li><p>Concepts like “logging out” can be defined in terms of destroying
an identity domain on the User Agent.</p></li></ul></content:encoded></item><item><title>Ephemeral Fingerprinting On The Web</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/ephemeral-fingerprinting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/ephemeral-fingerprinting/</guid><description>&lt;p>Any ephemeral low-entropy web observable property whose changes are
concurrently observable by multiple sites can lead to cross site
identity joining.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This method of identity joining does not require coordination between
multiple first parties. A single third party embedded within multiple
first parties can also use this method.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><p>TL;DR:</p><ul><li><p>Any web observable property whose changes are concurrently
observable by multiple top-level sites can lead to cross site identity
joining.</p></li><li><p>This method of identity joining does not require additional
coordination between multiple first parties. A single third party
embedded within multiple first parties can also use this
method.</p></li></ul><h2 id="background">Background</h2><figure><img src="./isolation-boundaries.png" alt="diagram of site isolation boundaries with overlap"/><figcaption aria-hidden="true">diagram of site isolation boundaries with
overlap</figcaption></figure><p><strong>Figure 1</strong>: Two sites observe a sequence of device
orientation changes at times 𝒕₀, 𝒕₁,𝒕₂ .</p><p>All sites on the same UA instance share a clock and therefore can
agree on the timestamps with a small margin of error. The triplet 𝒕₀,
𝒕₁,𝒕₂ has a high probability of uniquely identifying the user. The two
sites can thus use these observations to conclude that the observations
originate from the same user.</p><p>As illustrated above, one or more low entropy signals observed
concurrently can be used to identify a user with a high degree of
confidence. Let’s call these<strong>ephemeral fingerprints</strong>.
This document discusses two types:</p><ol type="1"><li><p><em>The sequence of timestamps corresponding to observed changes
of a volatile surface can be used for identification</em>. Let’s call
these<strong>correlated events</strong>.</p></li><li><p><em>A stream of observations of a volatile surface can be
identifying</em>. Let’s call these<strong>unique event
streams</strong>.</p></li></ol><p>Signals considered for ephemeral fingerprinting don’t need to be
highly identifying by themselves. The<a href="https://github.com/bslassey/privacy-budget">privacy budget
proposal</a> does not adequately account for fingerprinting based on
concurrent observations of low entropy signals.</p><p>Device orientation, from our earlier example, can take one of two
values (portrait or landscape) and is unstable. Thus a single sample of
device orientation carries almost no information. I.e. A recorded
observation of device orientation doesn’t help at all with identifying
the user at a later time. However the timestamps corresponding to
orientation changes could have identifying levels of entropy.</p><p>These are not new. For example, this is discussed by Van Goethem et.
al.<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a></p><p>who calls these “Cross-Session Events” (§ 5 of linked paper).
Potential ephemeral fingerprinting surfaces also get flagged during
standardization discussions (<a href="https://github.com/w3c/mediacapture-main/issues/403">Example:
Polling enumerateDevices</a>,<a href="https://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-privacy/2013JanMar/0007.html">Example:
Ambient light events</a>).</p><h3 id="modelling-correlated-events">Modelling Correlated Events</h3><p>A correlatable event can be thought of as the tuple<code>&lt;surface-sample, timestamp></code>. The addition of the
timestamp strictly increases the amount of information carried by the
surface sample.</p><h3 id="modelling-event-streams">Modelling Event Streams</h3><p>An event stream is simply a list of observed samples<code>sample₀, sample₁, ...</code>.</p><p>Each additional observation strictly increases the amount of
information.</p><h3 id="other-examples">Other Examples:</h3><ul><li><code>Accelerometer</code> properties.</li><li><code>Sensor</code>,<code>onreading</code> event.</li><li><code>BatteryManager.onlevelchange</code> : Deprecated but still
shipping.</li><li><code>Bluetooth.onadvertisementreceived</code></li><li><code>BroadcastChannel</code>, all events.</li><li><code>MediaDevices.devicechange</code> event.</li><li><code>GlobalEventHandlers.onfocus</code> and<code>onblur</code>
events can fire simultaneously when switching between two browser
windows.</li></ul><h2 id="mitigation">Mitigation</h2><h3 id="permissions">Permissions</h3><p><strong>Goal:</strong> Require informed consent from users.</p><p>There’s precedent for considering permissions<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a> to
be sufficient mitigation for similar issues. For example, the Media
Capture API specification includes the following:</p><blockquote><p>For origins to which permission has been granted, the devicechange
event will be emitted across browsing contexts and origins each time a
new media device is added or removed; user agents can mitigate the risk
of correlation of browsing activity across origins by fuzzing the timing
of these events.</p></blockquote><p style="text-align: right">
From §15 of<a href="https://w3c.github.io/mediacapture-main/#privacy-and-security-considerations">Media
Capture and Streams API</a> specification.</p><p><strong>Pros</strong></p><ul><li>Prevents drive-by fingerprinting.</li></ul><p><strong>Cons</strong></p><ul><li><p>UI for permissions don’t disclose the fact that all sites that
have been granted access to the same resource can synchronize
identifiers as a side-effect.</p></li><li><p>Doesn’t prevent identity joining once permission is
granted.</p></li></ul><h3 id="fuzzing-timing-of-events">Fuzzing Timing of Events</h3><p><strong>Goal</strong>: Deter correlation of events by injecting
timing skew.</p><p>Mentioned in the snippet above from the Media Capture and Streams API
and called out by Jeffrey Yasskin as a potential general mitigation in
“desynchronize whole-browser events” in<a href="https://github.com/whatwg/html/issues/5215">this issue</a> filed
against the WHATWG HTML specification.</p><p><strong>Pros</strong></p><ul><li>Lowers confidence of identity equivalence.</li></ul><p><strong>Cons</strong></p><ul><li><p>Precise timing may not be required. I.e. the lowered level of
confidence could still be sufficient for most uses.</p></li><li><p>Doesn’t address unique event streams.</p></li></ul><h3 id="first-party-restriction-for-apis">First-Party Restriction for
APIs</h3><p><strong>Goal</strong>: Deter identity correlation by third-party
sites.</p><p>Restrict APIs to the origin of the<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/browsers.html#top-level-browsing-context">top-level
browsing context</a>.</p><p>The latter may choose to explicitly delegate access to the APIs via<a href="https://w3c.github.io/webappsec-feature-policy/">feature
policies</a>. But third-party contexts can’t “reach across” browsing
contexts via correlation of cross context events or attributes that may
be made available by the API.</p><p><strong>Pros</strong></p><ul><li>Makes it a requirement that first-parties actively cooperate with
other first-parties or third-parties. I.e. Good first-party + bad
third-party = safe.</li></ul><p><strong>Cons</strong></p><ul><li><p>Difficult to retrofit into existing APIs.</p></li><li><p>Browser-wide events and attributes are still visible to distinct
top-level browsing contexts.</p></li><li><p>In practice top-level browsing contexts contain a fair amount of
third party scripts which may access the same APIs. Furthermore there
are financial incentives for first-parties to delegate API access to
third-parties.</p></li></ul><h3 id="limit-api-access-to-visible-browsing-contexts">Limit API Access
To Visible Browsing Contexts</h3><p><strong>Goal:</strong> Prevent background browsing contexts from
skimming identifiable events.</p><p>The Page Visibility API defines the<a href="https://w3c.github.io/page-visibility/#visibility-states">visibility
state of a document</a> as<code>visible</code> if the document is<em>“at least partially visible on at least one screen”</em>.</p><p>Restrict APIs to — possibly top-level — browsing context’s active
document.</p><p><strong>Pros</strong></p><ul><li>Is a convincing mitigation on mobile devices where only one
top-level document can be visible at the same time.</li></ul><p><strong>Cons</strong></p><ul><li><p>There could be multiple visible browsing contexts which still
leaves the door open for identity correlation across site
boundaries.</p></li><li><p>The fact that having more than one browsing context open at the
same time is a privacy risk is quite surprising for users.</p></li></ul><h3 id="limit-events-to-focused-top-level-browsing-context">Limit Events
To Focused Top-Level Browsing Context</h3><p><strong>Goal</strong>: Limit firing correlatable events to a single<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/browsers.html#top-level-browsing-context">top-level
browsing context</a>.</p><p>The HTML spec defines a concept of a<em><a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/interaction.html#currently-focused-area-of-a-top-level-browsing-context">currently
focused area of a top-level browsing context</a></em>. As defined, every
top level<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/browsers.html#browsing-context">browsing
context</a> has one regardless of visibility. A similar narrow concept
could be introduced that recognizes the top level browsing context that
has system input focus. There should be only one of these on a single
device.</p><p><em>Let’s call the top-level browsing context that has system input
focus as the</em><strong>focused top-level browsing
context</strong>.</p><p>New specifications could restrict browser-wide events to the focused
top-level browsing context.</p><p><strong>Pros</strong></p><ul><li>Likely fits in well with the intended usage model for most
APIs.</li></ul><p><strong>Cons</strong></p><ul><li>Does not address event stream fingerprinting via polling.</li></ul><h3 id="limit-api-access-to-focused-top-level-browsing-context">Limit
API Access To Focused Top-Level Browsing Context</h3><p><strong>Goal</strong>: Limit access to sensitive APIs to a single<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/browsers.html#top-level-browsing-context">top-level
browsing context</a>.</p><p>Similar to the above, but addresses issues around polling by
disallowing access to the entire API or sensitive attributes by
restricting the entire API instead of just events.</p><p><strong>Pros</strong></p><ul><li>Resilient to event stream fingerprinting via polling.</li></ul><p><strong>Cons</strong></p><ul><li><p>Can’t be easily retrofitted to existing APIs since it requires
defining behavior for “disabled” APIs.</p></li><li><p>May break critical use cases.</p></li></ul><h3 id="secure-context-restriction-and-control-via-feature-policy">Secure-Context
Restriction and Control via Feature-Policy</h3><p>These should be pretty standard at this point.</p><p><strong>Pros</strong></p><ul><li>Just makes sense.</li></ul><p><strong>Cons</strong></p><ul><li>Not sufficient by itself.</li></ul><h2 id="spotting-ephemeral-fingerprinting-surfaces-in-web-specs">Spotting
Ephemeral Fingerprinting Surfaces In Web Specs</h2><p><strong>Ephemeral fingerprints:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Require that multiple browsing contexts observe the same events
or access the same volatile attribute.</p></li><li><p>These browsing contexts could involve a single third party in
multiple first party contexts.</p></li><li><p>Does not require precise clocks nor agreement on the exact
timestamps of the observed events. Depending on the fingerprintable
surfaces involved the sequence of events could be identifiable by
itself. Servers can roughly bucket observations by time periods,
eliminating the need for client-side clocks.</p></li><li><p>Does not require an API to fire an event. A property with a
volatile value that can be polled periodically is sufficient.</p></li></ul><h3 id="what-to-look-for">What to look for:</h3><ul><li><p>Events with external triggers. E.g. hardware based
events.</p></li><li><p>Multiple distinct events that are fired in tandem to distinct
browsing contexts. E.g. any processing model where multiple events are
fired.</p></li><li><p>Volatile attributes that are visible across browsing
contexts.</p></li><li><p>Volatile attributes that don’t share values across browsing
contexts, but change simultaneously. E.g. Salting a volatile attribute
is insufficient if its mutations can be correlated.</p></li></ul><h3 id="example">Example</h3><p>Consider<code>onfocus</code> and<code>onblur</code> events.</p><p>The<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/interaction.html#focus-update-steps">focus
update steps</a> involve firing up to three distinct events:<code>change</code> if the node losing focus is an<code>input</code>
element,<code>focus</code>, and<code>blur</code>.</p><p>When focus traverses a browsing context boundary, these events may be
fired simultaneously to two different browsing contexts. Browsers
mitigate this by not firing<code>blur</code> for cross site tab
switches, but they still fire<code>blur</code> when the browser itself
goes out of focus. Thus identity can be correlated when switching
browser windows.</p><h4 id="possible-mitigation">Possible Mitigation</h4><p>When the<em>new chain</em> and the<em>old chain</em><a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a> are
in different top-level browsing contexts whose active documents are not
same-origin, queue but don’t fire<code>change</code> and<code>blur</code> events until focus returns to the old top-level
browsing context.</p><h3 id="notes">Notes</h3><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes"><hr/><ol><li id="fn1"><p>Van Goethem, T. and Joosen, W., 2017. One side-channel
to bring them all and in the darkness bind them: Associating isolated
browsing sessions. In<em>11th {USENIX} Workshop on Offensive
Technologies ({WOOT} 17)</em>. (<a href="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/5814/9610a57cb4626918bf003b8bad25e740b1f4.pdf">PDF</a>)<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn2"><p>Either via a legacy permissions prompt or explicitly
requiring the use of the<a href="https://w3c.github.io/permissions/">Permissions API</a> in the
spec for sensitive APIs.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li><li id="fn3"><p><em>New chain</em> and<em>old chain</em> are defined in<a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/interaction.html#focus-update-steps">focus
update steps</a>.<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li></ol></aside></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>