<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Career on Strong Opinions, Weekly Held</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/tags/career/</link><description>Recent content in Career on Strong Opinions, Weekly Held</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Asanka Herath</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 10:31:06 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://xn--izc.com/tags/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Solve a Problem in Three Steps</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/how-to-solve-a-problem-in-three-steps/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 21:09:29 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/how-to-solve-a-problem-in-three-steps/</guid><description>If you don’t know what a refridgerator is nor what an elephant is you
are likely to think that opening the door, putting the elephant in, and
closing the door is a viable strategy for putting an elephant in the
refridgerator.</description></item><item><title>Thirteen Years</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/thirteen-years/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 16:30:52 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/thirteen-years/</guid><description>Some reflections from thirteen years at Google.</description></item><item><title>Pillars And Governance Structures</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/pillars-are-governance-structures/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 20:18:23 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/pillars-are-governance-structures/</guid><description>Originally published on 2023 September 8. Revised 2023 November 12 with hopefully less rambling.
Re-orgs.
It’s a fact of life for large organizations. A popular metaphor making the rounds now is this concept of pillars. The metaphor makes sense to some extent.
A house without a foundation Let’s start with a picture of how a sanitized version of a pillar structure would look like.
A goal at the top and a bunch of pillars at the bottom.</description></item><item><title>The Point of a Strategy</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/the-point-of-a-strategy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2023 11:00:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/the-point-of-a-strategy/</guid><description>The only useful strategy is one that reduces risks.</description></item><item><title>Promise Fatigue</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/promise-fatigue/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:03:16 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/promise-fatigue/</guid><description>Setting low but realistic expectations is better than setting high
but unrealistic ones.</description></item><item><title>Sometimes It's the Interviewers Who Suck</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/sometimes-its-the-interviewers-who-suck/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 19:09:49 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/sometimes-its-the-interviewers-who-suck/</guid><description>I’ve done hundreds of interviews. I’ve also served in numerous hiring committees over the years.
Tech companies tend to have cultures built around tech people interviewing other tech people, typically in what is not-so-affectionately known as the “Tech interview.” This is good because candidates would be evaluated based on their actual skills instead of keywords in their resume. Interviewers are in effect choosing their future coworkers which makes in interview serve the interest of both the interviewer and the interviewee.</description></item><item><title>Ten Years</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/posts/ten-years/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 21:41:50 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/posts/ten-years/</guid><description>It’s been ten years since I started at Google. The work anniversary fell on 6th of December.
Ten years ago my wife and I made our way to Mountain View for my orientation; all excited for a brand new chapter in our lives. After spending a week in Mountain View / Palo Alto we both decided that California was not for us. But that’s beside the point.
I was elated. This was pretty much everything I dreamt of as a kid growing up in Sri Lanka.</description></item></channel></rss>