<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>engineering on Strong Opinions, Weekly Held</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/tags/engineering/</link><description>Recent content in engineering on Strong Opinions, Weekly Held</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Asanka Herath</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://xn--izc.com/tags/engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Code As UI: The UX of config-as-code and everything-as-code</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/code-as-ui/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/code-as-ui/</guid><description>Welcome to the UI review Your UX person comes up to you with the new mocks for the configuration UI. It looks like this:
A UI mock where all the labels are text boxes, and the values are also text boxes. The button just says “button”. You: What is this? Is this modern?
UX: That’s be beauty of it. The user can type in the label and type in the value.</description></item><item><title>Just Enough Technical Debt</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/just-the-right-amount/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/just-the-right-amount/</guid><description>Zero technical debt isn’t always the answer. Learn to look for the
point of diminishing returns.</description></item><item><title>The Loss of a Virtuous Culture</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/the-loss-of-a-virtuous-culture/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 17:13:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/the-loss-of-a-virtuous-culture/</guid><description>Luck isn’t enough. You need a culture of virtue.</description></item><item><title>The Lettergrade Rule</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/the-lettergrade-rule/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 20:27:57 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/the-lettergrade-rule/</guid><description>Don’t block a code review because of minor issues that are best left
to the discretion of the author.</description></item><item><title>DARPA's Heilmeier Catechism</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/darpa-heilmeier-catechism/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 10:11:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/darpa-heilmeier-catechism/</guid><description>A set of questions help you think through and evaluate proposed
projects and research programs.</description></item><item><title>Markdown should be readble without knowing Markdown</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/mark-goes-up-and-down/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 13:02:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/mark-goes-up-and-down/</guid><description>Markdown started out as a way to write text files that could also be machine parsed and rendered into a higher fidelity format.
To quote from the Philosophy:
Readability, however, is emphasized above all else. A Markdown-formatted document should be publishable as-is, as plain text, without looking like it’s been marked up with tags or formatting instructions.
This particular aspect of the format wasn’t maintained very well. Immediately following the “Philosophy” section is “Inline HTML” which contradicts the “without looking like it’s been marked up” requirement.</description></item><item><title>On Highlighting Syntax vs. Semantics</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/syntax-highlighting/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/syntax-highlighting/</guid><description>Takes a look at an alternate form of code highlighting based on core
semantics instead of syntactic role.</description></item><item><title>On WontFixing Bugs</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/on-wontfixing-bugs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2021 17:15:06 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/on-wontfixing-bugs/</guid><description>&lt;p>Large projects accumulate a large number of issue reports over time.
This is normal. Typically for a “successful” project the rate of new
issues being reported will exceed the rate of issues being fixed. Hence
the growth.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But what are they to do about this ever-growing pile of bugs?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Visualizing Internet Users</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/visualizing-people/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 11:37:53 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/visualizing-people/</guid><description>What does 0.3%1 of internet users look like?
As of this writing the global population hovers around 7.7 billion according to the World Population Clock 2.
Screenshot from census.gov showing the world population clock. The International Telecommunications Union “estimates that at the end of 2019, 53.6 per cent of the global population, or 4.1 billion people, are using the internet.”3
Screenshot from itu.int showing historical internet usage numbers as a percentage of the world population So a 0.</description></item><item><title>Names for Name Conventions</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/symbol-name-types/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 12:32:45 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/symbol-name-types/</guid><description>Names I’ve seen used to refer to naming conventions:
snake_case, hacker_case, unix_hacker_style : Everything is lower case, though exceptions exist. E.g. HTTP_foo_bar. SCREAMING_SNAKE_CASE : Usually reserved for macros and constants. camelCase : The first letter is lowercase. PascalCase : The first letter is uppercase. kabob-case : Like snake_case, but uses dashes instead of underscores. Common for command-line options1, CSS styles, commands (e.g. git-receive-pack). While looking idly looking for details on this, I stumbled on this Medium post which is relevant.</description></item></channel></rss>