<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on Asanka Herath</title><link>https://asankah.github.io/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on Asanka Herath</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://asankah.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A new way to work with Ansible on the command line</title><link>https://asankah.github.io/blog/ansible-cli-sugar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://asankah.github.io/blog/ansible-cli-sugar/</guid><description>This article is about using Ansible on the command-line.
Problem: You &amp;hellip;
&amp;hellip; want a convenient way to do ad-hoc tasks on a bunch of machines.
&amp;hellip; already have a few playbooks and machine groups defined in your inventory.
&amp;hellip; don&amp;rsquo;t want to invest too much into Ansible because you have other things to do and Ansible is just a tool to deal with one aspect of what you want to do.</description></item><item><title>Identity Domains</title><link>https://asankah.github.io/blog/identity-domains/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://asankah.github.io/blog/identity-domains/</guid><description>Above is a diagram showing relationships between clusters of documents and identity domains. foo.example and baz.example belong to the same first party set. a.example has no first-party relationship with any other domain.
An Identity domain is a scope within which we consider it a given that the user has a shared or trivially joinable identity.
The “Identity domain” has the following properties:
All active documents in descendent browsing contexts belong to the same identity domain as the active document in the top-level browsing context.</description></item><item><title>Ephemeral Fingerprinting On The Web</title><link>https://asankah.github.io/blog/ephemeral-fingerprinting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://asankah.github.io/blog/ephemeral-fingerprinting/</guid><description>Background TL;DR:
Any ephemeral low-entropy web observable property whose changes are concurrently observable by multiple sites can lead to cross site identity joining.
This method of identity joining does not require coordination between multiple first parties. A single third party embedded within multiple first parties can also use this method.
Example 1: Two sites observe a sequence of device orientation changes at times 𝒕₀, 𝒕₁,𝒕₂.</description></item></channel></rss>