<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on Strong Opinions, Weakly Held</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on Strong Opinions, Weakly Held</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Asanka Herath</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 11:37:53 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://xn--izc.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Visualizing Internet Users</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/visualizing-people/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 11:37:53 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/visualizing-people/</guid><description>What does 0.3%1 of internet users look like?
As of this writing the global population hovers around 7.7 billion according to the World Population Clock.2
Screenshot from census.gov showing the world population clock. The International Telecommunications Union “estimates that at the end of 2019, 53.6 per cent of the global population, or 4.1 billion people, are using the internet.”3
Screenshot from itu.int showing historical internet usage numbers as a percentage of the world population So a 0.</description></item><item><title>Things You Can Do With Neovim and Vscode That You Can't Do With Neovim Alone</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/things-you-can-do-with-nvim-and-vscode/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/things-you-can-do-with-nvim-and-vscode/</guid><description>This is the third time I’ve tried in earnest to switch to VSCode from Vim (or Neovim in my case) for reasons not all of which are relevant to this post. But I love Vim style modal editing and I’ve grown accustomed to some features that aren’t present or not well emulated in VSCodeVim.
Enter VSCode Neovim. I was intrigued by their claim to integrate Neovim instead of trying to emulate Vim.</description></item><item><title>Why 'Strong Opinions Weakly Held'</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/why-strong-opinions-weakly-held/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 15:17:16 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/why-strong-opinions-weakly-held/</guid><description>Origins of the phrase The title of this blog is Strong Opinions, Weakly Held. The same concept shows up elsewhere are Strong Opinions Loosely Held. An eponymous essay by Paul Saffo in [1] introduced the world to this concept.
In his essay – which isn’t very long if you would like to read the whole thing yourself – he lays out the concept as follows:
I have found that the fastest way to an effective forecast is often through a sequence of lousy forecasts.</description></item><item><title>Names for Name Conventions</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/symbol-name-types/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 12:32:45 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/symbol-name-types/</guid><description>Names I’ve seen used to refer to naming conventions:
snake_case, hacker_case, unix_hacker_style : Everything is lower case, though exceptions exist. E.g. HTTP_foo_bar. SCREAMING_SNAKE_CASE : Usually reserved for macros and constants. camelCase : The first letter is lowercase. PascalCase : The first letter is uppercase. kabob-case : Like snake_case, but uses dashes instead of underscores. Common for command-line options1, CSS styles, commands (e.g. git-receive-pack). While looking idly looking for details on this, I stumbled on this Medium post which is relevant.</description></item><item><title>How This Blog Works</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/how-this-blog-works/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:57:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/how-this-blog-works/</guid><description>How I put this site together and why.</description></item><item><title>The Comcast Technician Problem</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/comcast-technican-problem/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 13:21:51 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/comcast-technican-problem/</guid><description>Given a set of tasks, incentives are often aligned towards dropping a task rather than allowing for perpetual accretion of delays.</description></item><item><title>Vim: Use Drop Not Edit, SBuffer Not Buffer</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/use-drop-not-edit/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 12:02:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/use-drop-not-edit/</guid><description>I’m going to assume you are a Vim user.
Say you have a several windows open in Vim and you want to edit another file. Using :edit works if you want to open the file in the current window unconditionally.
But that’s often not what you want. If you have the same file open in another window, then the most efficient and least disruptive thing to do is to switch to that window.</description></item><item><title>Notes from Crash Course's Videos on Fact Checking Information You See On The Internet</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/notes-on-fact-checking/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/notes-on-fact-checking/</guid><description>Hank Green’s Crash Course YouTube channel has an excellent series about navigating digital information. It’s an excellent guide to how internet users could intelligently consume information they see on the internet. These are my (incomplete) notes from the series.</description></item><item><title>Easier CLI for ad-hoc Ansible tasks and playbooks</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ansible-cli-sugar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ansible-cli-sugar/</guid><description>Encode the host and group names into the name of a wrapper script for quick ad-hoc invocation of Ansible tasks and playbooks.</description></item><item><title>Identity Domains</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/identity-domains/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/identity-domains/</guid><description>An Identity Domain is a scope within which we assume that the user’s identity can roam freely.</description></item><item><title>Ephemeral Fingerprinting On The Web</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ephemeral-fingerprinting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ephemeral-fingerprinting/</guid><description>&lt;p>Any ephemeral low-entropy web observable property whose changes are concurrently observable by multiple sites can lead to cross site identity joining.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This method of identity joining does not require coordination between multiple first parties. A single third party embedded within multiple first parties can also use this method.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>