<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on Strong Opinions, Weekly Held</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on Strong Opinions, Weekly Held</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Asanka Herath</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 16:15:23 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://xn--izc.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Use Git hooks to automatically push after every commit</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/git-autopush/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 16:15:23 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/git-autopush/</guid><description>During before and after various Git operations, Git invokes special
hooks that can be used execute custom scripts. This article explains how
to use them to automatically push to an upstream repository every time
you make a commit to a local repo.</description></item><item><title>DARPA's Heilmeier Catechism</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/darpa-heilmeier-catechism/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 10:11:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/darpa-heilmeier-catechism/</guid><description>A set of questions help you think through and evaluate proposed
projects and research programs.</description></item><item><title>Markdown should be readble without knowing Markdown</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/mark-goes-up-and-down/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 13:02:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/mark-goes-up-and-down/</guid><description>Markdown started out as a way to write text files that could also be machine parsed and rendered into a higher fidelity format.
To quote from the Philosophy:
Readability, however, is emphasized above all else. A Markdown-formatted document should be publishable as-is, as plain text, without looking like it’s been marked up with tags or formatting instructions.
This particular aspect of the format wasn’t maintained very well. Immediately following the “Philosophy” section is “Inline HTML” which contradicts the “without looking like it’s been marked up” requirement.</description></item><item><title>On Gender Gap in Adolescent Mental Health</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/gender-gap-in-adolescent-mental-health/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 14:51:34 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/gender-gap-in-adolescent-mental-health/</guid><description>A recent study found that more gender-equal countries have larger
gender gaps in mental health. I look at the data that seems to have
yielded this counter-intuitive results and find it lacking.</description></item><item><title>On Highlighting Syntax vs. Semantics</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/syntax-highlighting/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/syntax-highlighting/</guid><description>Takes a look at an alternate form of code highlighting based on core
semantics instead of syntactic role.</description></item><item><title>Inktober - Stripes</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/inktober-stripes/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 17:20:38 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/inktober-stripes/</guid><description>“Stripes” - A bee wearing an incorrectly striped sweater For Inktober 52.</description></item><item><title>Inktober - Wild</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/inktober-wild/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 15:35:39 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/inktober-wild/</guid><description>“Wild” - Caught in the wild For Inktober 52.</description></item><item><title>Inktober - Decay</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/inktober-decay/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 15:21:37 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/inktober-decay/</guid><description>“Decay” - I was kind of going for tooth-decay caused by tiny little gremlins. For Inktober 52.</description></item><item><title>Quickly grab a snapshot of your reMarkable tablet</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/grab-diagram-workflow-re2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/grab-diagram-workflow-re2/</guid><description>How to bind a hotkey to grab a snapshot of your reMarkable display
and copy it to the clipboard on a Mac.</description></item><item><title>Note-taking on a reMarkable 2</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/remarkable-first-impressions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 16:10:30 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/remarkable-first-impressions/</guid><description>Sentiments after using the reMarkable 2 tablet for a month.</description></item><item><title>Why 'Strong Opinions Weekly Held'</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/why-strong-opinions-weekly-held/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/why-strong-opinions-weekly-held/</guid><description>Previously on this blog I wrote a short note on Why Strong Opinions Weakly Held.
I’m trying to get something out every week. Hence the new blog title.</description></item><item><title>Visualizing A Million People</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/visualizing-people-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/visualizing-people-2/</guid><description>If your feature pisses off a million people what does this angry mob
look like? Spoiler: We only get to 750,000.</description></item><item><title>Fart Limit</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/fart-limit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 11:30:18 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/fart-limit/</guid><description>Can a fart be fatal? Let’s see what science and OSHA have to say.</description></item><item><title>Shannon Paper</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/shannon-paper/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 16:14:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/shannon-paper/</guid><description>Claude Shannon’s &lt;em>A mathematical theory of communication&lt;/em> is
an oft cited classic in information theory. Let’s dive in and try to
tease apart the “why”s that are often overlooked when people build on
top of the introduced theory. They are definitely things that I didn’t
consider to be obvious without the benefit of reading the paper.</description></item><item><title>Sometimes It's the Interviewers Who Suck</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/sometimes-its-the-interviewers-who-suck/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 19:09:49 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/sometimes-its-the-interviewers-who-suck/</guid><description>I’ve done hundreds of interviews. I’ve also served in numerous hiring committees over the years.
Tech companies tend to have cultures built around tech people interviewing other tech people, typically in what is not-so-affectionately known as the “Tech interview.” This is good because candidates would be evaluated based on their actual skills instead of keywords in their resume. Interviewers are in effect choosing their future coworkers which makes in interview serve the interest of both the interviewer and the interviewee.</description></item><item><title>On WontFixing Bugs</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/on-wontfixing-bugs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2021 17:15:06 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/on-wontfixing-bugs/</guid><description>&lt;p>Large projects accumulate a large number of issue reports over time.
This is normal. Typically for a “successful” project the rate of new
issues being reported will exceed the rate of issues being fixed. Hence
the growth.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But what are they to do about this ever-growing pile of bugs?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Deriving the Poisson Distribution</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/poisson-distribution/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 11:13:39 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/poisson-distribution/</guid><description>Where does the Poisson Distribution come from?
A little bit of research1 tells us that the distribution was originally introduced by Abraham de Moivre in 1710 in an article called “On the Measurement of Chance, or, on the Probability of Events in Games Depending Upon Fortuitous Chance” 2 (not the original title).
A few steps that will get us there is laid out below.
Let’s start with a simple “rate” problem.</description></item><item><title>Ten Years</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ten-years/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 21:41:50 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ten-years/</guid><description>It’s been ten years since I started at Google. The work anniversary fell on 6th of December.
Ten years ago my wife and I made our way to Mountain View for my orientation; all excited for a brand new chapter in our lives. After spending a week in Mountain View / Palo Alto we both decided that California was not for us. But that’s beside the point.
I was elated. This was pretty much everything I dreamt of as a kid growing up in Sri Lanka.</description></item><item><title>Visualizing Internet Users</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/visualizing-people/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 11:37:53 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/visualizing-people/</guid><description>What does 0.3%1 of internet users look like?
As of this writing the global population hovers around 7.7 billion according to the World Population Clock 2.
Screenshot from census.gov showing the world population clock. The International Telecommunications Union “estimates that at the end of 2019, 53.6 per cent of the global population, or 4.1 billion people, are using the internet.”3
Screenshot from itu.int showing historical internet usage numbers as a percentage of the world population So a 0.</description></item><item><title>Things You Can Do With Neovim and Vscode That You Can't Do With Neovim Alone</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/things-you-can-do-with-nvim-and-vscode/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/things-you-can-do-with-nvim-and-vscode/</guid><description>This is the third time I’ve tried in earnest to switch to VSCode from Vim (or Neovim in my case) for reasons not all of which are relevant to this post. But I love Vim style modal editing and I’ve grown accustomed to some features that aren’t present or not well emulated in VSCodeVim.
Enter VSCode Neovim. I was intrigued by their claim to integrate Neovim instead of trying to emulate Vim.</description></item><item><title>Why 'Strong Opinions Weakly Held'</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/why-strong-opinions-weakly-held/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 15:17:16 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/why-strong-opinions-weakly-held/</guid><description>Origins of the phrase The title of this blog is Strong Opinions, Weakly Held. The same concept shows up elsewhere are Strong Opinions Loosely Held. An eponymous essay by Paul Saffo in [1] introduced the world to this concept.
In his essay – which isn’t very long if you would like to read the whole thing yourself – he lays out the concept as follows:
I have found that the fastest way to an effective forecast is often through a sequence of lousy forecasts.</description></item><item><title>Names for Name Conventions</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/symbol-name-types/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 12:32:45 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/symbol-name-types/</guid><description>Names I’ve seen used to refer to naming conventions:
snake_case, hacker_case, unix_hacker_style : Everything is lower case, though exceptions exist. E.g. HTTP_foo_bar. SCREAMING_SNAKE_CASE : Usually reserved for macros and constants. camelCase : The first letter is lowercase. PascalCase : The first letter is uppercase. kabob-case : Like snake_case, but uses dashes instead of underscores. Common for command-line options1, CSS styles, commands (e.g. git-receive-pack). While looking idly looking for details on this, I stumbled on this Medium post which is relevant.</description></item><item><title>How This Blog Works</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/how-this-blog-works/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:57:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/how-this-blog-works/</guid><description>How I put this site together and why.</description></item><item><title>The Comcast Technician Problem</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/comcast-technican-problem/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 13:21:51 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/comcast-technican-problem/</guid><description>Given a set of tasks, incentives are often aligned towards dropping a
task rather than allowing for perpetual accretion of delays.</description></item><item><title>Vim: Use Drop Not Edit, SBuffer Not Buffer</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/use-drop-not-edit/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 12:02:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/use-drop-not-edit/</guid><description>I’m going to assume you are a Vim user.
Say you have a several windows open in Vim and you want to edit another file. Using :edit works if you want to open the file in the current window unconditionally.
But that’s often not what you want. If you have the same file open in another window, then the most efficient and least disruptive thing to do is to switch to that window.</description></item><item><title>Notes from Crash Course's Videos on Fact Checking Information You See On The Internet</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/notes-on-fact-checking/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/notes-on-fact-checking/</guid><description>Hank Green’s Crash Course YouTube channel has an excellent series
about navigating digital information. It’s an excellent guide to how
internet users could intelligently consume information they see on the
internet. These are my (incomplete) notes from the series.</description></item><item><title>Easier CLI for ad-hoc Ansible tasks and playbooks</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ansible-cli-sugar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ansible-cli-sugar/</guid><description>Encode the host and group names into the name of a wrapper script for
quick ad-hoc invocation of Ansible tasks and playbooks.</description></item><item><title>Identity Domains</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/identity-domains/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/identity-domains/</guid><description>An Identity Domain is a scope within which we assume that the user’s
identity can roam freely.</description></item><item><title>Ephemeral Fingerprinting On The Web</title><link>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ephemeral-fingerprinting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xn--izc.com/blog/ephemeral-fingerprinting/</guid><description>&lt;p>Any ephemeral low-entropy web observable property whose changes are
concurrently observable by multiple sites can lead to cross site
identity joining.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This method of identity joining does not require coordination between
multiple first parties. A single third party embedded within multiple
first parties can also use this method.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>