<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://xn--izc.com/">
  <title>The Letter අ</title>
  <subtitle>Strong opinions weekly held</subtitle>
  <link href="https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://xn--izc.com/" />
  <updated>
    2025-09-27T00:00:00Z
  </updated>
  <id>https://xn--izc.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Asanka Herath</name>
    <email>asanka@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
    <entry>
      <title>Incentives</title>
      <link href="https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/incentives/" />
      <updated>2025-08-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/incentives/</id>
      <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
        &lt;div class=&quot;sidenote-host-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams can fail in many ways&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/incentives/#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. But when they succeed,
the most critical roles are those that form the communication structures
within and across teams. Forming these structures require teammates to
have some level of autonomy. In turn this requires a team stucture that
allows the team the freedom of movement to reconfigure itself to serve
the teams’ goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;aside class=&quot;sidenote-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;no-heros&quot;&gt;No Heros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any organization whose success depends on their employees working
&lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; their own self interests will eventually fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately incentives are seldom constructed by those who
understand what organizational cross beams are necessary to keep the
&lt;em&gt;“official”&lt;/em&gt; organizational structure from collapsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://sre.google/resources/practices-and-processes/no-heroes/&quot;&gt;Why
Heroism Is Bad&lt;/a&gt; in the Google SRE site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the conditions are right, a healthy team will fill in the gaps by
rebalancing their responsibilities. Such a rebalancing will inevitably
lead to an uneven distribution of burden. With time the burden will
become increasingly visceral, which will lead to burnout, resentment,
and attrition. For an uneven burden to be sustained, that burden must be
commesurately rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accurately measuring the contributions of each team member is a
hitherto unsolved problem. Managers are often left with gut instincts to
fall back on, which comes with a laundry list of shortcomings like bias
and favoritism. Those who come up with the right formula against all
odds are celebrated as &lt;em&gt;good managers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People write books and give speeches about their favorite &lt;em&gt;good
manager&lt;/em&gt;. But often the actual skills involved aren’t articulated.
The list of skills isn’t long. Primarily these skills revolve around the
ability to understand what each person is &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt;. Secondairly
they revolve around the ability to understand how those actions
&lt;em&gt;affect the rest of the team&lt;/em&gt;. Both require a manager to have
visibility into how the team interacts – either by direct observation or
by frequent and extensive communication with each team member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this still won’t do much if the team desn’t have psychological
safety. Without this, team members may not be willing to recognize and
reward their peers. Nor would they be liklely to disclose bad news in a
timely manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad incentive structures lead to people ridigly performing just their
roles and letting things fail around them (&lt;em&gt;“it’s not my
job”&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/incentives/#fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, good things happen when the incentives for a team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never pit employees against each other. One person’s success cannot
be another’s downfall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assume that the leadership hasn’t figured out exactly what needs to
be done. The team should be empowered to course-correct as they
learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward those who pull the team together and help the team
communicate internally and externally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;footnotes&quot; class=&quot;footnotes footnotes-end-of-document&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Five_Dysfunctions_of_a_Team&quot;&gt;The
Five Dysfunctions of a Team&lt;/a&gt; for a nice run through of different ways
in which teams fail to function.&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/incentives/#fnref1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-back&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/posts/intrinsic-motivation-an-anecdote/&quot;&gt;Intrinsic and Extrinsic
Motivation: An Anecdote&lt;/a&gt; for an example of what happens when people
try to force this process purely by creating extrinsic incentives and
assigned roles.&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/incentives/#fnref2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-back&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;

      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Ode to Glue People</title>
      <link href="https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/glue-people/" />
      <updated>2025-08-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/glue-people/</id>
      <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
        &lt;div class=&quot;sidenote-host-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of glue work isn’t new. Team building, mentoring, running
meetings, and many other mundane tasks fall under this category of often
uncompensated work. How glue work establishes unofficial communication
structures within and across teams is, however, discussed less
often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not every manager is a great communicator; and that’s okay. This is
specially true in large tech companies where the people management
ladders are the natural next step for individual contributors who are
seeking career growth. When important information that affects people’s
careers isn’t communicated in a fair and timely manner, trust collapses
taking down the team with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bound by needs for confidentiality and mandatory reporting, managers
are often not the best people to confide in or trust. Meanwhile peers
with the right set of social skills become speakeasies: people with whom
others feel psychologically safe. The level of trust between a speakeasy
and other team members can be much higher than with managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, these speakeasies become social hubs where both work
and non-work related information flow freely. Some might call it gossip.
But when the information is factual and timely, it can help teammates
made better decisions, at least for themselves if not for the company.
In times of turmoil – like the increasingly frequent
&lt;em&gt;“once-in-a-lifetime”&lt;/em&gt; recessions that keep happening in the US –
the glue people take on a dual role: as a pressure release valve for
individuals, and as a vehicle for breaking their sense of isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No surprise that such roles cannot be written down in a normal job
description. Also of no surprise that such roles aren’t recognized nor
compensated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class=&quot;sidenote-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;losing-glue&quot;&gt;Losing Glue&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was tempted to write about this after the departure of a coworker.
The extent to which they were holding the team together was not apparent
until they left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our team is spread out across many geographic regions, so pretty much
all of our interactions are online. Our team chats are more than just
sources of work information, they are also where most of the
socialization happens. So the tone and spirit of communication is
critical for engagement. Once the keeper of the spirit left, the chats
fell silent. And suddenly, it seemed, we became strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Soft Roles as Organizational Cross Beams</title>
      <link href="https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/crossbeams/" />
      <updated>2025-08-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/crossbeams/</id>
      <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
        &lt;div class=&quot;sidenote-host-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the obvious team scoped function of soft roles, they also
perform important functions at the organizational level. Of these two
common types are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Glue-people&lt;/strong&gt; who are necessary to tie teams
together, build cohesion, connect the dots between silos that are not
effectively communicating with each other, and establish an unofficial
foundation of trust that prevent teams from collapsing when the trust
between leadership and their underlings inevitably crumbles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immune Systems&lt;/strong&gt; are the people necessary to stop
the company from shooting themselves in their corporate feet. These are
the people who internally oppose measures that would cause widespread
collapse of user-trust, violate privacy policies, open up the
organization to litigation, irreversibly misuse customer data,
unnecessarily jeopardize the operational stability or security of
critical systems, or commit war crimes and human rights
violations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;aside class=&quot;sidenote-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;individual-failure-vs.-organizational-failures&quot;&gt;Individual
Failure vs. Organizational Failures&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately all the lessons we learn about human fallibility tend
to be forgotten the higher up the reporting chain we go. So even though
we expect and build in mechanisms to deal with individual failures, we
tend not to build mechanisms to deal with organizational failures. We
assume that organizations fail less often than individuals. The opposite
is true. Organizations are made up of people. The more people you have
the more likely it is that one of them will fail. The more people you
have the more likely it is that they will fail in a way that is
catastrophic to the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Emergence of Soft Roles</title>
      <link href="https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/" />
      <updated>2025-08-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/</id>
      <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Google’s early success is partly attributed to the use of commodity
hardware that were expected to break occasionally. Rather than demanding
perfection from complex systems it is far more effective to expect and
design around imperfections&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/google-servers.jpg&quot; class=&quot;noinvert&quot; alt=&quot;By Erik Pitti from San Diego, CA, USA - Google’s First ServerUploaded by Mewtu, CC BY 2.0, Link&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;By
&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; class=&quot;external text&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/people/24205142@N00&quot;&gt;Erik
Pitti&lt;/a&gt; from San Diego, CA, USA -
&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; class=&quot;external text&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/24205142@N00/2370851677/&quot;&gt;Google’s
First Server&lt;/a&gt;Uploaded by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=User:Mewtu&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1&quot; class=&quot;new&quot; title=&quot;User:Mewtu (page does not exist)&quot;&gt;Mewtu&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0&quot; title=&quot;Creative Commons Attribution 2.0&quot;&gt;CC
BY 2.0&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=8724999&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sidenote-host-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly when we design products, we design them for fallible users
who are prone to making occasional mistakes, and beholden to some number
of misconceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;aside class=&quot;sidenote-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;misconceptions&quot;&gt;Misconceptions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;misconceptions&lt;/em&gt; referred to here are misunderstandings of
how the product or process works. It could be situational
misunderstandings (e.g. confusion about how to accomplish an immediate
goal), or it could be a more persistent fundamental misunderstanding
about how something works (e.g. misunderstanding &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/common-myths-about-private-browsing&quot;&gt;how
private browsing works&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With real world problems, information flow is never perfect. Loss of
precision at each stage of discovery, analysis, prototyping, and
implementation leads to potential for misconceptions. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/posts/secret-life-of-systems/&quot;&gt;The Secret Life of Systems&lt;/a&gt; for
an illustration of how real world problems and the implementation of a
solution may not align.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we design products, so we must design our internal processes. We
once again assume that our teammates are fallible, prone to making
occasional mistakes, and operating under some number of misconceptions&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/#fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fallibility runs both ways up and down the org chart. Leaders operate
under vague, incomplete, and sometimes wildly inaccurate information&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/#fn3&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot; id=&quot;fnref3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Further complicating matters, it is
impossible to understand the capabilities and shortcomings of each
individual person or understand every nuance of what must constitute a
role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that team roles are neither comprehensive nor precise.
In any given team structure people are expected to adapt to a broad
range of situations that are unpredictable, and frankly unknowable. Some
(most?) of those situations are directly due to other team members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As teams mature, the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; role each person takes on will
gradually anneal around individual strengths and weaknesses forged by
need and cemented through consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in reality, what is intended to be a neat and well circumscribed
role profile becomes irregular, illdefined, and dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;horizontal&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/hierarchical.svg&quot; title=&quot;A neat organization chart.&quot; class=&quot;noinvert&quot; alt=&quot;Expectation: Neatly circumscribed hierarchichal roles.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;Expectation: Neatly circumscribed
hierarchichal roles.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/chaotic.svg&quot; title=&quot;A bunch of soft irregular shapes are squished together.&quot; class=&quot;noinvert&quot; alt=&quot;Reality: Smeared, lopsided, and chaotic roles.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;Reality: Smeared, lopsided, and chaotic
roles.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: Following the spirit of designing with imperfections, team
organization must always account for this fluidity of roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roles in a team will rarely be circumscribed by the corresponding
job description. People will always do work outside their scope.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roles will overlap in ways that will run counter to the intents of
the official role allocations. People will do other’s work
occasionally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roles will emerge that are not mentioned in anyone’s job
description.&lt;/em&gt; Sometimes called &lt;em&gt;soft&lt;/em&gt; roles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this series we will look at a few of these soft roles that emerge
often and look into the critical work that these roles perform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;footnotes&quot; class=&quot;footnotes footnotes-end-of-document&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A former Googler, Avery Penwarr wrote an influential
document while they were at Google called &lt;em&gt;View from Above&lt;/em&gt; about
the perspective of executives. Fortunately he also wrote a public
version called &lt;a href=&quot;https://apenwarr.ca/log/?m=201909&quot;&gt;What do
executives do anyway?&lt;/a&gt;. The basic premise is that when it comes to
any big decision, the executive highest up the ladder is the least
informed about the pertinent details – but that’s okay because knowing
the details isn’t their job.&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/#fnref1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-back&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://sre.google/sre-book/postmortem-culture/&quot;&gt;Postmortem
Culture: Learning from Failure&lt;/a&gt; for how anticipating mistakes lends
itself to a healthy culture where people proactively report and learn
from mistakes.&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/#fnref2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-back&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A former Googler, Avery Penwarr wrote an influential
document while they were at Google called &lt;em&gt;View from Above&lt;/em&gt; about
the perspective of executives. Fortunately he also wrote a public
version called &lt;a href=&quot;https://apenwarr.ca/log/?m=201909&quot;&gt;What do
executives do anyway?&lt;/a&gt;. The basic premise is that when it comes to
any big decision, the executive highest up the ladder is the least
informed about the pertinent details – but that’s okay because knowing
the details isn’t their job.&lt;a href=&quot;https://xn--izc.com/series/unsung-team-roles/emergence/#fnref3&quot; class=&quot;footnote-back&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;

      </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
